<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-26T04:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CTWG</title><subtitle>A website for collective self-clarification without consolation </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Précis of Mannheim’s Ideology and Utopia</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Mannheim/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Précis of Mannheim’s Ideology and Utopia"/><published>2024-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Mannheim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Mannheim/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post12-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post12-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post12-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post12.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>While Horkheimer’s paper in the <em>ZfS</em> provides a decent overview of Mannheim’s position, it is sparse and focused mainly on points of disagreement rather than providing a full overview of Mannheim’s thought. This appendix aims to rectify this. One may wonder why it appears here, given that Mannheim was never a member of the <em>Institut für Sozialforschung</em> and his influence on the members of the IfS was distant at best. There are a few reasons to focus on Mannheim. First, as Mannheim was a faculty member at the University of Frankfurt, his influence on German academia as a whole was rather large during the heyday of the IfS. Consequently, Mannheim’s influence is in the cultural aether and is a partially positive, and partially negative, touchstone for the Frankfurt School, even (implicitly and certainly far from uncritically) in the “temporal core of truth”<d-footnote>Horkheimer and Adorno, *Dialectic of Enlightenment*, xi.</d-footnote> which Adorno and Horkheimer reference in the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em>. Second, to appreciate Horkheimer’s conception of ideology, especially during his time as the director of the <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em>, one must be at least somewhat acquainted with Mannheim’s conception of ideology to fully understand Horkheimer’s critique thereof. Third, both Mannheim and early Critical Theory positioned themselves between Kant and Hegel, though in different ways. It is therefore instructive to show how Mannheim’s intervention between the two is suboptimal compared to the more illuminating version that the Frankfurt School provides. To that end, this blog post serves both as a brief introduction to Mannheim’s thought as a means to understanding the intellectual milieu to which Horkheimer responds.</p> <p>As an aside, I believe Kant to be the most prevalent influence on Mannheim’s thought. I therefore use verbiage associated with Kant (especially “categories” and “dogmatism,” “skepticism,” and “criticism”) that Mannheim often does not explicitly use, though leaves implicit for the astute reader to abduce.</p> <p>To appreciate Horkheimer’s critique of Mannheim, one must first sketch out a few general points that Mannheim underlines time and again in the book. The book’s subtitle, <em>An Introduction to the Sociology of Knowledge</em>, provides us with Mannheim’s aim: to explain how <em>real</em> people (contra philosophers) think.<d-footnote> Mannheim, *Ideology and Utopia*, 1.</d-footnote> Just as one’s language is not only one’s own, but shaped by the society one is in, so too do social forces shape one’s thought. Hence, Mannheim abandons the high ground of “thought as such”<d-footnote>Ibid., 2.</d-footnote> to examine thought in specific concrete situations. This implies that one must engage in an analysis at the level of the group rather than the individual, since not only do people live together, but they also <em>think</em> together. Attempting to sever thought from the historical circumstances which give rise to it is to render it impotent and incapable of action.<d-footnote>Ibid., 3.</d-footnote> To explain real people’s thought processes is to also explain their behavior. Though this framework may seem to militate against scientific objectivity, Mannheim thinks it both possible and desirable to achieve a sort of objectivity in sociological analysis <em>if</em> the investigator makes explicit the unconscious biases which catalyze the investigation and shape its general course.<d-footnote> Ibid., 5.</d-footnote></p> <p>Mannheim distinguishes the “sociology of knowledge” from <em>ideology</em>. For Mannheim, “ideology” can denote two related things: either a “particular conception of ideology”<d-footnote>Ibid., 49.</d-footnote> that refers to a specific belief or assertion, and the “total conception of ideology”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> which refers to a total <em>Weltanschauung</em> that a given group adopts. Invocations of both types of ideological conceptions require the invoker to not take their interlocutor’s claims at face value. Yet one crucial difference is that <em>particular</em> conceptions of ideology leave open the possibility of a common epistemic framework with which to resolve the dispute. Differences between <em>total</em> conceptions of ideology, however, involve categorical differences which preclude such a common framework. <d-footnote>Ibid., 51.</d-footnote> Thus, invocations of <em>particular</em> ideological beliefs are claims about an interlocutor’s psychology, while differences in total conceptions of ideology are structural in nature, due to “a correspondence between a given social situation and a given perspective.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Moreover, the totalizing element of total conceptions of ideology mean that even a flesh and blood “bearer of ideology”<d-footnote>Ibid., 52.</d-footnote> only participates in “certain fragments of this thought-system.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Not even aggregating the individual fragments can get us a complete mosaic. Thus, analyzing individual particular ideologies may only get us specific (and possibly idiosyncratic) psychological states of the bearers and <em>not</em> the <em>total</em> ideology as such, which requires the investigator to reconstruct “the systematic theoretical basis underlying the single judgements of the individual.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Even aggregating the psychological states of individual ideological bearers does not get us a complete picture of the total conception of ideology, which requires us to “know […] the theoretical implications of my mode of thought which are identical with those of my fellow members of the group.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 53.</d-footnote></p> <p>Just as Mannheim distinguishes between the particular and total conceptions of ideology, so too does he claim that these two concepts arise out of different historical developments. While distrust toward others is commonplace, what distinguishes claims that others are in the grasp of an ideology can only develop when distrust “becomes explicit and is methodically recognized.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 54.</d-footnote> Ideological claims are not intended to deceive; they are a midpoint between “a simple lie at one pole, and an error […] at the other.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> A particular ideological belief is the result of an unintentional psychological distortion that follows “inevitably and unwittingly from certain causal determinants.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> For this reason, the task of a sociologist of knowledge is <em>not</em> to resent those who make ideological claims, but to uncover the social forces which give rise to them. Mannheim then traces the concept of ideology along a tenuous historical development from Bacon to Machiavelli and finally Hume. From the former, Mannheim sees the origin of the claim that society and tradition may lead us to error (though he thinks that Bacon’s concept of the <em>idola</em> is far from the modern conception of ideology).<d-footnote>Ibid., 55.</d-footnote> From Machiavelli one can see that our awareness of ideology stems from participation in the political world. Those Florentine magistrates, who ascended to power after driving out the Medici in 1494, would often be deceived about general matters until knowledge of the particular “removed that deception that, in considering [the matter] generally, one had presupposed.”<d-footnote>Niccolò Machiavelli, *Discorsi sopra la prima deca di Tito Livio*, trans. mine, (Milano: BUR Rizzoli, 2018), I.XLVII.23, p. 161. &lt;&lt; la cognizione delle cose particulari gli toglieva via quello inganno che nel considerarle generalmente si aveva presupposto.&gt;&gt; </d-footnote> Those who heard the magistrates change their mind concluded that this change was due to understanding the matter more fully, but due to political corruption. From this, the common expression “those people have one mind in the piazza and one in the palazzo”<d-footnote> Ibid., I.XLVII.25. &lt;&lt; costoro hanno uno animo in piazza e uno in palazzo.&gt;&gt; </d-footnote> arose, which Machiavelli quotes and Mannheim takes to be an embryonic form of the type of attribution of men’s thought to their interests that particular ideology does.<d-footnote>Mannheim, *op. cit.*, 56.</d-footnote> According to Mannheim, Hume takes this and generalizes it, claiming that rationally investigating a matter requires us to presume that others have a tendency to deceive us for their ends. We thus must decode the <em>true</em> meaning of our interlocutors’ claims “that lies concealed behind a camouflage of words.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Invoking the notion of particular ideology is one (albeit uncouth) way to penetrate the illusory fog that masks one’s (perhaps unknown) presuppositions.</p> <p>So much for the etiology of particular ideology: what of the <em>total</em> conception of ideology? This latter type of ideological innovation stems from a world in flux, “in which fundamental new values are being created and old ones destroyed.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 57.</d-footnote> While the feudal order provided a common lingua franca with which to settle intellectual conflict, the rise of capitalism changed not only the relations of production but the relations of thought as well. The fundamental philosophical shifts which occurred at the dawn of capitalism were so profound that they constituted not a difference in degree with the old ideas they supplanted, but a difference in kind. The first step in this development was the “development of a philosophy of consciousness”<d-footnote>Ibid., 58.</d-footnote> that Kant, with his emphasis on the individual’s contribution to the categorization of the world, constitutes the apex of. The transcendental deduction of the categories is the embryonic form of the total conception of ideology because it places the individual at the helm of experiential cognition. The shift from Kant to Hegel marks the transition to the second stage of the development of total ideology. Not only is the world a unity, but it is now <em>historical</em> in nature, where one can chronicle different <em>Volksgeister</em> as bearers of different stages in the development of the Geist of freedom.<d-footnote>Ibid., 59.</d-footnote> Consequently, brute experience is no longer the bedrock of justification; experience itself becomes interrogated by making explicit the assumptions which make it possible and the historical course thereof. The French Revolution’s concretization of consciousness into <em>l’esprit du peuple</em> also represents the <em>politicization</em> of such a process.<d-footnote>Ibid., 60.</d-footnote> In a footnote, Mannheim emphasizes that the task of the sociology of knowledge is not to trace ideas back as remotely as possible, lest it lead to regress. Rather, ideas are placed in the context of extant sociopolitical forces, and for this reason objections that there is nothing new under the sun fall. The final, most important step in this process occurs when class replaces the <em>Volk</em> as the “bearer of the historically evolving consciousness,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> that is, when the Marxian tradition discovers that the proletariat has at last become the subject-object of history and that changes in the relations and means of production cause a corresponding change in the ideal <em>Überbau</em>. The result of this process, per Mannheim, is twofold: consciousness becomes an increasingly large organic unity, and this unity becomes less rigid and formulaic. Hence, consciousness is no longer ahistorical and universal, but varies based on time and space, as does the unity thereof.<d-footnote>Ibid., 61.</d-footnote> There are two important consequences Mannheim draws from this: first, that “human affairs cannot be understood by an isolation of their elements,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> and secondly, that the meaning of the unity of these elements changes based on historical circumstances. At the end of this process, particular and total ideology, which were never <em>fully</em> distinct, converge upon each other further. Where we once accused our opponents of unconscious falsification due to psychological deficiencies, we now accuse them of being unable to think correctly thanks to structural forces on the “noological level.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 62.</d-footnote> The rise of total ideology raises the question of how false consciousness, by which Mannheim means “the totally distorted mind which falsifies everything which comes within its range,”<d-footnote> Ibid.</d-footnote> could have arisen.</p> <p>At this point, Mannheim tackles the concept of false consciousness, claiming that the concept has a religious origin. Despite its ancient origin, the more important methodological <em>form</em> of false consciousness is modern. The secularization of the concept not only entails new methods for determining the truth, but “even the scale of values by which we measure truth and falsity, reality and unreality have been profoundly transformed.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 63.</d-footnote> To appreciate this transformation, Mannheim thinks it necessary to give a historical account of the origins of the concept. While the term “ideology” was originally associated with a French philosophical school which “rejected metaphysics and sought to base the cultural sciences on anthropological and psychological foundations,”<d-footnote>Ibid., 64</d-footnote> Napoleon gave the term a new pejorative sense: an “ideologist” was a rigid doctrinaire. This was derogatory because the ideologue’s thought was now unrealistic and inapplicable as a practical guide. Hence, Mannheim argues that practice is the barometer by which one measures whether a given system of thought is ideological. In the 19th century, “ideology” came to gain this sense, and hence the question of what is <em>really</em> the case (as opposed to what the ideologue <em>claims</em> to be the case) is always implicit in any accusations of ideological bias. That questions of what constitutes reality gain a political valence is an important turning point in the development of the concept of ideology and make possible the development of a sociology of knowledge.<d-footnote>Ibid., 65.</d-footnote> Due to the politicization of ideological bias, ideologies become increasingly counterposed to pragmatism. Mannheim relays the anecdote about Napoleon giving the term its derogatory sense to show that the question of ideology escaped the ivory tower of academia and became a practical concern. Moreover, the politicization of ideology as a concept allows for it to become a “weapon” or tool that one political group may use against another.<d-footnote> Ibid., 66.</d-footnote> While this starts off with the proletariat using the concept as a part of class analysis, the concept has become generalized to such a degree that no viewpoint can escape accusations of ideology. However, the predominance of ideology in Marxist thought is notable because Marx’s Hegelian background allows for a merger of the particular and total conceptions of ideology. No longer were invocations of ideology merely a way to posit an individual ideological bias, but rather a more comprehensive and philosophical false consciousness. Furthermore, the Marxist insistence on the inseparability of theory from practice gives ideology a predominant conception in the Marxist tradition.<d-footnote>Ibid., 67.</d-footnote> However, this does not mean that accusations of ideological bias are the domain of Marxists alone: today, every group invokes the concept against all others. Mannheim cites the rise of, inter alia, Max Weber as one such instance of this generalization. Consequently, the very tool that has played a central role in Marxist thought now became a weapon that others brandished against it.</p> <p>Marxism discovered the clue to understanding thought by discovering the concept of ideology, and rival political forces were forced to use the concept in retaliation, thereby generalizing the concept of ideology beyond its Marxist roots. This expansion of ideological thought creates a new epistemic framework; when one analyzes one’s opponents ideologically, “all elements of meaning are qualitatively changed and the word ideology acquires a totally new meaning.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 68.</d-footnote> All previous concepts undergo a transformation thanks to the introduction of the concept of ideology. This intensifies when moving from the particular to total conception of ideology, as the latter throws even the categories of an opponent’s thought into question via sociological analysis. Yet to merely restrict this sociological analysis to an opponent’s ideology is to leave the task incomplete. This restriction constitutes the <em>special</em> formulation of the total conception of ideology, which Mannheim distinguishes from a <em>general</em> form of the total conception of ideology, in which “the analyst has the courage to subject not just the adversary’s point of view but all points of view, including his own, to the ideological analysis.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 69. </d-footnote> The <em>general</em> form recognizes that all thought, by all groups in all eras, “is of an ideological character.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> By transitioning from the special to general form of total ideology, one at last reaches Mannheim’s sociology of knowledge, in which a social group uncovers the “situational determination”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> of its political opponents before elevating this determination to a general principle which applies to all. In this context, two approaches to ideological analysis arrive: the former consists in showing the interrelation between thought and social position while renouncing the unmasking of opponents, while the latter consists in treating one’s own ideology as an <em>idee fixe</em> and combining it with a given epistemology.<d-footnote>Ibid., 70.</d-footnote> According to the latter approach, reliable knowledge may either be constituted via <em>relationism</em> or via <em>relativism</em>. Relativism stems from the modern recognition that historical thinking is tied up with the thinker’s social position, but combines this with an older, more dogmatic<d-footnote>“Dogmatic” is used here in the Kantian sense.</d-footnote> epistemology that rejected the thinker’s standpoint as a condition of knowledge. To escape relativism, one must combine this modern insight with the claim that what conflicts with thought is not epistemology <em>simpliciter</em> but “a certain historically transitory type of epistemology.”<d-footnote>Mannheim, *op. cit.*, 70.</d-footnote> For Mannheim, a modern epistemology must assume that in certain intellectual spheres it is “impossible to conceive of absolute truth existing independently of the values and position of the subject and unrelated to the social context.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 70–-1.</d-footnote> After recognizing that all historical knowledge is relational, one may discern truth from falsity by asking which social determination gets an optimal amount of truth, while recognizing that reaching historically and socially independent truths is quixotic. When dealing with the general-total conception of ideology, one must distinguish between two approaches: that of a value-free analysis, and an “epistemological and metaphysically oriented normative approach.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 71.</d-footnote> In the former, one approaches the question of ideology by merely discovering how thought relates to the social situation of the milieu which promotes said thought. One need not think it a source of error to investigate thought in this manner. But this approach does have limits, for it entails that thinkers are unable to understand certain problems if their situational determination forbids it. The sociologist of knowledge, then, attempts to show the limits of each ideology and their interrelation within the total social process.<d-footnote>Ibid., 72.</d-footnote> Moreover, by showing how “certain intellectual standpoints are connected with certain forms of experience,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> one can show why it cannot be the case that, contra philosophers’ self-aggrandizement, there is no eternal set of categories which may unfold in historically determined ways. In effect, the sociology of knowledge acts as a defeater to claims of ahistorically valid categories of thought. Even the notion of <em>value</em> (in a normative sense) is historically determined, and conflation between ethical, aesthetic, and religious value is a product of the primacy of economic thought in bourgeois society.<d-footnote>Ibid., 73.</d-footnote> Moreover, the attempt to invoke universal, objective formal categories is characteristic of modern rationalization which discounts the irrational forces which are also in play in shaping human life. Differing modes of thought across both time and culture not only have differing content but different <em>categories</em>, which change as the social group which uses said categories changes.</p> <p>Consequently, the sociologist of knowledge is unconcerned with discovering putatively transhistorical truth, but of discovering “the approximate truth as it emerges in the course of historical development out of the complex social process.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 75.</d-footnote> This alleged epistemic humility, Mannheim claims, will lead us closer to the truth than a dogmatic insistence that one has the whole truth. Only the present, in which all fixed social structures are thrown into question and in which there are sundry viewpoints “of equal value and prestige, each showing the relativity of the other,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> could values have been subjected to ideological criticism. Epistemic humility is the order of the day; self-confidence leads to bias and a one-sided point of view which can only be supplemented by others when one interacts with conflicting views.<d-footnote>This displays a clear Millian influence, down to the insistence that past epochs were the domain of unearned dead dogma.</d-footnote> This also requires us to face the fact that all values and viewpoints are subject to situational determination.<d-footnote>Mannheim, *op. cit.*, 76.</d-footnote> The non-evaluative investigation into situational determination leads to relationism, the claim that “all […] elements of meaning in a given situation have reference to one another and derive their significance from this reciprocal interrelationship in a given frame of thought.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Knowledge, though historically determined, is still <em>knowledge</em>. Changes in the social situation therefore throw all hitherto norms and knowledge out of alignment. All knowledge is knowledge <em>about</em> some object, and depends on the knower both in its qualitative depth (i.e., <em>scientia</em>, mere understanding, or some lesser degree of understanding in the Early Modern schematism) and the transmission of knowledge. The categories which we use to organize and transmit knowledge are determined by the social situation of the thinker, and hence partial knowledge is connected to a larger organic unity of meaning. Since the social situation and the categories of thought which correspond to it are always in flux, one must think dynamically rather than in ahistorical absolutes. This implies a rejection of conservatism; “[t]hose who are satisfied with the existing order of things are […] likely to set up the chance situation of the moment as absolute and eternal;”<d-footnote>Ibid., 78.</d-footnote> requiring self-aggrandizing myths in defense of the status quo to “distort, pervert, and conceal the meaning of the present.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote></p> <p>However, we arrive <em>post festum</em> at the conclusion that, despite its pretensions to a non-evaluative approach, the concept of ideology requires an evaluative and metaphysical approach. In the process of criticizing static thought, Mannheim recognizes that he has used “metaphysical-ontological value-judgements of which [he has] not been aware.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This need not be cause for concern, as unmasking the presuppositions of thought requires a foundation of “certain meta-empirical, ontological, and metaphysical judgements.<d-footnote>Ibid., 79.</d-footnote>Even positivism, which attempted to forego such foundational suppositions, implicitly did so when putting faith in progress and scientific realism. There is no danger in <em>a priori</em> knowledge <em>per se</em>, but merely that receiving a ready-made ontology unquestioningly “obstructs new developments.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 80</d-footnote> To allow for change, one must emphasize the situational determination of one’s viewpoint and make explicit the implicit metaphysical suppositions that undergirds one’s thought and allows for the possibility of empirical knowledge.</p> <p>So which metaphysical approach does the non-evaluative conception of ideology take? There are two possible paths one may take. The former <em>mystical</em> approach dismisses all history as transient and epiphenomenal, and hence unable to grasp the fundamental, ahistorical truths.<d-footnote>Ibid., 81.</d-footnote> While mysticism never gained much purchase in a world where day-to-day affairs where given primary significance, its insistence on the interconnectedness of all things in the Godhead survives as a secularized methodological truth: that all partial truths gain significance thanks to its connection to the social situation which supplies it with the categories of its meaning. On the other hand, the second approach which leads to sociological methodology insists that history is not the mere assemblage of arbitrary events, but “must be regarded as following a certain necessary regularity.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 81.</d-footnote> This realization renders history as important rather than incidental. While the mystic insists that humanity is not fully encompassed by history, this does not entail that history is unimportant. Rather, history is the “matrix within which man’s essential nature is expressed.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 82.</d-footnote> One gains subjectivity within the bounds of the ever-varying social institutions, which in turn furnish a dynamic series of viewpoints “in terms of which each social-historical subject becomes aware of himself and acquires an appreciation of his past.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Even if one can only understand human essence mystically, this essence must “bear some relation to social and historical reality.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> A mystical viewpoint overlooks the very forces of history which shape mankind into what it is. Even though Mannheim (allegedly) rejects a <em>telos</em> of history, history is nonetheless an important object to analyze, as it provides the situational determinations which imbue ideas with their meaning.<d-footnote>Ibid., 83.</d-footnote> Thus, the study of history is the study of the totality; the study of ideology shows that <em>Weltanschauungen</em> are not arbitrary. Their unfurling signals “a cross-section of the total intellectual and social situation of our time.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> While this begins as a non-evaluative practice, evaluation and ontological judgment come in as it is needed to separate the wheat of history from the chaff.</p> <p>Hence, there is a conceptual transition from the non-evaluative general, total conception of ideology to the evaluative conception, though this evaluative conception does not take as static the values of a given era.<d-footnote>Ibid., 84.</d-footnote> Rather, it is evaluative in the sense that it seeks to differentiate the true and insightful from the false and spurious modes of thought. The question of false consciousness is hence transformed from how it obscures static reality to how it obscures reality as “the outcome of constant reorganization of the mental processes which make up our worlds.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> While the secularization of the concept of false consciousness by searching for the criterion of validity in practice, it did not go far enough while it remained ahistorical and posited thought and action as two separate poles. This marriage of thought and action renders any ethical belief invalid if it is formed in such a way that no action in a given historical setting can comply with it. Moral transgressions are invalid if they are the result not of individual failings but of “an erroneously founded set of moral axioms.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 85.</d-footnote> Moral interpretations of these actions are invalid if forbids action and thought to adapt to new social situations. Moral theories are wrong if it uses categories in inapt situations which prevent people from adjusting to changes in circumstances. These outdated modes of thought become ideological “whose function is to conceal the actual function of conduct rather than to reveal it.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Mannheim cites the taboo against usury as a moral practice that lapsed into an ideology. While the norm took root in societies based on intimate interpersonal relations, it became ideological as it became adopted by large impersonal social structures, viz., the Catholic Church. Eventually, the shift to capitalism caused even the Church to discard the norm as an outdated ideological remnant. An example of false consciousness as false interpretation of oneself, Mannheim cites the tendency to obscure one’s <em>real</em> relation to the world via escapism and self-aggrandizement (especially by putative allegiance to ideals that mask our real reasons for action). An example of ideological distortion that occurs when it can no longer explain the actual world is that of the landed gentry who insists on using feudal categories in what has clearly become a capitalistic enterprise. The conception of ideology in play is both <em>evaluative</em> in that it “presupposes certain judgements concerning the reality of ideas and structures of consciousness,”<d-footnote>Ibid., 86.</d-footnote> and <em>dynamic</em> as “these judgements are always measured by a reality which is in constant flux.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Thus, over and above common sources of error, we also must be vigilant about “the effects of a distorted mental structure.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 87.</d-footnote> This distortion may be because they are outdated or too avant-garde (the latter of which gains the moniker <em>utopian</em>). Either way, the ideology is measured against a dynamic reality.</p> <p>Mannheim concludes his project by claiming that the struggle to escape “ideological and utopian distortions is […] a quest for reality.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This quest involves grounding thought in action, and keeping fidelity to the “actual situation to be comprehended.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Yet ideology and utopia throw the concept of reality into question: no longer is it accepted as a static, ahistorical entity which we can dogmatically assume, but rather differing conceptions of reality produce different “modes of thought.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 88.</d-footnote> Consequently “every ontological judgement that we make leads inevitably to far-reaching consequences.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Ignoring this problem may be pragmatic: we may avoid the need to critique the categories of our “conceptual devices”<d-footnote>Ibid., 89.</d-footnote> so long as they prove adequate to the task of dealing with our “highly restricted sphere of life.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> But when faced with the different categories of experience present in earlier epochs, we are faced with the following question: “under what conditions may we say that the realm of experience of a group has changed so fundamentally that a discrepancy becomes apparent between the traditional mode of though and the novel objects of experience (to be understood by that mode of thought?).”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Assuming that theoretical reasons caused the change is too intellectualistic, and appealing to “special cultural sciences”<d-footnote>Ibid., 90.</d-footnote> is fraught as such disciplines carve the world at joints abstracted from concrete reality. The academic division of labor poses its own problems, incentivizing scholars to narrow the confines of their studies to such an extent that an overall coherent picture is lost. This does not make such investigations useless, but one should keep in mind that the social sciences, much like the natural sciences, has reached a point where “empirical data compel [it] to raise certain questions about [its] presuppositions.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> So long as empirical research remains within the confines of a given situational determination’s common sense, it cannot criticize its fundamental concepts. The crisis that this inability causes has swelled into a crescendo, even affecting empirical research itself. This is not to deny the existence of facts, but merely to show that facts “exist for the mind always in an intellectual and social context.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 91.</d-footnote> One needs a “conceptual apparatus”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> to frame facts. Differing apparatuses use different categories of experience differently, and hence represent and perceive facts through different logical categories. Our categories thus impose a viewpoint on us, but the more comprehensive our conception of rival apparatuses, the more phenomena we can account for. This appears in empirical research, where Max Weber has shown that particularity of viewpoint is demonstrated by the limitations of the definitions that the investigator chooses to deploy. These viewpoints are themselves influenced by “a good many unconscious steps in our thinking.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 92.</d-footnote> Two dogmas prevented a critical examination of the categories used in intellectual investigations. First, a deflationary dogma (associated with logical positivism) dismissed these questions as irrelevant, granting validity only to analytic a priori knowledge on one hand and empirical truths on the other.<d-footnote>Note that this division has fallen out of favor as of late, due in large part due to the defense of contingent a priori and necessary a posteriori knowledge in Saul Kripke’s *Naming and Necessity*.</d-footnote> A second dogma divided the division of intellectual labor in two, assigning the sciences the empirical questions and philosophy the “loftier”<d-footnote>Mannheim, *op. cit.*, 92.</d-footnote> speculative ones. This allowed philosophy to maintain the pretense of being the queen of the sciences, so long as it did not interfere with scientific investigation. Unity is thereby undermined, leading the philosopher ill-equipped to clarify “the observer’s own mind in the total situation”<d-footnote>Ibid., 93.</d-footnote> and the scientist unable to get a more complete picture of a totality based on the results of empirical investigation. “For mastery of each historical situation, a certain structure of thought is required which will rise to the demands of the actual, real problems encountered, and is capable of integrating what is relevant in the various conflicting points of view.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This requires a search for a “fundamental axiomatic point of departure”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> which should attempt to find a totality rather remain stuck at the level of the limitations of an individual point of view. Only by recognizing the limitations of each point of view can one reach a comprehension of the whole. That we can see that there is a crisis represents a step forward, not an intellectual dead-end, as “[t]hought is a process determined by actual social forces, continually questioning its findings and correcting its procedure.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 94.</d-footnote> Even totality is not eternally valid, but “implies both the assimilation and transcendence of the limitations of particular points of view.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> Its telos is not an ahistorical and universal truth, but “the broadest possible extension of our horizon of vision.”<d-footnote> Ibid., 95.</d-footnote> Discovering the “fundamental conditions which determine [one’s] social and intellectual existence”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> provides someone with the impetus to go beyond the confines of one’s point of view to discover the way in which this point of view is part of a situational determination. This in turn sheds light on the way in which one’s viewpoint is situated within an overall historical process. This is the “ever-widening drive towards a total conception.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> If new “problems of thought arise, men must learn to think anew.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 96.</d-footnote> While we previously were stuck in a naïve dogmatism toward our intellectual process, we are now “grappling with the critical situation that has arisen in [our] thinking”<d-footnote> Ibid.</d-footnote> to aim at clarity.</p>]]></content><author><name>Sam Thomas</name></author><category term="report"/><category term="study"/><category term="write-up"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hans-Jürgen Krahl’s Authorities and Revolution</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Krahl-translation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hans-Jürgen Krahl’s Authorities and Revolution"/><published>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Krahl-translation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/Krahl-translation/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post7-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post7-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post7-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post7.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="translators-introduction">Translator’s Introduction</h2> <p>This introduction will be brief and, frankly, somewhat aggressive. My reasons for translating this piece here and now should be obvious (just check the news). The complete moral, political, and theoretical bankruptcy—and that is the word for it, because ‘failure’ would imply they made an effort—of the doyens of critical and “democratic” theory in the present moment recalls the weakness of their forebears (and, in the case of Habermas, that of his own past self) in the era of the Vietnam War, decolonization, and the New Left. The archons of the academic system are as ethically worthless and politically inhumane as ever; just as Talleyrand said of the Bourbons, the capitalist academy has “learned nothing and forgotten nothing” from their own revolutionary interregnum—the global revolt of 1968. From Manhattan to Berlin, bringing anti-imperialism into the university is forbidden. Supposedly humanist intellectuals expend their oh-so-valuable time nitpicking the language of those who protest Israel’s genocide in Gaza while the Democratic Party and its decrepit poobah Biden throw their entire weight behind the police and the fascist apartheid State of Israel, thus setting up American “democracy” to be hoist by its own petard and confirming Krahl’s claim that “an authoritarian State means that democracy can be transformed into the state of exception with no break in legal and political legitimacy.”</p> <p>But enough about that: who is Hans-Jürgen Krahl? Once a leading figure in the <em>Sozialistischer Deutscher Studentenbund</em> (SDS), he is today mostly forgotten. (If you want to know more, <a href="https://viewpointmag.com/2018/04/14/personal-information/">read this</a> and the related texts in the <em>Viewpoint</em> dossier). More than forgotten, he is repressed, and, even worse, the few who do not repress the very memory of his existence are mostly <em>Anti-Deutschen</em>. (One of the founders of the tendency, Joachim Bruhn, once expressed his disdain for the Marxist-Leninist movement in Germany with the observation that “nobody [among them] had read anything by Hans-Jürgen Krahl” <sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Krahl himself, however, thought the fact that the works of Che Guevara and other revolutionaries were not being closely studied was evidence of the “decline of theoretical consciousness” <sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>.) Against his oblivion in mainstream Habermasian critical theory and cult status in German subcultural leftoid critical theory, his texts still testify to the possibility that things could have gone differently. That’s one reason why he’s worth reading. Things could have gone differently then; things can go differently today.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post8-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post8-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post8-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Pictured: The banner proclaiming the University of Frankfurt as Karl Marx University is taken down after the end of the occupation of the university in late May 1968 </div> <p>Krahl wanted to advance from the theoretical self-criticism of the bourgeoisie to the practical betrayal of it, from the mourning of the bourgeois individual to the birth of a socialist society. The problem of how to move from the one to the other is the essential problem of his whole project, and in this regard his project was personal: he was the son of a petty-bourgeois family from a reactionary country town and had been a member of a few different reactionary youth and student organizations in the past. (That said, his talk of class betrayal and repeated run-ins with the law did not keep his parents from funding him <sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>.) At the same time, however, it was universal: the orthodox Marxist conceptions of practice and organization, which found their highest expressions in Lukács’s <em>History and Class Consciousness</em>, seemed to him to have retained certain bourgeois presuppositions, and so did not represent a complete break with the bourgeois social forms they were meant to overthrow.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post9-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post9-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post9-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post9.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Pictured: Adorno and Krahl at the September 23rd discussion on the topic of “authorities and revolution” put on by Luchterhand-Verlag at Frankfurt’s ‘Haus Gallus,’ a modernist building which had been constructed earlier in the 1960s specifically to house the Auschwitz trials. Other participants, Habermas among them, are out of frame </div> <p>The problem in this text is political and organizational, but, like Lukács, Krahl saw organizational and theoretical questions as inextricably linked. The task of turning critical theory into revolutionary theory meant grappling with organizational problems. Accomplishing that task in the reality of 1960s West Germany and the student movement meant grappling with the academy and its scholarly authorities in their concrete existence. In this text, Krahl mounts a critique of two academic authorities who have failed to support the student movement: Habermas and Adorno. His criticism of these two is biting, but what makes the text truly notable is the way which Krahl weaves together the organizational problems of SDS with theoretical reflections on the nature of capitalism and the State, re-activating concepts from Horkheimer’s decisively political texts from the 1940s. Along the way, he poses crucial political and organizational questions for which we still have no convincing answer. (This is another reason to read him: his texts are the testament of a mind engaged in the same problems which still haunt us today.)</p> <p>I mentioned Habermas above. Krahl’s criticism of him in this text is informed by a faith in his character that is no longer tenable today, a faith which indeed has been untenable for many years. His claim in a 2012 interview with <em>Ha’aretz</em> that Germans essentially have a duty to cover up, or at least ignore, the crimes of the Israeli occupation <sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> should have been more than enough to put an end to <em>Habermas als Institution</em>.</p> <p>What about Adorno, who despite being present at the discussion receives less flak than Habermas? Some background may be in order here. Krahl went to the University of Frankfurt specifically to study under him. The two, however, developed mixed feelings about one another. While Habermas was more open to practical engagement in politics, his theory was less radical. Adorno was more radical in theory, but completely unwilling to engage in practice beyond the occasional conversation with SDS members. There are two notable apocryphal stories about Krahl and Adorno <sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. In one, Adorno is supposed to have written on the wall of the Institute for Social Research, after Ludwig von Friedeburg had the police expel and arrest the students occupying it <sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, either “This Krahl is inhabited by wolves” or “The wolves howl from this Krahl,” punning on the rhyme Krahl/Saal (hall). In the other, Adorno allegedly had a dream in which Krahl held a knife to his throat. When Adorno protested this, Krahl retorted in good Adornian fashion with something like, “Come now professor, you mustn’t personalize.” In another version of this story Krahl was sat incubus-like on Adorno’s chest during the whole affair—that version has much clearer libidinal undertones to it. The context of this latter story is that Adorno was somewhat disturbed by Krahl’s ability to separate the political from the personal: Krahl once turned to him after a speech and whispered, so Adorno wrote to Günter Grass, “that he hoped I would not take it amiss since it was purely political and not meant personally” <sup id="fnref:7" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>. For Adorno this was not admirable but rather evidence of “something pathological” in Krahl’s personality <sup id="fnref:8" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote">8</a></sup>.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post10-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post10-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post10-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post10.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Pictured: A comic depicting Adorno’s supposed Krahl nightmare. </div> <p>Adorno’s callousness towards Krahl, his accusations—made in bad faith?—that the student movement either stood to provoke a fascist restoration or was fast approaching a form of “left-wing fascism” itself <sup id="fnref:9" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote">9</a></sup>: what to make of these? In his correspondence with Marcuse, Adorno musters the traumatic memory of fascism to justify his weariness of the student movement <sup id="fnref:10" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote">10</a></sup>, but gay men like Krahl were also victims of the Nazi regime and continued to be persecuted under the Federal Republic. And isn’t there something, I don’t know, ironic in the horror at Krahl’s ability to separate the political and the personal coming from someone permanently unable, indeed proud of his inability, to unite the political and the theoretical? (Adorno even criticized Angela Davis, another student of his for a time, for her militancy, showing that his reticence towards practice was not at all attached specifically to the conditions in Germany <sup id="fnref:11" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote">11</a></sup>.) Adorno grounded his critique of practice in the concept of “pseudo-activity,” a concept originally critical of late-capitalist society which Adorno later employed for a backhanded defense of that same society which used many of the same tropes employed in the anti-left canards of reactionaries the world over. The condescending and psychologizing accusation that the “actionists” of the SDS or APO cared more about doing something, anything, than doing something effective is wrong. Krahl addressed such accusations in this text and elsewhere: for him the spectacular protest actions of SDS were “forms of appearance afflicted with growing pains” (kinderkranken Erscheinungsformen) of a movement which was still in the process of constituting itself and wanted to one day be capable of “essentially correct pre-revolutionary practice” <sup id="fnref:12" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote">12</a></sup>. In general, Adorno’s critiques of practice should be met with the question Krahl poses to Habermas in this text: what function do such arguments have if one does not assume that SDS are so stupid that they don’t already understand them?</p> <p>I could critique Krahl, for there are, of course, some questionable moments in his corpus, but this is neither the time nor the place. His project was left unfinished, both politically and theoretically. It has been fifty years since his death and we are by and large still in the same position. Banal remarks about this faulty assumption or that naïve expectation would be worse than worthless, and so I haven’t bothered.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post11-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post11-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post11-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post11.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Pictured: Krahl and Adorno in court ca. July 1969 after Adorno had him charged with trespassing for occupying the building of the _Institut für Sozialforschung_. </div> <p>Last thing: I have put a few translator’s notes in the text. They are set off in their own paragraphs and enclosed in square brackets. These notes either provide information, summarize the proceedings of the discussion, or denote interjections. The text of this translation uses the main body and notes from <em>Konstitution und Klassenkampf</em> and the transcript reprinted in Volume II of Wolfgang Kraushaar’s <em>Frankfurter Schule und Studentenbewegung: von der Flaschenpost zum Molotowcocktail 1946-1995</em> (1998, pp. 458-470). The translation may sound awkward at points, but I assure you that this is only partly my fault: Krahl’s sentences are often highly unwieldy and grammatically complex.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="authorities-and-revolution">Authorities and Revolution</h2> <p>A Contribution to a Discussion held September 23, 1968</p> <p>[*Before Krahl’s address, Frank Benseler, an editor at Luchterhand and organizer of this discussion; Ludwig von Friedeburg, the Hessian minister of education; and Kurt Lenk, a political scientist, make contributions to the discussion. Krahl does not directly respond to any of them in his contribution, and so I will not summarize them here.]</p> <p>I would like to relate [my contribution] to what has happened over the past three days. Firstly, a paradox must be explained: namely that the student movement, which conceives of itself as anti-authoritarian, has need of so many authorities with regard to both its nature [in Sachhinsicht] and personnel. Anyone who followed the last SDS delegate conference could establish that the anti-authoritarian revolt had continued to a certain degree and had also begun with the de-mythologization and disenchantment of its very own authorities. This is, at least for a Marxist movement, a principle of organization in an emphatic as well as historical-philosophical and revolutionary-theoretical sense; it means that a movement has an irrational need for authorities to the extent that it is not organized and has not built up any sort of qualification structure based on the division of labor, and then, afterwards, this authority, as Georg Lukács critically noted [3] contra Pannekoek and Luxemburg, turns to the propaganda phase, to agitation. And it is typical that in the SDS the agitators, who lead the discussions at teach-ins, are to a certain extent authoritarian. The extra-parliamentary opposition, most of all its anti-authoritarian faction, has still not yet built up a sufficient division of labor in this sense, namely that on one hand there should be nothing without a qualitative function, an old principle of the communist division of labor, which demanded of everyone a corresponding authoritarian pressure to perform, even today in a society wherein the abolition [Abschaffung] of labor has emerged so far out of the dimension of the utopian; on the other hand, however, this pressure to perform is supposed to be made up for by the development of solidaristic collectives, which are supposed to anticipatorily sublate the separation and atomization of individuals which capitalist society nurtures on the basis of its abstract division of labor. This is exactly the question that Georg Lukács posed in his speculative summation of the European debate over organization: how can the realm of freedom be anticipated in a communist and thoroughly authoritarian form of organization? This question is still insufficiently considered today, because the Leninist type of party corresponded only to the conditions of a country that was still in the phase of industrialization, where authoritarian work discipline had, in general, to first be constituted and could not already be abolished in society as a whole, and so surplus-norms—thus, surplus labor time—had to be internalized. Today the problem is posed in an inverted fashion: these surplus-norms, “surplus-repression,” as Marcuse says, have become superfluous as authoritarian performance-principles. And for us in the SDS the question is posed as to how is it possible to develop a form of organization which, under conditions of coercion and violence, develops both autonomous individuals as well as those who are capable of a certain disciplined subordination to the requirements of struggle and to the conditions of coercion. This problem is fully unresolved. We are in the process of realizing an anti-authoritarian revolt of the same provocative style as that which we had in the college. This anti-authoritarian revolt aims at making something like a collective learning process possible. At the same time, in no way may a form of collectivism hostile to individuals be allowed to develop in the SDS. I want, further, to discuss the role that journalistically definable critical authorities represent. This should be discussed with regard to two prominent individuals who are present here in the hall, Habermas and Adorno. I believe that these authorities falsely define their relation to the extra-parliamentary opposition, above all to its Marxist and socialist section. Jürgen Habermas, in the illusion that one could still construct something like a liberal counter-coalition ranging from Brenner to Augstein*, that one could still mobilize something like a liberal counter-public-sphere through work in the institutions, thinks that he must tactically distance himself in certain volatile action situations where we have need of his solidarity. With the fatal accusation of “left-wing fascism,” [4] which was immediately seized upon by the liberal press—to which any plebiscitary-egalitarian movement already seems fascistic from its form alone, fully abstracting from its content—Habermas has for the first time realized this tactical distancing. He realized it a second time when he hurled the accusation of pseudo-revolutionism at us. I am not even going to discuss whether this accusation is justified in terms of the content of the dispute between different factions of the extra-parliamentary opposition; rather only which function it has in a definite volatile moment of the movement. Daniel Cohn-Bendit relays that a sociologist, who politically plays a similar role in France to Habermas here [in Germany], explained during the May revolution: “I strongly disagree with many of your actions, especially with regard to the structure of violence, but in this moment it is necessary that I stand in solidarity with you all.” Why is it necessary that we lead such authorities into the field? In the authoritarian, performance-oriented society of education, manipulation, and executive indoctrination, the masses are so fixated on authorities that they initially have need of authorities—that is, ones who understand themselves as critical authorities—for their enlightenment. And so we need the public, pronounced solidarity of critical authorities; they can, in a certain way, help destroy the principle of authority in society with the weapon of authority itself. I believe that neither Habermas nor Adorno have upheld this to date.</p> <p>[*Augstein. Founder and editor of <em>Der Spiegel</em>, which was targeted by the government of the BRD in the 1962 <em>Spiegel-Affäre</em>. Augstein was a liberal who went on to briefly hold office as a deputy from 1972 to 1973 for the <em>Freie Demokratische Partei</em>, still the foremost liberal party in the Federal Republic today, but a party which was not part of the contemporaneous 1966-9 <em>Große Koalition</em> of the CDU and SPD. The <em>GroKo</em> held 90% of the seats in the Bundestag and, from the extra-parliamentary opposition’s perspective, seemed poised to turn the BRD into something like the authoritarian State prophesied by Adorno and Horkheimer.]</p> <p>It’s different with Adorno. This may be discussed rather as the question of theory. Here I want only to summarize it as an anecdote: as we were besieging the [university] council about half a year ago, Mr. Adorno came to the students for the sit-in as the only professor there. He was overwhelmed with ovations, ran immediately up to the microphone, and then just before reaching it swerved into his philosophy seminar; thus, moments away from practice [he went] back again into theory. That is basically the situation of critical theory today. It rationalizes its resignative and refined-individualistic fear of practice, [claiming] that practice is somehow impossible, and so one must go back home to philosophy.</p> <p>A third thing. Just in the last [few] days it has been shown here, or at least been formally indicated, that something has changed since the enactment of the emergency acts** without becoming drastically and immediately manifest in the structure of the State. From a book fair, which is by definition something like the stage of a critical public-sphere, even if a somewhat antiquated and regrettable one, was made an emergency-camp. We have experienced the systematic targeting of individuals for beating, [for example] yesterday when police stormtroopers surged out of the mess hall. In such a situation, where brutality has become just as manifest as the fact that we stand alone, we need the solidarity of these [critical] authorities. My thesis is of a theoretical kind, concerned with principles. What does it mean, if exactly in the end-phase of our struggle against the enactment of the emergency acts we time and again think back to the concept of the authoritarian State? With this [concept], we wanted to take the problematic of the emergency acts out of the frame of reference of the traditional politics of defense against restoration-tendencies as were current in the fifties, i.e. the defense against the reapproval of corporations, re-armament, and atomic weaponry, collectively a politics which was out to save democracy in the bourgeois sense. With the concept of the authoritarian State, we wanted to posit a different frame of reference, one of revolutionary theory. I would also like to ask, in this regard, what does [the concept of] “authoritarian State” mean in terms of principle for the structure of late-capitalism? This concept has risen to [the status of] a theoretical dictum, not least from the tradition of the Frankfurt School; I have in mind Max Horkheimer and Franz Neumann, and also Adorno. In his essay on the authoritarian State, Horkheimer handled it not merely as an isolated problem of the welfare state [sozialstaatliches] and the philosophy of law, rather he meant with [the concept of] the authoritarian State a change in the whole constitution of the system itself. That means in basic outline that, with the transition from competitive to monopoly capitalism, the mediating instances of bourgeois society, specific forms of association [Verkehrsformen] such as parties and parliament, have lost their economically load-bearing substance. Parliament and parties had [for their] substance the free commodity exchange of commodity owners who are equally valid and equally validating for another. Parliament was thought of as the political market in which the different factions of the bourgeoisie could politically negotiate their economically differentiated interests without violence. Compromise, in the concept of bourgeois <em>Realpolitik</em>, is the political rationalization of economic competition.</p> <p>[**Emergency acts (<em>Notstandsgesetze</em>). A series of laws passed on May 30 1968 which gave the government of the BRD the power to establish a state of exception and abrogate certain rights guaranteed by the constitution of the BRD—the <em>Grundgesetz</em>—in a state of emergency. Critics saw similarities between these laws and the clauses concerning emergency powers in the constitution of the Weimar Republic which had been used by the NSDAP and its bumbling accomplice Hindenburg to turn the Weimar Republic into a dictatorship.]</p> <p>With the growing eclipse of free exchange by oligopolistic and monopolistic market concentrations at the end of the last century, these instances of parties and parliament, the forms of association of the bourgeoisie, lost their economic substance; an advancing self-assertion of the State over and against society took place. For Marxist theory, the legal person is the character-mask of the commodity owner; in place of the <em>Rechtsstaat</em> came the authoritarian welfare state [Sozialstaat]. That means that the State made itself the subject of social reform in order to keep the wage-dependent masses from organizing and coming together. The great organizational forms of the working class forged in days past amidst the struggle for the right to combination, [namely] unions and parties, were, due to this socially reforming tendency of the authoritarian executive, progressively integrated into the structure of that very same authoritarian executive. Max Horkheimer’s theorem that monopoly capitalism is potentially fascism is justified. Fascism, taken fundamentally, is the consequence of the social-reformism of the authoritarian State. An authoritarian State means—and this is becoming manifest with the emergency acts—that democracy can be transformed into the state of exception without a break in political and legal legitimacy. Indeed, one can destroy democratic instances—parliament, for example—by means other than terrorist ones; precisely due to those theoretical presuppositions which I have just mentioned they can be manipulatively integrated into the arsenal of the authoritarian executive.</p> <p>I’ll summarize it in three levels:</p> <ol> <li> <p>Over and against the function that parliament and parties have in the State today, where they are no longer mediums for critical will-formation, it is evident that a revolutionary organization cannot adopt the Leninist concept of discipline. It must rather cultivate within its organization autonomous individuals who are capable of imposing on themselves a pressure to perform in the revolutionary sense.</p> </li> <li> <p>With the present state of the anti-authoritarian movement, we require critical media [publizistisch-kritischen] authorities and their authoritarian weight for critical enlightenment. We require their concrete solidarity; the theoretical dispute would have to play out as a fractional dispute, not as a contemplative critique from outside.</p> </li> <li> <p>The authoritarian State can have society transform into the state of exception without a break in political and legal legitimacy. For the conclusions I will take up the old controversy with Habermas again. He has accused us of infantile pathology; we confuse, he thinks, symbolic actions—building barricades, occupying institutions—with factual situations of struggle for power [5]. When we were occupying the university here in Frankfurt [6], the Hessian minister Rudi Arndt said about it, “We will not let this State be destroyed by them.” It was thus suggested that we, who are still a minority, would be capable of immediately destroying the State. The State must produce a tactical power-struggle ideology and behave as if [the situation] is already concerned with the struggle for political power in the State for two reasons; for one, it cannot, due to the authority-principle in society, endure even the beginning of the emergence of a mass-movement. This became distinctly evident when the student movement stepped over the limits of the academy for the first time and mobilized a strike movement with workers, particularly young workers. For the other, it must produce this power-struggle ideology because a terroristic and brutal approach to the extra-parliamentary opposition is only legitimizable to begin with by suggesting in some way that we could already immediately bring about the collapse of the State. Therefore it needed corresponding falsifications: since July 2nd we’ve known the familiar topoi with which the State authorities transform tomatoes into knives, which demonstrators are supposedly throwing. And so, Mr. Habermas, it is not us who suggest a situation of struggle for power on the basis of the authority-principle in society, but rather the State which is compelled to produce a power-struggle ideology in order to legitimize the attack on the extra-parliamentary oppositions from the start.</p> </li> </ol> <p>[Krahl’s initial address stops here. After him, Karl-Dietrich Wolff, the president of SDS at the time, briefly builds off of Krahl’s points before Adorno interjects to defend his failure to give a speech at the sit-in. He claims that he had to go give an examination and that a student had already been waiting for him half an hour. He also denies that he “swerved away from the microphone” instead saying that he had “not even seen it.” He asserts his conviction in non-violent, “immanent” protest, but refuses to judge his actions as right or wrong. When Wolff then responds by asking Adorno if it would not have been meaningful and symbolically powerful for him to march with them against the ban on protests, Adorno rhetorically asks if portly old men are really the right ones to be participating in marches. Moreover, he asserts, it is his right as an individual not to participate, and SDS is—so Krahl just claimed—not a vulgarly collectivistic organization in the first place. After this exchange, Werner Hofmann—maybe the art historian, I don’t know—criticizes the SDS’s mode of action, accuses them conceiving of themselves as a “substitute class,” insists that the most important thing is “breaking through to the working masses.” Habermas follows Adorno by responding to Krahl’s address, calling him a “party chief who calls the insubordinate intellectuals to order” and accusing him of being authoritarian. Afterward, the Marxist philosopher Hans Heinz Holz gives his address, which Krahl does not respond to and which I will therefore not summarize. Lenk then questions Krahl’s dismissal of the utility of political parties for radical oppositional movements before Krahl begins again.]</p> <p>Mr. Hofmann has used an argument that is always used against us: that we, the intellectuals and students, should not conceive of ourselves as a substitutional class, rather an alliance of the intelligentsia and, as he puts it, ‘working people’ is what’s important. This argument is constantly falsely advanced. The SDS and the extra-parliamentary opposition, insofar as they define themselves as socialist, do not conceive themselves as a class which takes action in [the form of] Blanquist substitution. Now, we did once rather blindly take up the vulgar-Marcusian formula [7] that only groups on the edges of society [Randgruppen] could still be a revolutionary subject; then, on May 1st of this year we issued the slogan, “class struggle instead of social partnership.” In essence, this is a great turn towards the proletariat. We no longer believe that only groups on the edges of society can be a revolutionary subject of change. In all this, however, the class question in today’s society, the question as to how class structures have changed, is theoretically completely unsettled. All these formulas are more a blind reflex of our own practice than a reflected-upon strategy. The second theoretically unsettled question is how the role of the critical intelligentsia has changed in a society where science is a more and more important factor of production, if not outright the primary one. I pose these questions so that we don’t just issue formulas [to the effect] that we have to connect to ‘the working person’—that [phrase itself] being more of an expressionistic formula than a really class-specific term. Posed in terms of content, the question means this: is it the case today that the intellectual has a natural solidarity with the bourgeoisie, which at least phenomenologically no longer exists, although there’s obviously a capitalist class; is it really the case that intellectuals can only exit society as individuals; is this also the case today with the role that the sciences have taken as a productive force? If now the relation of the State to the economy has thereby changed, [i.e.] because the State itself has become a factor of production and an elementary regulator of the economic process, if this relation of politics and economy, in which ultimately even classes, as they are conditioned in themselves, are constituted, has changed, [then] how has the class position of both the capitalists and the wage-workers themselves changed? All these questions are theoretically open, and we essentially proceed in an orthodox way when it comes to agitation, education, and activation for the working class, but in an orthodox way with the pragmatic disposition that we experience changed class structures in our practical work itself. The orthodox work that we carry out presently advances tentatively: we work with a view towards left-wing union members where there is still a revisionist labor center, as in Frankfurt; we work together with comrades from the Communist Party, and this is by no means over even with the expulsion of the Communist Party wing; we try to form our own cells chiefly with young workers. All this is certainly very orthodox work; this cell-work basically corresponds to the politics of the ultra-left opposition among the German communists at the beginning of the twenties. One must consider this educational agitation work in terms of and with regard to the working class and within the context of the pragmatic disposition that we ourselves gather qualitatively new experiences during this work, experiences which [however] only through theoretical reflection give information about the class structure, about the factual constitution of the class structure in society. Otherwise one runs the risk, like the orthodox dogmatists, of only ever working with reified and analytical, in no way mediated oppositions of class in itself and for itself.</p> <p>Now, as to what Mr. Habermas said: he has the impression that I speak as the party chief who calls the insubordinate intellectuals to order. He has not justified this impression at all, but there may be something correct in it. To the extent that one identifies with certain functions in the practice of SDS and the extra-parliamentary opposition, it can indeed be relatively natural to gradually assume the reified mode of behavior of a party chief. In this respect, the remark can serve as an occasion for practical self-reflection.</p> <p>Habermas has misunderstood my demand for unconditional solidarity. This misunderstanding originates from a very specific theoretical approach of his own conception. It’s clear from what he said about the action of the last few days, namely that it had been very brave and escalatory, but not well prepared in terms of reconnaissance. This is, in fact, the case. I would only like to know what function such an argument has if one does not take SDS to be so stupid in their organizational self-understanding that they already didn’t know that themselves. Is it supposed to follow from this that the action should have been refrained from?</p> <p>[Habermas interjects: “I mean that exactly!”]</p> <p>If you mean that, then I must contradict you. We did indeed do a bad job preparing this action, but everyone knows the reason. The mass actions against the emergency acts have had a disintegrative and chaotic effect on the pre-existing organizational structures of SDS. At the moment we are truly badly organized. The qualitatively new organizational forms, the informal cadres that have been newly cultivated—and this [goes also for] the college during the ‘political university’ and during the strike in France and [our work with] with young workers—could not yet be introduced into a coordinated organizational framework. But it is not the case that only organizational chaos has been created; we have also developed new forms of organization. But if, with this background in mind, I now take seriously his (Habermas’s) claim, namely that we should have given up on the action, it would mean that the extra-parliamentary opposition should withdraw back into its organizational snail shell—so to speak—and give up on actions until it has organizationally regenerated. That, however, would be fatal for a socialist and anti-authoritarian movement which has constituted and reproduced itself so much in and through action. Secondly—and especially with regard to the action against Senghor—it was poorly prepared in terms of information for the reasons mentioned. The question, however, is whether, despite the overwhelmingly negative reactions that are to be expected from this action, it is not precisely such actions which could initiate a process of enlightenment. We must first of all create the potential that provides this enlightenment ourselves. This action itself can have an enlightening effect in retrospect. We have plenty of examples of such things. Enlightenment does not mean addressing <em>in abstracto</em> the population, which is an abstract statistical mass, but rather addressing certain relevant strata, just as the extra-parliamentary opposition itself developed by first mobilizing the university students, then secondary students, and then finally young workers.</p> <p>[Habermas interjects again: “Mr. Krahl, I mean only that an action must be justified such that one can themselves be convinced with good reason that they…”]</p> <p>Yes, naturally! If you are demanding a minimum of enlightenment, i.e. that those who act must themselves be enlightened about that which they are acting against, then that has been completely accomplished. The minimum of information has been given. It is sufficient if one is informed about which means a head of state uses in their own country against the proletariat (for example, the parachutists in France), informed about the means by which the basic foodstuff of a country—rice—is kept at a price level which is scarcely affordable for the poor, namely the fishers and peasants of the country. We have attempted, insofar as it was possible, to give this minimum of information in our teach-ins and furthermore to say something about the ideology which Senghor represents. I believe that such informational minimums, however imperfect, were warranted precisely in the context of such an action, an action which was not directed at a definite campaign, but was on the whole a single action. No one is demanding that the critical authorities run out in the streets with us and join in the Ho Chi Minh chant. Surely, however, they should be capable of devoting enough working time to be active not just with their pens, but also in the context of actions, if only in an advisory role. And then, Mr. Habermas, you could indeed—and this is again the typical topos—have said it beforehand and not once again <em>post festum</em> and retrospectively. One must be resolved to participate in the action in an organized manner, even if this organized participation consists only of enlightenment beforehand. Otherwise you will be exactly the type of intellectual that Max Horkheimer was talking about when he said that critique is only legitimate if one decides to participate in the organization and in action, but that bourgeois critique of proletarian struggle is a logical impossibility.</p> <p>[The discussion ends with von Friedeburg accusing Krahl of demagoguery for this invocation of Horkheimer.]</p> <h3 id="notes">Notes</h3> <p>[1] 23rd Delegate Conference. See neue kritik 50, Oktober 1968</p> <p>[2] Lukäcs, Methodisches zur Organisationsfrage, in: Geschichte und Klassenbewusstsein, Berlin 1923</p> <p>[3] Bedingungen und Organisation des Widerstandes. Der Kongress in Hannover, VoltaireFlugschrift 12, Berlin 1967, p. 101</p> <p>[4] Habermas, Die Scheinrevolution und ihre Kinder. Sechs Thesen über Taktik, Ziele und Situationsanalysen der oppositionellen Jugend. First in: Frankfurter Rundschau of 5 June 1968; then in: Die Linke antwortet Jürgen Habermas, Frankfurt 1968, p. 5ff. [Reprinted alongside related texts by Habermas in Volume II of Kraushaar’s Frankfurter Schule und Studentenbewegung]</p> <p>[5] Ibid., p. 12</p> <p>[6] On 29/30th of May [1968] the University [of Frankfurt] was occupied; it was renamed to Karl Marx University and a call for a political university was issued. See: Universität und Widerstand. Versuch einer politischen Universität in Frankfurt, Frankfurt 1968</p> <p>[7] Marcuse, Der eindimensionale Mensch, S. 267ff.</p> <h3 id="appendix">Appendix</h3> <p><a href="https://viewpointmag.com/2018/04/16/hans-jurgen-krahl-1943-1970/">Viewpoint Dossier on Krahl</a></p> <p><a href="http://www.krahl-briefe.de/">Krahl-Briefe</a></p> <p><a href="https://illwill.com/refusal">“Refusal Requires a Guerilla Mentality” by Dutschke and Krahl </a></p> <p><a href="http://www.hjki.de/links.html">Hans-Jürgen Krahl Institut</a></p> <p><a href="https://cominsitu.files.wordpress.com/2023/03/krahl-sage.pdf">Konstitution und Klassenkampf</a></p> <p><a href="https://cominsitu.wordpress.com/tag/hans-jurgen-krahl/">Other texts by/about Krahl in German and English</a></p> <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=65DpZBQab1w">Seminar on Krahl in English (ironically at Columbia University)</a></p> <p><a href="http://www.infopartisan.net/archive/1967/index.html">Website about the German student movement</a></p> <p><a href="https://field-journal.com/editorial/theodor-adorno-and-herbert-marcuse-correspondence-on-the-german-student-movement">Adorno-Marcuse correspondence on the student movement</a></p> <h3 id="intro-notes">Intro Notes</h3> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Link. https://www.ca-ira.net/verein/positionen-und-texte/bruhn-who-are-the-anti-germans/ <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Reinicke, Helmut. Für Krahl. http://www.mxks.de/files/kommunism/Reinecke.FuerKrahlt1.html <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Koenen, Gerd. “Der tranzendental Obdachslose — Hans-Jürgen Krahl.” p. 4 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Limone, Noa. “Germany’s Most Important Living Philosopher Issues an Urgent Call to Restore Democracy” Ha’aretz 2012. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Versions of both stories are recounted in Koenen’s essay “Der tranzendental Obdachslose;” the ‘incubus version’ of the nightmare story appears in Jäger’s Adorno: A Political Biography, as well in the comic I included. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Contrary to the received idea, it seems that Adorno himself did not dial the phone, rather he had the Hessian minister of education Ludwig von Friedeburg do it after Krahl and co. refused to leave “despite being asked three times to do so.” (Jäger, Adorno: A Political Biography, tr. Spencer. Yale UP, p. 203). In any case he had no problem with the decision to call the cops and followed it up by having Krahl charged with trespassing. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Claussen, Detlev. Theodor W. Adorno: One Last Genius. tr. Livingstone. Harvard UP, 2008, p. 336 <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Ibid. Claussen, p. 336 <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:9" role="doc-endnote"> <p>See his correspondence with Marcuse on the student movement and the texts “Marginalia to Theory and Praxis” and “Resignation” in Critical Models: Interventions and Catchwords. <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:10" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Link. https://field-journal.com/editorial/theodor-adorno-and-herbert-marcuse-correspondence-on-the-german-student-movement <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:11" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Angela Davis, “Marcuse’s Legacy,” in Herbert Marcuse: A Critical Reader, ed. John Abromeit and W. Mark Cobb (New York: Routledge, 2004), 46-47. <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:12" role="doc-endnote"> <p>Krahl. “The Political Contradictions in Adorno’s Critical Theory.” Translation modified. https://cominsitu.wordpress.com/2021/04/20/the-political-contradictions-in-adornos-theory-krahl-1971/#more-10079 <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>J.E. Morain</name></author><category term="translation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Origins of Studien über Autorität und Familie</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/origins_of_the_family/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Origins of Studien über Autorität und Familie"/><published>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/origins_of_the_family</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/origins_of_the_family/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post6-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post6-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post6-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post6.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="prefatory-remarks">Prefatory Remarks</h2> <p>This text is a relatively rough report on some ongoing research. I would like to look into the other archives of the Frankfurt School to explain some of the gaps I have encountered, but my situation presently militates against this possibility. This report is complementary to my forthcoming essay on Erich Fromm’s early work, to be published in the first volume of our e-journal later this year. In that essay I will analyze the way that psychoanalysis provided both a framework for conceptualizing different levels of mediation in society and a framework of micro-foundational processes, concepts, and mechanisms for explaining larger-scale social phenomena. The focus of this blog post is the pre-history of the Institute’s <em>Studien über Autorität und Familie</em>, but before getting into that, I would like to relate a few interesting findings related to Fromm that are only tangentially related to the <em>Studien</em>. I’d also like to thank Rainer Funk for allowing the use of quotations from the archival materials here and assisting me with the interpretation of certain documents.</p> <p>The Erich Fromm collection at the New York Public Library was deposited by Fromm in 1949 or 1950. It is accessible to the public so long as you first sign up for the NYPL system. The collection, or at least the part consisting of text, has been scanned into microfilm for preservation and easy access. The material ranges from early studies on the sociology of Jews to preliminary drafts and notes for mature works like <em>Escape from Freedom</em> (1941) and <em>Man for Himself</em> (1947). The correspondence preserved in this collection is unfortunately rather fragmentary, mostly being the letters received by Fromm. Unfortunately I was only able to visit the NYPL for a few hours and therefore had to carefully select documents to scan for further analysis. Luckily, I was able to find and scan several documents of interest in the brief time I had. (One document I found was a short essay in German on Marx’s value theory which had the letters “MH” at the top, possibly indicating that it was written by Max Horkheimer. I was, unfortunately, unable to scan this document, and hope to have a chance to do so in the future.)</p> <p>A number of interesting documents related to Wilhelm Reich are present in the archive, specifically in the Reich section of the correspondence. It seems that Reich and Fromm carried on a spirited debate about the merits of social psychology (or <em>Massenpsychologie</em>, as Reich still called it) in relation to individual psychology and sociology. Fromm believed a psychoanalytic social psychology to be possible and desirable, whereas Reich was skeptical about the possibility of applying concepts developed for individual psychology to society. Reich at one point requested Fromm to pass an essay onto the editors of the Institute’s <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em> for publication, but ultimately nothing came of this. Reich later requested the manuscript be returned. In the end, Reich would write a handful of reviews for the ZfS, however.<d-footnote>Reich reviewed Malinowsky’s (1930) Das Geschlechtsleben der Widen in Nordwestmelanesien for the ZfS in 1932 (<a href="/assets/pdf/Autorität/reich-geschlechtsleben-1932.pdf">PDF link </a>), as well as Gillin (1932) and Mangold’s (1932) Social Pathology texts together in a review for the ZfS in 1933 (<a href="/assets/pdf/Autorität/reich-social-pathology-1933.pdf">PDF link</a>). Several of Reich’s works were reviewed for the ZfS as well: Fromm reviewed Reich’s (1932) Der Einbruch der Sexualmoral for the ZfS in 1933 (<a href="/assets/pdf/Autorität/fromm-reich-review-1933.pdf">PDF link</a>); Karl Landauer reviewed Reich’s (1933) Massenpsychologie des Faschismus and Reich’s (1933) Charakteranalyse together in a review for the ZfS in 1934 (<a href="/assets/pdf/Autorität/landauer-reich-reviews-1934.pdf">PDF link</a>)</d-footnote>Reich and Fromm (and perhaps a few others) met several times in Switzerland in 1932. A conversation in August 1932 about (sado-)masochism and the follies of “race theory” was important enough to Fromm that he typed a short page of notes summarizing the conclusions of the discussion. It seems that it was Reich who convinced Fromm of the importance of (sado-)masochism for the understanding of human nature and society, an insight which Fromm passed onto the other members of the Institute. (Notably, however, masochism was never as central of an analytic concept for Fromm and the IfS as it was for Reich.) As for the question of “race theory,” they thought the fact that each presently living individual’s number of ancestors expands exponentially the further back in history one goes was sufficient to prove that “all [humans] are biologically related to one another,” and that supposedly hereditary traits should really be attributed to “psychological ancestors.” (At present, I don’t know what the concept of ‘psychological ancestors’ is supposed to mean. However, at the same time when Fromm and Reich were attempting to refute the concept of race, Fromm’s IfS colleague Karl August Wittfogel was attempting to integrate a vague, Lamarckian version of race theory into his formulation of historical materialism and apply this theory of race in his studies on ancient China.)</p> <h2 id="1-the-background-of-the-project">1 The Background of the Project</h2> <p>The anthology volume <em>Studien über Autorität und Familie</em> was published as the fifth volume of the <em>Schriften des Instituts für Sozialforschung</em> in 1936. It carried the subtitle <em>Forschungsberichte aus dem Institut für Sozialforschung</em>. The book is split into three (really more like four) divisions: <em>Theoretische Entwürfe über Autorität und Familie, Erhebungen, and Einzelstudien + Literaturberichte</em>. Max Horkheimer edited the first part, Erich Fromm the second, and Leo Löwenthal the third. Two of these divisions, <em>Erhebungen</em> and <em>Einzelstudien</em> are extremely fragmentary and are probably the reason that the disclaimer-like subtitle was added to the volume, although, as we will see, the entire structure of the published book was not the original intention.</p> <p>The study of German workers which was partially included in the <em>Studien</em> was first imagined in 1929, begun in 1930, and was announced to the public by Horkheimer in 1932. Work on it would continue past the publication of the <em>Studien</em> in 1936, only stopping in 1938 as the relations of the study’s director, Erich Fromm, to the rest of the Institute became increasingly strained.</p> <p>The <em>Studien</em> project had probably started in earnest by late 1933 (see footnote in <em>ZfS</em> II, p. 413), as the Institute (or rather Friedrich Pollock acting independently on behalf of the Institute, see Wiggershaus 1995, p. 150) had initiated several empirical studies on the family from their temporary base in Switzerland around the same time. Serious planning for the project seems to have started in 1934, however. This second, more serious phase saw the commissioning of essays from members and associates of the Institute as well as the holding of internal “seminar-style” discussions (see <em>Studien</em> p. IX) intended to produce “schemas” (see below) that could guide the writing process and inform the overall structure of the volume. According to Horkheimer, the main participants in these discussions were Fromm, Marcuse, Löwenthal, Wittfogel, and himself.</p> <h2 id="2-documents-from-1934">2 Documents from 1934</h2> <p>In the Erich Fromm collection of the New York Public Library, an early outline of <em>Studien</em> is preserved alongside a few other documents related to the project, such as early drafts of Fromm’s “Social-Psychological Part” essay, an outline of Horkheimer’s theoretical essay, and a full typescript of Wittfogel’s essay “Wirtschaftsgeschichtliche Grundlagen der Entwicklung der Familienautorität.” A number of letters related to the project are also preserved, such as one in which Löwenthal denigrates Marcuse’s contributions, an evaluation which was apparently common amongst the directors of the project.</p> <p>These documents offer a fascinating insight into the working process of the Institute for Social Research and show a more ambitious and systematically structured version of the <em>Studien</em> that was never realized. In this section, I will review several documents individually to demonstrate the insights that can be gleaned from them.</p> <h3 id="21-the-1934-outline-of-the-family-in-bourgeois-society">2.1 The 1934 Outline of “The Family in Bourgeois Society”</h3> <p>This document is a file folder (a <em>Soennecken’s Schnellhefter</em>) dated to the end of June 1934 labeled “Notizen über den Stand der Untersuchungen über die Familie” (Notes on the Status of the Investigations into the Family) containing five distinct documents: two pages of “preliminary notes” (<em>Vorbermerkungen</em>); an outline of an “anthology volume” (<em>Sammelband</em>) serving as the first of a series—the text is unclear but it seems to refer to a series of books on the family—to be titled “Die Familie in der bürgerlichen Gesellschaft;” a draft relating several conceptual “schemas” (<em>Schemata</em>) to be used for literature reviews (Chapter 2 of the book; see below for further details); another set of conceptual schemas for Chapter 4 (<em>Ueberbau. A. Staat und Recht</em>); and a preliminary report on the results of an empirical sociological study of experts (Erich Fromm Papers b. 7 f. 5 / r. 8; cf. <em>Studien</em> p. 292 ff). It is unsigned and contains no sentences in first person. Moreover, a number of different styles of handwriting appear throughout the document, likely indicating that multiple members of the IfS redacted/amended it. This hypothesis agrees with the consensus in the literature on the internal practices of the IfS. If I were forced to put a name to the document, I would probably assign it to Löwenthal or Pollock, although the content of it was undoubtedly arrived at by a collective process regardless of who actually operated the typewriter.</p> <p>The project seems to be divided into volumes, with the first entitled “Beiträge und Materialien mit besonderer Berücksichtigung des Autoritätsprobleme in der Familie” (Contributions and Materials with Special Attention to the Problem of Authority in the Family), although this could also be the subtitle of a single anthology volume titled “Die Familie in der bürgerlichen Gesellschaft.” It is further divided into three unlabeled parts which, based on Horkheimer’s notes, I designate as an introductory part, a theoretical part, and an empirical part. Each part was made up of several chapters, while each chapter had a director (<em>Leiter</em>), any number (often zero) of participants (<em>Mitarbeiter</em>), and any number (also sometimes zero) of texts designated with the somewhat ambiguous word <em>vorliegend</em>, the nature of which designation more is discussed below. The things designated as <em>vorliegend</em> seem to mostly be ongoing or already completed texts and pieces of research, although some are noted to have merely been ordered (<em>bestellt</em>) and at least one was “lacking manuscript.” Some of the things listed under <em>vorliegend</em>, such as “Talk H[orkheimer] in Centre” (<em>Rede H. im Centre</em>, see above image), are more mysterious. It is possible that this particular phrase refers to some record of a discussion involving or lecture by Horkheimer which took place in the Centre de Documentation of the École Normale Supérieure of Paris, whose director Celestin Bouglé had previously offered to house the Institute in the offices of said Centre (see Jay 1996, p. 30; Studien, p. VII).</p> <p>The introductory part was to include a chapter by Horkheimer which would serve “das Programm der ganzen Serie zu entwikkeln [sic]” (to develop the program of the entire series). Also covering the “Bedeutung des Problems in der Gesamttheorie” (the meaning of the problem in the theory as a whole) and a “Diskussion der anzuwendenden Methoden” (discussion of the methods to be used).</p> <p>The second and final chapter of the first part was to be a survey of the literature on the family from several major countries. This projected section was completed and incorporated into the final version with some modifications.</p> <p>The more interesting difference comes into focus with the second projected part of the work. It was to be divided according to the Marxist categories of base and superstructure, with one chapter (Chapter 3) on the economic infrastructure (<em>Unterbau</em>) in relation to the family directed by Friedrich Pollock and Andries Sternheim. Registered here are essays by Andries Sternheim and Hilde Weiss, among some other texts of an unclear nature. Abstracts of the essays by Sternheim and Weiss appeared in the final version of the book.</p> <p>This chapter was to be followed by three chapters on the superstructure covering “Staat und Recht;” “Erziehung (Theorie und Praxis);” and “Besondere Ideologien (Religion und Kunst)” (State and Law; Education (Theory and Practice); Specific Ideologies (Religion and Art)).” The first of these chapters—officially Chapter 4 of the work as a whole—is of especial interest for the referenced essay on the family in socialist political theory by Hans Mayer. In the published version, this was reduced to a review of the specifically anarchist literature on authority and the family. Of two further referenced essays on politics by sociologist Willi Strzelewicz, only one (“Aus den familienpolitischen Debatten der deutschen Nationalversammlung 1919”) was included—albeit as an abstract—in the final version. The only essay to be salvaged and published in full from this projected chapter was Ernst Schachtel’s “Das Recht der Gegenwart und die Autorität in der Familie.” The chapter was to be directed by Ernst Schachtel and Friedrich Pollock.</p> <p>The chapter on education was to be directed by Löwenthal and focus on “Die Dialektik der Relation Familie – Staat,” (the dialectic of the relation family-state) especially as analyzed through the political history of the past few decades. An essay by Franz Borkenau on the German youth movement was referenced and later actually published in full under the pseudonym Fritz Jungmann in the final version, while reports on different countries were to be made by various Institute associates, apparently including Karl and Hedda Korsch. None of those reports seem to have materialized in the form projected, or at least they were not published.</p> <p>The final chapter on the superstructure has a very barebones outline and mentions only two projected (and not yet available) contributions: an essay by Walter Benjamin on the “Theorie der Familie in der Belletristik” (Theory of the Family in the <em>Belles Lettres</em>) and one by Erich Fromm on “Katholische und Protestantische Anschauungen” (Catholic and Protestant Outlooks). The demand for an essay on the theory of the family in the <em>Belletristik</em> was apparently so urgent that the work of another author, Curt Wormann, on the topic ended up being included in the final version. The author of the document questions if this chapter should not be incorporated into chapter two (literature review) and makes a note of considering commissioning an essay on the family in “Schundlitertur”—a German word referring to something like pulp literature—from Benjamin.</p> <p>The second part was to be closed out by Chapter 7 (“Psychologie als Vermittlung,” directed by Fromm) and an “excursus” on “the family of primitives.” Chapter 7 was to include an essay by Fromm on authority, while the excursus was made up of either one or two essays on “Autorität bei primitiven Stämmen” (Authority in Primitive Tribes) written by Fromm and Paul Honigsheim either collaboratively or separately (the document has Honigsheim’s name listed under Fromm’s with the comment “dto,” that is, presumably, “ditto”). Fromm had a growing interest in ethnography in general and the work of Margaret Mead in particular around this time. In a note, the author of the document questions if these two chapters should not be incorporated into the first part of the book.</p> <p>The only worked out chapter of the third part (Chapter 8) was to be concerned with “Die Enqueten und ihre Auswertung,” (The Enquiries and their Evaluation) encompassing at least four different survey-based studies. Besides reports by Sternheim, Käthe Leichter, and the pair of Fromm and Schachtel, this chapter was to incorporate an explanation of the Institute’s approach to empirical research. In the final version, Fromm wrote a short essay on this topic (<em>Studien</em>, p. 231 ff).</p> <p>I have just given a pretty thorough list of all the texts etc. referenced as <em>vorliegend</em>, but I have not yet interrogated the meaning of this word in relation to the content of the projected volume. There are two possibilities: either each chapter was intended to be made up of separate texts/essays covering research by different authors, or each chapter was to be a newly written synthesis of the pieces of research which are marked as <em>vorliegend</em>. In favor of the latter interpretation is the remark about Chapter 2 that “when all the individual manuscripts [i.e. literature reviews] are ready, it will be probably be necessary not merely to redact them, but rather to combine them into one whole report.” A similar remark is made about of Chapter 3: “the work which is presently ready is for this purpose [i.e. the investigation into how economic factors effect the family] usable only as raw material.” There is also Horkheimer’s comment in the foreword to the published <em>Studien</em>, dated April 1935, “most of the reports on different subjects and countries, the monographs on seemingly distant problems, <em>were not originally destined for publication</em>” (<em>Studien</em>, p. XI; my emphasis). On this interpretation of the document, the <em>Studien</em> was originally intended to be a synthetic work which did not merely report on the research of the Institute but forged this research into a systematic whole structured and presented on the basis of certain fundamental categories from Marxism. (The only text from the Institute which achieves something even remotely like this hypothetical collaborative-synthetic form is the much later <em>Aspects of Sociology</em> (1956) which was credited to the Institute as a whole but written mainly by Heinz Maus, Hermann Schweppenhäuser, Ernst Kux, and Johannes Hirzel, all of whom were students of Adorno and Horkheimer). If this interpretation is correct, then the three long theoretical essays by Horkheimer, Fromm, and Marcuse may represent the only ‘synthetic’ chapters which had achieved completion by the time the book had to go to the press. Moreover, this interpretation would lend some evidence to the idea of Helmut Dubiel that the Institute’s theoretical practice was structured around a dialectic of empirical social research (<em>Forschung</em>) and theoretical presentation (<em>Darstellung</em>), although the dialectic implicit in this document does not correspond exactly to Dubiel’s reconstruction (see Part II in Dubiel 1985). (In my opinion, Dubiel was absolutely correct that there was a dialectic of research and presentation at work, but I disagree strongly with the way he attempted to reconstruct this dialectic.) I should be clear that no matter which interpretation is adopted, the document makes it clear that a more systematic structure was originally planned for the book in any case. The question is mainly the <em>degree</em> of systematicity, although the difference between a systematic categorization (and partial revision) of already finished texts and the synthetic re-presentation of their research-content in an integrated form is a difference which implies a dialectical transition from quantity to quality. I myself am not sure which interpretation I find more likely.</p> <p>Now that I have summarized all the content that was intended to be included in this volume and speculated about its structure, I will reveal how long Horkheimer planned this book to be. The first page of the outline clearly states that the entire thing is supposed to be “[circa] 30 Bogen” (about 30 sheets), with each part being 10 sheets. No matter how this is calculated (i.e., if 30 is multiplied by 16, 32, 64, etc.), the result is either that the final length of around 1,000 pages was planned from the start—in which case the author overestimated how much could be fit in 1,000 pages—or that the author initially projected a shorter length of perhaps 500 pages. Either way, the projected length is too short to accommodate his ambitious plans, as he himself related in the foreword to the volume: “The disproportion of the space available for the publication as a whole and the prepared [<em>vorliegeden</em>] scientific material has made itself especially palpable in the third division [of the book]” (<em>Studien</em>, p. XI). It is even more strange because the project does not seem to have been originally intended as a collection of mere <em>Forschungsberichte</em> (research reports) and abstracts of essays not printed in full. (One would wonder why so much editorial work would be needed for such a project.) For example, the essay by Fromm which was eventually repurposed as part of the first section of the final book went through multiple fairly different versions and was originally intended to be part of a chapter on “psychology as mediation,” not merely an essay which presents the problem of authority in the family social-psychologically (see <em>Studien</em>, p. IX). (Indeed Fromm’s essay is really the odd one out in the first section of the book in terms of content and overall ‘vibe.’) That said, the original sub/title “Contributions and Materials with Special Attention to the Problem of Authority in the Family” does not really testify to any particular form, and in all its vagueness could be interpreted as something similar to <em>Forschungsberichte</em>.</p> <h3 id="22-the-schemas">2.2 The Schemas</h3> <p>SCHEMAS FOR CHAPTER 2 (“ENTWURF FÜR DIE ANWEISUNGEN AN DIE LITERATURBERICHTERSTATTER”)</p> <p>(1.) Entstehung und Geschichte der Familie</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>Theorien</th> <th>Beispiel</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>a</td> <td>statische 1. bürgerliche Monogamie2. ethnologische Monogamie</td> <td>[bürgerliche Familie] Prototyp Pygmäen</td> </tr> <tr> <td>b</td> <td>evolutionistische 1. mutterrechtliche 2. sonstige</td> <td>Promiskuität Kulturkreistheorie</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>(2.) Funktion der Familie in der Gesellschaft</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>Theorien</th> <th>Beispiel</th> <th>idealistisch</th> <th>materialistisch</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>a</td> <td>biologisch-physiologisch</td> <td>Fortpflanzung</td> <td>Erhaltung der Menschheit</td> <td>Befriedigung der Naturtriebe</td> </tr> <tr> <td>b</td> <td>ökonomische</td> <td>Produktions- und Konsumptions- [Gemeinschaft?]</td> <td>Mehrerin des Familienguts</td> <td>Ausbeutung von Familienmitgliedern</td> </tr> <tr> <td>c</td> <td>soziologistisch</td> <td>Familie [ausgezeichnet?] [gesellschaftlicher] Gebilde</td> <td>Keimzelle der Gesellschaft</td> <td>Keimzelle der Gesellschaft*</td> </tr> <tr> <td>d</td> <td>sozial-psychologistisch</td> <td>Einordnung des Nachwuchs in [die] [bestehende?] Gesellschaft</td> <td>Trägerin kultureller Traditionen</td> <td>Vermittlerin von Ideologien</td> </tr> <tr> <td>e</td> <td>personal-psychologistisch</td> <td>Schutz des Privatlebens</td> <td>Heim als Reservat</td> <td>Befriedigung gesellschaftlich nicht [befriedete] Triebe</td> </tr> <tr> <td>f</td> <td>religiöse</td> <td>Trägerin religiöser Traditionen</td> <td>Trägerin religiöser Traditionen</td> <td>– – – –</td> </tr> <tr> <td>g</td> <td>philosophische</td> <td>Objektivierung von Ideellem</td> <td>Stufe des objektiven Geistes</td> <td>– – – –</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>*In the typescript the phrase “Keimzelle der Gesellschaft” is written so as to occupy both cells</p> <p>(3.) Funktionen der einzelnen Familienmitglieder</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Familienmitglied</th> <th>Beispiel</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Vater</td> <td>Verantwortung für die Kindererziehung</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Mutter</td> <td>Sorge für Sachgemässe Verwendung des Haushaltsguts</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Kind</td> <td>Verantwortung für das Alter der Eltern</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>SCHEMAS FOR CHAPTER 2 — ENGLISH TRANSLATION (“Draft for the Instructions to the Writers of the Literature Reports”)</p> <p>(1.) Emergence and History of the Family</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>Theories</th> <th>Example</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>a</td> <td>static 1. Bourgeois monogamy 2. Ethnological monogamy</td> <td>[bourgeois family] prototype pygmies</td> </tr> <tr> <td>b</td> <td>evolutionist 1. matriarchal 2. other</td> <td>Promiscuity Kulturkreis (culture-circle) theory</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>(2.) Function of the Family in Society</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th> </th> <th>Theories</th> <th>Example</th> <th>idealist</th> <th>materialist</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>a</td> <td>biological-physiological</td> <td>Reproduction</td> <td>Continuance of the human race</td> <td>Satisfaction of natural drives</td> </tr> <tr> <td>b</td> <td>economic</td> <td>[community?] of production and consumption</td> <td>Accumulator [Mehrerin] of family goods</td> <td>Exploitation of family members</td> </tr> <tr> <td>c</td> <td>sociological</td> <td>Family [displays?] [social] forms</td> <td>Germ-cell of society</td> <td>Germ-cell of society*</td> </tr> <tr> <td>d</td> <td>social-psychological</td> <td>Incorporation of offspring [into] [existing?] society</td> <td>Bearer of cultural traditions</td> <td>Mediator/transmitter of ideologies</td> </tr> <tr> <td>e</td> <td>personal-psychological</td> <td>Protection of private life</td> <td>Home as a reserve</td> <td>Satisfaction of socially not [satisfied] drives</td> </tr> <tr> <td>f</td> <td>religious</td> <td>Bearer of religious traditions</td> <td>Bearer of religious traditions</td> <td>– – – –</td> </tr> <tr> <td>g</td> <td>philosophical</td> <td>Objectivation of the ideal</td> <td>Level of objective spirit</td> <td>– – – –</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>*In the typescript the phrase “Keimzelle der Gesellschaft” is written so as to occupy both cells</p> <p>(3.) Functions of the individual Family Members</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Family member</th> <th>Example</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Father</td> <td>Responsibility for the education of children</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Mother</td> <td>Care for the proper use of household goods</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Child</td> <td>Responsibility for the old age of parents</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Above are reproduced the three schemas for Chapter 2. The purpose of these schemas is explained in the <em>Vorbemerkungen</em>:</p> <blockquote> <p>The goal of the heretofore completed discussions consists above all in the drafting of schemas for the individual chapters of the entire provisional structure; the individual assignments should go out to the participants on the basis of these schemas. They are a—relatively crude—means for [bringing about?] a common understanding of the goal of the work in the closest circle of participants as well for the creation of a certain methodological unity in the construction of the specific assigned projects.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Das Ziel der derzeitig geführten Besprechungen besteht vor allem darin, Schemata für die einzelnen Kapitel der vorläufigen Gesamtgliederung zu entwerfen; auf Grund dieser Schemata sollen dann die einzelnen Aufträge an die Mitarbeiter herausgehen. Sie sind ein—relativ rohes—Mittel, um der gemeinsamen Verständigung über das Ziel der Arbeit im engsten Kreise der Mitarbeit zu [erziehen, crossed out and corrected to dienen?] und andererseits eine gewisse methodische Einheitlichkeit in der Anlage der zu vergebenden Sonderarbeit herzustellen.</p> </blockquote> <p>At the time that these texts were written, the discussions intended to produce these schemas had only reached up to the subject matter of the fourth projected chapter (Superstructure: State and Law), while the discussions about the third chapter (Economic Infrastructure) had not yet reached the point where a useful schema could be produced.</p> <p>The schemas for Chapter 2 were intended to communicate the difference between a materialist and idealist approach to the family. The content is deliberately somewhat vague, as they were only meant to illustrate the general viewpoint, not provide strict guidelines. A particularly interesting (or amusing) part of this schema is the claim that the idea that the family’s function is to “preserve the human race” is idealism and the counterpart claim that according to materialism it merely functions to “satisfy natural drives.”</p> <p>There are two schemas for Chapter 4 (“Familie, Recht und Staat”). One is numbered I, II, III. Section I of the first schema divides up different sources / areas of inquiry (<em>Quellen</em>), namely “private law/right;” “public law/right;” and “general doctrine of state (<em>Staatslehre</em>) and politics.” Section II of the first schema (“Gliederung nach Familienstruktur”) is like this:</p> <ol> <li>Familie als Ganzes</li> <li>Mann – Frau</li> <li>Eltern – Kinder</li> <li>Geschwister</li> <li>Aszendenz</li> </ol> <p>Finally Section III of the first schema (“Gliederung nach Funktionen [Realität und Ideologie]):</p> <ol> <li>Biologische, Fortpflanzung, Bevölkerung</li> <li>Sexuelle, Sexualrecht und Einfluss auf Sexualmoral</li> <li>Erziehung, Einordnung des Nachwuchses in bestehende Gesellschaft, vermittelt durch</li> <li>Familie (</li> <li>Staat ( Verhältnis der 3 Faktoren zueinander</li> <li>Kirche (</li> <li>Ökonomische, Privateigentum, Arbeitsmarkt</li> </ol> <p>The second schema for Chapter 4 is split into A, B, and C sections. A is labelled “Mittels des Rechts zur Regelung der Autorität in der Familie (berücksichtigt werden nur die modernen Kulturstaaten).” B is “Typenbildung (etwa extrem autoritativer Typ, kirchlich feudal konservativer Typ, liberalistisch bürgerlicher Typ, extrem autoritätsloser Typ).” C is “Ideologie und Realität.”</p> <h3 id="23-early-drafts-of-essays">2.3 Early Drafts of Essays</h3> <p>I mentioned above that I found early versions of Horkheimer’s “Allgemeiner Teil” and Fromm’s “Sozial-psychologischer Teil” essays. I would like to comment on them very briefly.</p> <p>Horkheimer’s text—titled “Die gesellschaftliche Bedeutung der Autorität in der gegenwaertigen Familie” and dated to October 16, 1934—appears in an early outline form. The form is very similar to Horkheimer’s earlier “Notes on Science and the Crisis,” a text which itself was merely an outline of a longer essay which Horkheimer was unable to complete in time for the first volume of the <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em> on account of an illness. After a page of methodological <em>Vorbemerkungen</em>, the draft is divided into four parts: “I. Die Bedeutung des Kittbegriffs fuer die Theorie der Gesellschaft;” “II. Allgemeines zur Bedeutung der Autorität;” “III. Die Autorität in der Familie;” and “IV. Die Dialektik der Autorität.” Each part is composed of numbered paragraphs, which are themselves made up of a mix of grammatically coherent sentences and fragments. Sections II and III mostly correspond to the versions found in the final essay. The final version of Section I was renamed to “Culture,” and the cement concept (which Horkheimer calls the “Inbegriff der kulturellen, sozialen, seelischen Maechte”) was largely abandoned. In the draft, Horkheimer contrasts “cement” to ideology, stating that the latter “ist falsches, gesellschaftliches Bewusstsein und gehoert eindeutig zu den hemmenden Momenten einer geschichtlichen Periode,” while cement “kann sowohl ein produktives Element sein,” etc. In any case, Horkheimer’s reasons for changing this part of the essay remain unclear to me. It seems unlikely that it was provoked by tensions between Fromm and Horkheimer or anything of that nature.</p> <p>The reasons for changing Section IV are not so opaque, however. The outline of Section IV consists of a numbered list of three phrases, like so:</p> <ol> <li>Zerfallende Autorität</li> <li>Autorität und Revolution</li> <li>Die Familie in und nach der Revolution</li> </ol> <p>Given the established practice of self-censorship in the writings of the Frankfurt School, it is understandable why this Section was deleted entirely, the final essay only having a passing gesture towards the end of the family built on a reference to Henry Lewis Morgan. The topic of “Autoriät und Revolution” was briefly covered in the final book in Marcuse’s “Ideengeschichtlicher Teil” essay with reference to Engels, Lenin, and even Stalin.</p> <p>There are three drafts of Fromm’s essay. Two versions titled “Zur Psychologie der Einstellung zur Autorität” and another titled “Zur psychologischen Struktur der Autorität.” Parts of all of these were incorporated into the final version. The differences in terms of content between these early versions and the final essay are rather minor. There are a handful of overtly political passages that seem to have been excised, and a review of the psychological and psychoanalytic literature on authority was ultimately not included. This is the extent of the changes. I don’t analyze these documents in depth in my upcoming essay on Fromm, but I do reference them and quote from them.</p> <h2 id="3-conclusions-and-questions">3 Conclusions and Questions</h2> <p>These documents confirm several aspects of the Institute’s practices that have been reported in the literature. Political self-censorship makes an appearance, as does a process of theoretical coordination lead by Horkheimer. The ambitious scope of the outline also testifies to the tendency of Horkheimer et al to underestimate the difficulties involved in completing the projects they set for themselves, although this tendency was also be readily observed in other, posthumously published internal documents. Above all, the fundamentally Marxist orientation of the Institute is shown in these documents.</p> <p>Below is a table which shows the fate of all of the texts mentioned in the outline, whether they made it into the final version in a form similar to what is described or implied by the outline, and so on. Many of the texts eventually included in the <em>Einzelstudien</em> section of the published book do not appear at all in the 1934 outline.</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>Text</th> <th>Appears in book? (Y = yes; A = abstract; N = no; D = different author; R = substantially revised)</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td>Horkheimer: The Problem</td> <td>YR</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Marcuse: Historical Essay</td> <td>Y(R?)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Marcuse: Report on German Sociology</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Report on Nazi Sociology</td> <td>DY (-&gt; Meusel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Bouglé-Schüler: Report on French Sociology</td> <td>DY (-&gt; Honigsheim)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Rumney: Report on English Sociology</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Report on American Sociology</td> <td>DA (-&gt; Calhoun)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Sternheim: Economy and the Family</td> <td>YA</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Weiss: Conjuncture and Family</td> <td>YA</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Pollock: Economy</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Schachtel: Family and Law</td> <td>Y</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Schachtel: Authority and Law</td> <td>YR? (probably partially incorporated into the final essay, which covers law, family, and authority)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Strzelewicz: Family in political programs</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Strzelewicz: Family in the German national convention</td> <td>YA</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Mayer: Family in socialist theory and political programs</td> <td>YR (revised to be about anarchism in particular)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Borkenau: Youth movement</td> <td>Y (published under the pseudonym Fritz Jungmann)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Löwenthal/Karsen: Report on education in Germany</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Leichter: Report on education in Switzerland</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Leichter: Report on education in Austria</td> <td>DY (-&gt; Jahoda-Lazarsfeld)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Piaget-Schüler: Report on education in France</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Karl Korsch: Report on Education in England</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Hedda Korsch: Report on Education in Scandinavia</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Benjamin: Family in Belles Lettres</td> <td>DA (-&gt; Wormann)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Fromm: Catholics and Protestants</td> <td>N</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Fromm: Authority</td> <td>YR</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Fromm: Authority in Primitive Tribes</td> <td>N or DY (-&gt; Wittfogel)</td> </tr> <tr> <td>Honigsheim: Authority in Primitive Tribes</td> <td>N or DY (-&gt; Wittfogel)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>A number of problems are also posed by the difference between the 1934 and 1936 versions of the project. Which interpretation of its form is correct? Why was so much of the political content scrapped? Was this the result of circumstance or did pragmatic motivations enter into it? Why was the conceptual-thematic organization of the material abandoned? To what extent were the “schemas” of the materialist approach to the family drawn up by Horkheimer imposed by the editors/directors on the individual contributors? (Was that extent a matter of policy or the result of organizational-technical constraints?) Does the relative dearth of economic material (nothing by Pollock, Weiss’s essay only as an abstract) indicate that the difficulties mentioned by Horkheimer in the <em>Vorbermerkungen</em> persisted throughout 1934 and 1935, leading to an inability to synthesize a coherent viewpoint on the contemporary economy? Was such an inability symptomatic of a larger problem? Horkheimer claims (<em>Studien</em> p. X) in the 1935 preface to the final version that Pollock had drafted an essay on the economic aspects of the problem of authority in the family, but no such essay appears in the 1934 outline of the book. (Unless, of course, one adopts the ‘synthetic’ interpretation of the 1934 outline).</p> <p>In the main, these questions can be answered by claiming that either organizational and technical issues impeded the more ambitious initial outline or that political and theoretical changes occurred between 1934 and 1936 which made Horkheimer and the other editors significantly overhaul their design. I am more partial to the former kind of answer. Some of the alterations and deletions, above all the removal of the section on revolution in Horkheimer’s theoretical essay, strike me as politically motivated, but most do not. Definitive answers to the questions posed by this preliminary research can only be answered on the basis of further archival work. Unfortunately, few scholars were interested enough in this work to ask the members of the Institute about its genesis while they were still around.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bibliography">Bibliography</h2> <p>The <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em> is cited as (<em>ZfS</em> [volume in roman numerals], [page number]). The Erich Fromm Papers at the New York Public Library are cited as (Erich Fromm Papers b. [box number], f. [file number] / r. [microfilm reel number]; [title of document], [page or section number]).</p> <p>Dubiel, <em>Helmut. Theory and Politics: Studies in the Development of Critical Theory</em>. TR. Benjamin Gragg. MIT Press, 1985.</p> <p>Jay, Martin. <em>The Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute of Social Research 1923-1950</em>. U of California Press, 1996.</p> <p>Institut für Sozialforschung. <em>Studien über Autorität und Familie: Forschungsberichte aus dem Institut für Sozialforschung</em>. Dietrich zu Klampen Verlag, 1963. (reprint of original 1936 edition).</p> <p>— <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em></p> <p>Wiggershaus, Rolf. <em>The Frankfurt School: Its History, Theories, and Political Significance</em>. Tr. Michael Robertson. MIT Press, 1995.</p>]]></content><author><name>J.E. Morain</name></author><category term="archive"/><category term="translation"/><category term="study"/><category term="report"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A report on the early history of the Institute for Social Research's Studien über Autorität und Familie project]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The concept of language and linguistic presentation in Horkheimer and Adorno, by Hermann Schweppenhäuser (1986)</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/language/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The concept of language and linguistic presentation in Horkheimer and Adorno, by Hermann Schweppenhäuser (1986)"/><published>2024-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/language</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/language/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Translator’s note:</strong><d-footnote>[Translator’s fn.] Translation from: © Springer-Verlag GmbH Deutschland, ein Teil von Springer Nature 2019. T. Friedrich, S. Kramer, G. Schweppenhäuser (Hrsg.), Hermann Schweppenhäuser: Sprache, Literatur und Kunst, https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-476-04763-2_4; See fn. 3 below for information on original publication (1986)</d-footnote> This essay by <a href="https://aktuelles.uni-frankfurt.de/english/bequest-of-philosopher-hermann-schweppenhaeuser/">Hermann Schweppenhäuser (1928-2015)</a>, a ‘second generation’ student of the ‘first generation’ of critical theory and contemporary of Oskar Negt and Jürgen Habermas, seemed to warrant translation for three reasons: (1) the essay is a careful study of Adorno and Horkheimer’s hyper-conscious method or mode of presentation (<em>Darstellungsweise</em>) that has vexed readers of their <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em> (1947) since its publication; (2) Schweppenhäuser grounds Adorno and Horkheimer’s vexing stylistic approach in their fragmentary, but illuminating, remarks on language (and their first attempts to formulate a concept or theory of language) on the one hand and their common, if independently developed, idea of philosophy as the delicate work of critical and (historical-)materialist interpretation on the other; (3) the author shows how Adorno and Horkheimer not only anticipate the ‘pragma-linguistic reformulation’ of critical theory in the work of Jürgen Habermas, but also that the ‘first generation’ of critical theory self-consciously defended, in the content and form of their writing, an idea of true <em>communio</em>: communism understood as the unity of concessionless free association and coercionless planning – often in the formulation of a <em>rational</em>, rather than merely rationalized, and <em>human society</em> – that still served as the guiding normative ideal for both Adorno and Horkheimer through the end of the 1940s. Moreover, they defend this idea from the illusory ‘pseudo-democratic’ reconciliations to be won from the refinement of communication or communicative rationality under the mutilating conditions of the compulsory normative orders of everyday life (e.g., of ‘ordinary language,’ of ‘common sense,’ of the ‘lifeworld’) in late capitalist society.</p> <p>The translator’s hope is that the reconstruction Schweppenhäuser gives of unity of form and content in Adorno and Horkheimer’s mode of presentation, including their reasons for adopting such a mode in the first place, will be useful for future anglophone readers of the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em> who are as dissatisfied with its ham-fisted reception – at the hands of generations of readers who could never distinguish between performative and dialectical contradictions – as they are exasperated by the text of the infamous book itself.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post5-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post5-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post5-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post5.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> [Picture] Newspaper clippings from “Science Probes the Anti-Semite” in “The Jewish Community Bulletin” (San Francisco, California). June 7, 1946.<d-footnote>[Translator’s fn.] Published in: Schmid Noerr, G., Ziege, EM. (eds) Zur Kritik der regressiven Vernunft. Springer VS, Wiesbaden. (2019)</d-footnote> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="the-concept-of-language-and-linguistic-presentation-in-horkheimer-and-adorno-by-hermann-schweppenhäuser-1986">“The Concept of Language and Linguistic Presentation in Horkheimer and Adorno”, by Hermann Schweppenhäuser (1986)</h2> <p>Though Horkheimer and Adorno did not fully work out a theory of language, individual language-theoretical reflections scattered throughout their work, and unpublished during their lifetimes, form the elements of such a theory — sufficient, at least, for attesting to the linguistic reflection and self-reflection of critical theory and the intention behind these reflections.<d-footnote>[Editor’s fn.] On this see Gunzelin Schmid Noerr: “Truth, power and the language of philosophy. On Horkheimer’s linguistic-philosophical reflections in his posthumous writings between 1939 and 1946”, in: Max Horkheimer today: Work and Impact, edited by A Schmidt and N Altwicker, Frankfurt am Main 1986, pp. 349–370. – The synchronous arrangement of the two lectures dedicated to language problems during the conference prohibited their discussion in relation to each other; since the speakers were unable to discuss the matter together beforehand due to time constraints, they, like those interested, are referred to the print of both lectures in this volume as a belated starting point for the discussion. [Editor’s note: The contributions by Schweppenhäuser and Schmid Noerr both appeared in the above-mentioned conference volume Max Horkheimer today: Work and Impact.]</d-footnote>This was at a time when the self-critical linguistic turn of scientific and philosophical thinking was already underway, and even before critical theory itself achieved this in the form of methodological desiderata prior to the later, pragma-linguistic reformulation of critical theory.</p> <p>I would like to remind you of this today, to take the calendar occasion as a relevant one, in order to visualize the self-reflective state of this thinking in a language-reflective way. In so doing, I try to concentrate on some essential aspects of both authors’ concept of language and the way of using language – the linguistic presentation of knowledge – that it induces; to indicate the points from which the problem of language is viewed and can be illuminated. The achievement of language is illuminated in its strength and in its weakness and, in the process, a piece of the <em>enlightenment</em> of the <em>Enlightenment</em> is mastered. It turns out that proving one’s thinking on the matter – given the proximity of knowledge and language to one another – only seems easier than elsewhere; but this illusion is the transcendental linguistic illusion itself, which should not conceal from the discerning gaze what it conceals, that which manifests the illusion itself. The closeness of knowledge and language to one another also turns out to be a distortion of the two by each other, a figuration. As a <em>congealed dialectic</em> – which the authors seek to affirm dialectically. This is the core of their effort to find an adequate concept of language. Formulaically, it could be said that they visualize it in two basic elements: in language as a representation and as a manifestation of what is linguistically determined – in the ambiguity of its power to generalize the real and a counter-striving to its own expression of the generalized, including that of generalizing itself. It is the difficult concept of language as a polar arrangement, which Benjamin also asserted early on in his general linguistic treatise of 1916.<d-footnote>Cf. Walter Benjamin: Collected Writings, with the collaboration of TW Adorno and G Scholem, edited by R Tiedemann and Hermann Schweppenhäuser, Volume II, Frankfurt am Main 1977, p. 140 ff.; on the role of the treatise in Adorno’s thinking cf. Rolf Tiedemann: “Concept, image, name. About Adorno’s utopia of knowledge”, in: Hamburg Adorno Symposium, published by M Löbig and G Schweppenhäuser, Lüneburg 1984, p. 76 f. – Cf. also Hermann Schweppenhäuser: “Nome Logos Espressione. Elementi della teoria bejaminiana della lingua”, in: Walter Benjamin. Tempo, storia, liguaggio, edited by L Belloi and L. Lotti, Rome 1983, p. 49 ff. [The German version in this volume, pp. 159–174.]</d-footnote></p> <p>One could describe it, again formulaically and with the intention of providing preliminary orientation, something like this: <em>lingua index suae et rationis</em>, but the index itself is <em>illingual</em> in the sense that language, the objectification and self-illumination of reason – of the logos as word and as spirit – is at the same time also expression: manifestation of something other than language is – “a certain silent order of things,” to use Foucault’s words, a “subgrammar” that relates to the logical-linguistic in a similar way as the unconscious relates to the conscious, as subterranean to manifest history, so that both are in figuration, alternately concealing and yet also penetrating each other.<d-footnote>Michel Foucault: The Order of Things, Frankfurt am Main 1974, p. 23.</d-footnote> The problem of language is also posed in the sense of such figuration by Horkheimer and Adorno. The subject of the discussion is the language, energy and instinct of reason in its own light, and the language, ergon, work of history and the real subjects in it, in its side facing away from the light. Let me deal with both aspects, which cannot be separated from one another internally, one after the other, first with an emphasis on language as a conceptual representation and then on language as an expression. A few comments on the reflection of both authors’ concept of language – in the manner of their linguistic presentation itself – may conclude the visualization of their concept of language.</p> <h3 id="i">§I.</h3> <p>What do we learn from language, the way we use it to make judgments and statements, with regard to the real thing about which we say something and which we judge linguistically? Thus asks Horkheimer in an important reflection published from his estate.<d-footnote>Cf. Max Horkheimer: “Trust in History”, in: Neue Rundschau, Volume 95 (1984), H 1/2, p. 8 ff.; recently in: Max Horkheimer: Collected Writings, Volume XII, published by G Schmid Noerr, Frankfurt am Main 1985, p. 119 ff.</d-footnote> The answer is twofold: the strength of language is the weakness of its performance, and this weakness is precisely the strength of its intention. – Its strength is generalization: the predicate subsumes the subject “under terms that are the same for everyone.”<d-footnote>Ibid. p. 11.</d-footnote> The judgments are valid through the universality that they express linguistically: what they express makes them the existing norm, and the norm is founded in law. This is the conceptual realism of language, which itself gravitates towards nominalism. Because “the predicated universal” is “not appropriate to the individual that it is supposed to apply to. The predicate seeks to concretize the subject through something abstract, to determine it through something indefinite.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This means that “the name of the subject is provisional,” “the predicate wants to find the right one, the one that unlocks its secret.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote></p> <p>It turns out that “the judgment is an attempt” – an attempt that cannot stop, even and especially with the success of generalization – namely to help the real “to express what it cannot say in its silence. That is the meaning of language, which it always intends despite its weakness.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> – From the other side, this weakness is its strength – strength in the fatal sense. It wants to do justice to the “unique particular”;<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> but the universal with which it identifies the particular in the judgment is “always its doom.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> “Also” – so initially none. Because insofar as language identifies the universal in the individual, it meets with disaster. The fact that the individual is human logically protects him from being treated and destroyed as a non-human. As a human being, he has attributes whose political expression is, for example, human rights, which he is essentially entitled to. If they are not respected, it is a violation of the logic and truth in which they are based by virtue of being, the copula. But what is the basis of the power that so easily overrides logic and truth: the irrational? – The universal is “always fatal” to the particular. For example, in the definition of human rights as bourgeois rights: that of the free and the property-owning, which excludes the unfree and the property-less. To this extent, rationality itself is also the irrational: reason that is done to the subject, that happens to the subject in a nemesis-like manner on both sides of particularization.</p> <p>The truth of the universal shows itself as an enlightened myth, the universals are the demythologized gods who controlled destinies, just as the gods turned out to be the personified natural power. The nature clarified in myth and the myth clarified in rationalism re-emerge conceptually in the universal as the ideas, forms, laws to which the individual is ‘objectively’ subject. They “express the finiteness,” the disappearance “of the particular: because the subject is an animal, a human being, a man, it must come to nothing. The judgment conceives the living merely as nature, even when it thinks of the particular not in physical but in social categories, as a nation or state.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 11 f.</d-footnote></p> <p>This is the real, the historical realism of language, the one that denounces the ideal, the universal realism. With such a denunciation, language criticizes being, the copula, “because in the identity it creates, it logically suppresses in the subject what cannot develop in practice.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 11.</d-footnote> In this respect, words and concepts are actually adequate to what they capture – to the extent that they limit and imprison what they capture. This is the meaning of what Adorno called negative ontology, as he terms it in <em>Negative Dialectics</em>, in which identification is developed as the constraint that prevents the non-identical from achieving its own identity.<d-footnote>The logical place of the aesthetic theory can also be identified in Horkheimer’s text; It was preceded by a phase of particularly intense joint reflection by both authors since 1939; cf. Horkheimer, ‘Trust in History’. p. 14.</d-footnote> – That criticism of being emerges from the specifying, restricting, negating predication itself: the universal becomes “a negative in language, which it says for denunciation. By subsuming, it specifies suffering.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote></p> <p>As a consequence, it is the negation of every predicative judgment as predicative: the immanently forced progression of judgment, which tends to the downfall of predication by name – in the sense of the innermost nominalistic tendency, that of the recognition of the individual res as an indesignable thing in itself.<d-footnote>Tiedemann’s in-depth investigation is dedicated to the utopia of language as one of names and its inseparability from the innermost intention of knowledge, as one of the centers of Adorno’s thinking, which points out the limit in advance to the misinterpretation of aesthetic theory as a capitulation of thought to art; cf. Tiedemann, Concept, Image, Name, p. 67 ff.</d-footnote> But nominalism – according to both authors – capitulates to the name by which it is called and against whose innermost historical implications it unhistorically – and methodologically – blinds itself.<d-footnote>Cf. Max Horkheimer and Theodor W. Adorno: Dialectic of Enlightenment. Philosophical Fragments, Amsterdam 1947, p. 36.</d-footnote> In the text from 1946, Horkheimer says of the progression of judgment that it is the negation of the judgment as fixed and at least keeps the adequate predication open, at least as long as predication does not resolve itself and stand still in identity theses of the idealistic, universalistic kind or nominalistically resigns itself to the infinity of facts as what is merely designable. In this way, language and concept teach truth is dialectical, and that is why “Hegel [hits on] the spirit of language like no other: the determinacy of the finite that it expresses means at the same time its pain and its destruction.” “Whoever says being must necessarily mean power and death.” “The identification of language with truth is diabolical, just as the separation of truth from language is silent despair. This is the highest insight to which its penetration leads.”<d-footnote>Horkheimer, “Trust in History”, p. 13.</d-footnote></p> <p>Therefore, both positions on language that evade this are inappropriate to the insight: the one that idolizes language ontologically (which Hegel himself ultimately fell into with the absolutization of the logos in the face of its historically determined negation) as well as the one that is nominalistically silent. Nominalism is more honest, but at the price of the idea of truth, which linguistic absolutism turns into a lie. Both show themselves to be typical of the era, in the sense of the present, as “positivism”, which “declares language dead”, and as “fascism”, which “galvanises” it – as de-mythologization, the two forms of which determine each other.<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 11.</d-footnote> The scientifically illuminated language, like the galvanized language, is no longer able to express “the community of suffering”, which silences and neutralizes the community and transfigures the suffering, which they both accept.<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 15.</d-footnote> This happens to language and with it to people when it is deprived of expression, and no less to expression when it is deprived of language. That the linguistic term “freedom” aims “by concretely thinking about lack of freedom”; The fact that language points to reconciliation with the “power of determination through negation”, i.e. through one’s own weakness, disappears with the manipulated and idolized language.<d-footnote>Cf. Ibid.</d-footnote> The dialectic of language, which with its strength confesses its weakness and with weakness indicates healing from strength; which “only helps the living to express itself by making it the concept with which it coincides”;<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 22.</d-footnote> in which “fulfillment and suffering lie undivided” and which precisely preserves the possible divorce<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 12.</d-footnote>– this dialectic still remains to be taken at its word where idolized and correspondingly illuminated language takes the word away from us.</p> <p>This presupposes that language criticism remains secure in language, despite the distortions that happen to it – that which is objectively given and historically developed, which supports thought and expression, knowledge and criticism of the real.<d-footnote>Cf especially Theodor W. Adorno: “Theses on the language of the philosopher”, in: Adorno, Collected Writings, published by R Tiedemann, Frankfurt am Main 1973, Volume I, p. 366 ff. and the same: Jargon of Authenticity, in: Volume VI, Frankfurt am Main 1973, p. 413 ff. – On the criticism of operationalized language cf. Herbert Marcuse: One-dimensional Man. Studies on the ideology of advanced industrial society, Neuwied/Berlin 1967, especially: “The barrier of the universe of speech”, p. 103 ff. and “The triumph of positive thinking: one-dimensional philosophy”, p. 184 ff.</d-footnote> Just as memory is constitutive for thinking and knowing <em>in actu</em>, language – according to Hegel, a concrete sign of memory – is, inextricably, constitutive for the person currently formulating it.<d-footnote>Cf. G. W. F. Hegel: Complete Works, edited by H. Glockner, Stuttgart 1965, Volume X, System of Philosophy 3, § 458, 462.</d-footnote> “Universal concepts form the material of the presentation as well as names for individual things,” says the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em>. “The fight against universal concepts is pointless. However, this does not determine what the dignity of the universal is. The scale of genuses is not at the same time that of significance.” Repeating “the moments that present themselves as the same thing over and over again is more like a futile and compulsive litany than a redemptive word. Classification is a condition of knowledge, not knowledge itself, and knowledge in turn dissolves the classification” – so too in the sense of insight into its historical genesis.<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 260.</d-footnote> Without the light of the universal, the concept that creates consensus, there is no binding knowledge – but also no obligation, no compulsion of logic without the logic of coercion in historical reality. Concepts are immanently luminous reason-sense and transcendently sinister expression: that which also shapes autonomous reason heteronomously.</p> <p>In this sense, linguistic rationality is an expression of habituality as a form of socialization itself. And this is the result of the process of external and internal control of nature and its growing organization. Regarding the genesis, Horkheimer refers to Durkheim and the reflection of early forms of social organization in terms of logical classification,<d-footnote>CF Max Horkheimer; The Critique of Instrumental Reason. From the lectures and recordings since the end of the war, published by A Schmidt, Frankfurt am Main 1967, p. 105.</d-footnote>as well as the fact that the Platonic ideas reflect less the “secret affinities of things” than those of “power relations”, which, however, can be criticized again through those ideas.<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 169.</d-footnote> Reason in the bourgeois sense is a form of reflection of social intercourse, of developed exchange, and its rationality is as impressive as the reciprocal equivalence of rights and duties.</p> <p>Logic is “the money of the spirit” – this is how Marx summarizes in brilliant abbreviation the relationship between the real economic ground and the ground of knowledge, and how the latter can be rooted in the former.<d-footnote>Karl Marx: Economic-philosophical manuscripts, in: ibid. and Friedrich Engels, Works, published by the Institute for Marxism-Leninism at the Central Committee of the SED, supplementary volume, 1st part, Berlin 1968, p. 571.</d-footnote> The rationality in both is at the same time irrational, and “cleverness”, as it is provocatively called in the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em>, is also stupid. But the contradiction is necessary. Because the bourgeois rationality must claim universality and at the same time develop to limit it. Just as everyone gets their due in exchange and yet social injustice results from it, so too is the form of reflection in the exchange economy, the dominant reason, fair, universalistic and yet particularistic, the instrument of privilege-in-equality.<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 248.</d-footnote> Behind the clarity of the judgments of the One Reason are hidden the real opposites in which the subjects, the bearers of the One Reason,<d-footnote>Cf. Ibid., p. 102.</d-footnote>exist as privileged and unprivileged, as competent and incompetent. Here we need to measure the importance of an idea of ‘communicative reason’ and how it can seriously prove itself in the face of actual ‘asymmetrical communication’, according to the presentations of Habermas and Lorenzer.</p> <p>As long as the oppressed’s own silent language remains unheard and uninterpreted, prevailing reason itself proves to be deaf – as a deficiency in understanding, a form of reason in its own unreason. Institutionalized in the polished language of traffic, it makes itself incapable of knowledge, can no longer find the healing word, and the better the language and concept function, the more blind they become to their own meaning, the meaning and absurdity of functioning. This is reflected in Wittgenstein’s famous definition, according to which the “use of the word in language is its meaning”.<d-footnote>Ludwig Wittgenstein: Philosophical Grammar, in: ibid., Writings, Frankfurt am Main, Volume IV, § 23 (p. 60).</d-footnote> The meaning of the use itself, the trans-linguistic meaning and purpose, remains unconsidered and is itself repelled by the internally fixating logic of the whole occurence, the linguistic concept itself. The universalizing power of the rules of the game is beyond question – but the language is not exhausted in the rule-type of the game; its ‘reflexive’ sense – to use Apelsian-Habermasian terminology<d-footnote>Cf Jürgen Habermas: On the logic of the social sciences, Frankfurt am Main 1970, Part III, Chapter 7.</d-footnote>– inherently prohibits its ‘reduction’ to this type.</p> <p>Rather, the self-blinding purpose of mere functioning can only be read in the light of its reflexivity. This also applies to the different functionality of the word in terms of genus, insofar as it is a word of reflexive, non-reduced language. But what does the word and concept of reflexive language achieve? Horkheimer and Adorno put the matter to the test by contrasting the entire sphere of the logos – that of language and reason – with the sphere of wordlessness and reasonlessness – the silent world of the creature, against which language and reason would have to prove themselves. Do they? Does the humanistic logos seriously mean humanization of nature?</p> <h3 id="ii">§II.</h3> <p>“The lack of reason has no words,” says the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em>. “Eloquent is their possession, which prevails throughout manifest history. The whole earth bears witness to the glory of man” (the <em>zoon logon echon</em>). “In war and peace, arena and slaughterhouse, from the slow death of the elephant overpowered by primitive human hordes based on rudimentary planning, to the complete exploitation of the animal world today, the irrational creatures have always experienced reason. This visible process covers the invisible one: existence without the light of reason.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 295 f.</d-footnote></p> <p>“The world of the animal is without concepts. There is no word to capture the identical in the flow of what appears, the same species in the change of specimens, the same thing in the changed situations.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 296.</d-footnote> The “possibility of re-cognition”, which would go beyond the identification of the “vitally predetermined” – the situational context in the sense of Bühler, for example – is missing.<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> here is “no firm knowledge of the past and no clear foresight into the future. The animal listens to the name and has no self, it is enclosed within itself and yet exposed, a new compulsion always arises, no idea extends beyond it.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote></p> <p>The medium in which the coercion would be perceived as coercion is missing. This would mean consolation, awareness of happiness – liberating differentiation from burdens, from the constant sameness of being abandoned, the eternal readiness to react in fear. – Now to conclude as follows: ‘Because the idea, the liberating thought, is missing, unreasonable existence <em>is not perceived</em> as painful and <em>is not</em>, because only the idea and concept determine it as painful and horrifying in the sense of an idealistic constitution’ – this conclusion would be absurd. Fear and coercion of creaturely existence are only the epistemological consequence, but metaphysically the ground. Here the fundamentally materialistic meaning of this theory becomes apparent, which it shares with natural and historical philosophical materialism – on the one hand, with Schopenhauer and Schelling and through them with certain mystical theorems; on the other hand, with Vico, the French Enlightenment thinkers and Feuerbach and through them with Marx.<d-footnote>Cf. Max Horkheimer: Beginnings of the Bourgeois Philosophy of History, Stuttgart 1930, p. 95 ff.</d-footnote> The significance of these connections in critical theory as a ‘materialist theory of constitution’ has previously been illuminated by Schmidt;<d-footnote>Cf. Alfred Schmidt: “Max Horkheimer’s Spiritual Physiognomy”, in: Three Studies on Materialism. Schopenhauer. Horkheimer. The problem of Happiness, München/Wien 1977, p. 120 ff.</d-footnote> They are of greatest relevance precisely for Horkheimer and Adorno’s concept of language – this is due to the characteristic of language, according to which it is the signature, expression and manifestation of the real; of nature and history as a text to be read.<d-footnote>Cf. Horkheimer, The Critique of Instrumental Reason, p. 122.</d-footnote></p> <p>Spirit and idea, language and expression are then a consequence of that ground, however mediated they always are, and only become self-grounding after their emergence – historically – as knowing and conceiving, as language and text, as practice in the emphatic sense in the light of human – and creaturely – purposes; It is also worth remembering, in precisely this context, Benjamin’s concept of origin.<d-footnote>Cf. Walter Benjamin: Origins of the German Tragic Drama, in: Collected Writings, with the participation of TW Adorno and G Scholem, edited by R Tiedemann and Hermann Schweppenhäuser, 1974, Band I, p. 226.</d-footnote> – “In order to escape the boringly empty existence,” the authors continue, “a resistance is necessary, the backbone of which is language. Even the strongest animal is infinitely moronic.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 297.</d-footnote> It is true that “the animal soul […] contains the individual feelings and needs of humans, even the elements of the spirit,” but “without the support that only organizing reason provides.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote></p> <p>Their lack “banishes the animal in its form forever, unless the human being, who is one with it through the past, finds and speaks the redeeming word and through it softens the stone heart of infinity at the end of time.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> This is the materialist formulation of utopia here, in a significant way. – The entire discussion is important because of the aspect under which the animal psychological characteristics suddenly turn out to be human psychological ones: The animal soul shows itself to be the appropriate object of psychology because psychology sees it in the animal the form of psychological and spiritual mutilation and regression of people<d-footnote>Cf. Ibid., p. 296.</d-footnote>– of people who are forced to react in creaturely ways under the increased pressure of the existing situation, which include the reaction to signs and signals that serve the purpose of sheer survival – based on the system into which language tends to shrink in the biotechnical universe of society as a whole – as well as the variety of behavior of mimicry with the existing: in general the regression to blind, unsublimated mimesis.</p> <p>In doing so, the authors provide insight into one of the centers of the language problem. They consider the mimetic origin of language to be a given. It should be noted that the mimetic origin is not the same as what emerges from it – the emancipation from mimesis through language and concept, expression and symbolic manifestation, which remain intertwined with it. And the elucidation of the interconnection is what the theory is concerned with – whether it be called critical, dialectical or aesthetic theory. – In early mimesis, relating to the overpowering surrounding man, his unknown and his terror, this is separated from the sound with which man reacts to it: “The call of terror becomes his name. It fixes the transcendence of the unknown over the known.” “The doubling of nature” – “the echo of real superiority” – “comes from man’s fear, the expression of which becomes an explanation.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 26; This theory, as a theory of the origin of art based on ethno- and myth-psychology before the turn of the century, can already be found in Aby Warburg, with striking parallels to The Dialectic of Enlightenment.</d-footnote> This explanation is – as an echo – first tautology, mimetic tautology; then – through the fixation of the echo – the name of diffusely overpowering nature, which objectifies it into a numinous power over it. “Through the deity, language turns from tautology into language,” the one that expresses “the contradiction.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 26.</d-footnote></p> <p>The explanation of nature becomes possible as a predication and negating specification: first in the magical embryonic form of incantation, worship, the planned mimesis with the intention of gaining power over power – and that literally in the name of powers and gods -; then in the developed form, an explanation of nature first via the depersonalized, semi-mythical, semi-logical <em>archai</em> of the primordial philosophy; then via the ideas and forms of classical, the essences and substances of later metaphysics; finally in the critical and scientific principles and laws in which the entire linguistic rationalization process ends.</p> <p>This turns out to be dialectical: The original explanation that produced and developed the meaning and meaning of language, shrinks back to naked denomination and designation and establishes the starting point on a higher scale – the scientifically explained through and through and with the operationalized explanation, the technical – in contrast to the magical – universe, which can really be successfully determined, reveals the lack of meaning that provoked the fear of orientation in the beginning. The fully oriented, ‘informed’ world produces a complete horror of itself. The devastating nature of a lack of <em>meaningful</em> language – rather than just <em>informed</em> language in the strictest sense of the word – is becoming evident. The state loses the expression in which it could contain itself, understand itself, without losing the expression with the grasp, the concept. If such expression threatens to become impossible as a whole – hence Adorno’s paradox of the <em>whole is the false</em> -, so it remains as an individual, as a specific expression of the whole: it can be deciphered by the individual forces and powers that shape it.</p> <p>This is where the objective and methodical sense of a concept of philosophy as interpretation becomes apparent – which Adorno postulated early on, in the programmatic inaugural speech of 1931,<d-footnote>Cf. Theodor W. Adorno: “The Actuality of Philosophy”, in: Collected Writings, edited by R. Tiedemann, Frankfurt am Main 1973, Band I, p. 325 ff.</d-footnote>and which Horkheimer used in historical-philosophical terms even before that, in 1930,<d-footnote>Cf. Max Horkheimer: “Vico and mythology”, in: Horkheimer, Beginnings of the Bourgeois Philosophy of History; One of the key ideas can be found on page 110: “There is no pre-established harmony between the social expressive value of creative achievements and the individual intention on which they are based. The works only gain transparency in the course of history”: through interpretation.</d-footnote>before he grasped it in a decidedly programmatic way,<d-footnote>Cf. Max Horkheimer: “The Concept of Philosophy”, in: Horkheimer, The Critique of Instrumental Reason, p. 153 ff.</d-footnote>and which both then practiced in central pieces of the <em>Dialectic of Enlightenment</em> and since then. As Tiedemann showed in his study of the relationship between language and knowledge in Adorno, which must be explicitly mentioned here, it was Horkheimer, who, on the occasion of Adorno and Benjamin’s debate about the concept of the dialectical image, gave the discussion the decisive turn in terms of expression and theory of interpretation with the reference to the key phenomenon of the commodity, Marx’s commodity fetish as an historical-objective, expressive character.<d-footnote>Cf. Tiedemann, Concept – Image – Name, p. 73.</d-footnote></p> <p>The “word before its rationalization,” both authors write, had “unleashed” the “longing” for the meaning of something different and better.<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 195.</d-footnote> It marks the dividing line between the world of the logos and the silent world and thus points to the overcoming of the boundary as a strictly separating one, in both the synchronic and diachronic sense. If in the world of light, the identifying concepts dominate as names of order and classification – in an historically significant sense, for example, the patriarchal one, in which the strictly matriarchal itself is universalized -, then they show their expressive character on the side facing away from the light in the border zone in between – again in an historically significant sense, and here, according to the authors’ theory, exemplary sense, in the position of women in the patriarchal era, which was preceded by the reciprocal position of men – in their middle position between man as man and the unreasoning creature. The middle term is generally the schema. Schematism as a sensualization of the concept and as a logization of the sensual is interpreted in linguistic theory as an expression, with its two sides of the formative and the imprint, within our horizon, the epochal patriarchal horizon, and by virtue of the middle position of the woman between nature and man as man – of the woman as the “<em>mas occasionatus</em>”.<d-footnote>Thomas Aquinas, cited in: Horkheimer, The Critique of Instrumental Reason, p. 188.</d-footnote> The expressive character of language and the middle position of women equally become a test of the humanization of nature – within and through civilization.</p> <p>Oppressed for her part, woman has achieved “admission into the world of domination for all of exploited nature,” “but as a broken one.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 299.</d-footnote> She herself, and through her nature, “reflects to the victor his victory in spontaneous submission: defeat as surrender, despair as a beautiful soul, the violated heart as the loving bosom. At the price of a radical break from practice, at the price of retreating into a protected circle, nature receives its reverence from the Lord of Creation. Art, custom, sublime love,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote>beauty – “appearance of strength through weakness,”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 303.</d-footnote>thinking that is more than just ordering, speaking that is other than commanding and operationalizing; they all “are masks of nature,”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 299.</d-footnote>images<d-footnote>Cf. Ibid., p. 298.</d-footnote>“in which she returns transformed and becomes expressed as her own opposite. Through her masks she gains language,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote>and would therefore remain as mute without the mask as she would be unreadable without the image.</p> <p>This refers, historically and structurally, to the intermediate layer, that which mediates between nature and culture: the objective expression in a broad sense. This is illuminated by Benjamin’s idea that the ‘superstructure is an expression of the substructure’<d-footnote>Cf. Walter Benjamin: Das Passagen-Werk, in: Collected Writings, with the cooperation of TW Adorno and G Scholem, edited by R Tiedemann and Hermann Schweppenhäuser, Frankfurt am Main 1982, Band V, edited by R. Tiedemann, p. 573 f.</d-footnote>– ideology is objective appearance, manifestation in which what manifests becomes legible, understandable in the meaning of what is, ultimately, practical criticism of the relationship between the two. While that expression used to mean “not just beauty, but thought, spirit and language itself,” today “language” is something that tends to only “calculate, designate, reveal, and murder” – “it no longer expresses.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 302.</d-footnote> This is analogous to thinking, the spirit, which lost the power of self-illumination – in linguistic theory, the sense of expression – with the reduction to the instrumental, that of self-preservation;<d-footnote>“‘What we call ‘sense’ will disappear.’ Conversation with Max Horkheimer”, in: Der Spiegel, year 1970, No. 1/2.</d-footnote>lost in the double meaning of a loss of the possibility of understanding oneself as expression, and thus of giving this loss expression.</p> <p>While expression was once “vicarious suffering” – in the dimension of historical reflection of nature – this dimension shrinks to that of playing “with horror itself”;<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 302 f.</d-footnote>that of the ideology that has slipped into the base. “Nature” becomes “ruin. Only the sophisticated force that survives is right. It is nature herself – the entire sophisticated machinery of modern industrial society is just nature tearing itself apart. There is no longer any medium that expresses this contradiction. It takes place with the stubborn seriousness of the world from which art, thought, and negativity have disappeared.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 304.</d-footnote>“What is dangerous to the prevailing practice is not nature, with which it actually coincides, but rather that nature is remembered.”<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 305.</d-footnote> Wherever this still happens, the effort of thinking finds expression for it, it proves the counterforce, however precarious, against that disappearance of expression. It must prove itself, on a knife’s edge, as an effort of interpretation – methodologically speaking, as a theory of expression in the decided sense that its expressive characters themselves become the key to its theoretical purpose: its ‘knowledge interested in emancipation’. One of the keys is the concept of expression as a mask.</p> <p>The mask is not what hides, but conversely what reveals; ‘the being appears in the distortion.’<d-footnote>Ibid., p. 298.</d-footnote> This is the objective meaning of the expression, which remains obscured in the widely used concept of expression by the subjective meaning, which is precisely the accidental one, and which has had the most fatal effect in the misinterpretation of critical theory that supposedly corrects it or dismisses it as an expressive-aesthetic capitulation of thought. What is in the subjective expression, the accidental expression: imprint and form: in the subject and its expressive person, character mask in the strictly objective sense of the critique of political economy; what is <em>in sensu stricto</em> expression in the work, thing, product, artifact, be it a commodity, an aesthetic structure or an historical influence of whatever kind<d-footnote>“Value transforms […] every product of labor into a social hieroglyph.” Karl Marx: Capital, edited by Karl Korsch, Vol. I, Berlin 1932, p. 86.</d-footnote>– deciphering and fathoming this constitutes the effort of theory, of philosophy as interpretation, of a materialistic hermeneutics that unravels and reads the features, the traces, the engravings, the ciphers in the historically concrete,<d-footnote>Cf. Theodor W. Adorno: “The Idea of Natural History”, in: Collected Works, edited by R. Tiedemann, Frankfurt am Main 1973, Band I, p. 345 ff.</d-footnote>translates the silent language of nature and, with the translation, makes it a speaking one. Translated according to the way in which we make a foreign language eloquent in our own, precisely by preserving its signature, the thing -foreign to us, its character external, which we work on and which enriches our own language, so that with it something different, real – not just in nuance but in historical substance – emerges in the language we speak; provided that we are serious about translating.<d-footnote>Cf. Walter Benjamin: “The Task of the Translator”, in: Collected Writings, with the collaboration of TW Adorno and G Scholem, edited by R Tiedemann and Hermann Schweppenhäuser, Volume IV, edited by T Rexroth, Frankfurt am Main 1972, p. 9 ff.</d-footnote></p> <p>Through the problem of translation, we experience the double-sidedness of language itself: as an inner fluid medium of communication and comprehensibility – as meaning – and as an outer hard signature, as writing that has to be laboriously spelled out – as a meaning that has to be unraveled. At the same time, it becomes clear what a utopia of language would be: the Pentecost miracle of communication, in which comprehensibility and meaning merged – the hard idiomatic ciphers, whether mnemonic-intoned or hieroglyphic-silent, would be dissolved in the liquid medium of meaning. It would be the utopia of the name: the substantial unity of meaning and sign, ultimately of subject and object themselves, as both authors extrapolate in several places and with changing emphasis; the unity blocked by the given reality and from which something penetrates into the given reality as if through cracks. People have tried to interpret it as a secretly operating telos with all the effort of knowing, speaking and interpreting. In the Babylonian world of languages and ciphers, of gestures and signs, of symbols and signatures, which seal an internal sense within themselves and which cannot interpret themselves, it is the language of humanity that can unseal and help to understand the sealed meaning of the silent languages: provided that it is inherent in its own expressive character and thus in the schema mediating it and the foreign, the silent expressions.</p> <p>It is the prerequisite of historically developed language, in which receptivity to matter and nature is, at the same time, receptivity to the thinking that grasps the difference of itself from matter and nature, an opposition each side developed themselves – a language that historical people shaped, just as they are shaped by it, which they use and which at the same time uses them, thereby revealing to them the purpose of its use in the light of which they think, speak and act. Only an un-mutilated language can provide the interpretative scheme that conveys the internally speaking, trans-lingually silent expressions – to which the un-mutilated human language itself belongs, in one element, and to the mutilated language, in its entirety – with the concept, its other element -, and makes this un-mutilated language readable, understandable: knowable in the light of rationality. To make it knowable then also means to become mature – the conceptual language itself is made mature: mature nature through the expression of women, the oppressed, art, protest and thought: mature through the man and the woman, the mature human being to be produced <em>in sensu stricto</em>, that is, the one who only emerges in the perspective of developed language.</p> <p>The language-concept of critical theory aims at nothing more and nothing less, which may only now be ‘pragma-linguistically reformulated’. If this means seriously humanizing procedural questions that are committed to language and thinking and critically substantiating ‘internal differentiations’, critical theory can put up with it. Internal differentiations – the progression of determinate negation – which affect the attitude of knowledge, the use of language, and restructuring of practical behavior are in the spirit of critical theory. But if we mean the concept and procedures of speaking and thinking that are already affected in their core by reduced forms and standards, operations and procedures, with which they obey prevailing rationality and irrationality, and which, despite all the effort, lose the distinction between criticism and enforcement of that order, the desideratum is absurd. The weight of the objection, which accuses critical negation of the denunciation of consent, is, in fact, too heavy. “What connects people, when language designates the universal, is not so much that they allow themselves to be grasped again in their thoughts by the universal by which they are grasped in reality, but that they say what has power over all. In such a function, language alone shakes the walls between people, behind which the identical is distorted into the equality of the mutilated, into the uniformity of the dominated.”<d-footnote>Horkheimer, “Trust in History”, p. 14.</d-footnote></p> <p>If the discourse in communication should not postpone communication <em>ad Calendas Graecas</em>, should not pile up the ramparts instead of shaking them, communication in the function of the language that Horkheimer speaks of would have to prove itself in view of the procedures that are supposed to guarantee it in the first place – breaking down the consensus for the sake of language, rather than breaking language down for the sake of the consensus; this is also relevant for the idea of “communicative action”, which as a “theory” admits the antinomy in which emphatic practice remains entangled beyond recognition in the era of monopoly. “Blocked” at the point of knowability – but only if language, the expression of shared suffering, is what makes it knowable. If harmony is an illusion thrown over real contradictions, reconciliation is only indicated in the denunciation of harmony. That such denunciation becomes incomprehensible – in the double meaning of the offensive and the unclear articulation, which is summarized in the accusation of the unreasonable – is itself only the intelligibility, or index, of the expression of common suffering; of the identical distorted “into the sameness of the mutilated, into the uniformity of the dominated.”</p> <p>Adorno exemplified the plight of responsible expression, which turns people against expression for the sake of the causes of people: “Language, as an expression of things, is not absorbed in communication, in communicating to others. But it is not entirely independent of communication. Otherwise it evaded any criticism of its relationship to the matter and reduced it to arbitrary pretense. Language as an expression of the thing and language as a message are interwoven. The ability to name the thing itself was formed by the compulsion to pass it on and preserves it, just as, conversely, it could not communicate anything that it did not have as its own intention, undistracted by further consideration. Such dialectics take place in its own medium and is not just the fall from grace as it is called by the inhumane social zealotry that ensures nothing is thought that cannot be communicated. Even the most honest linguistic procedure cannot eliminate the antagonism between in-itself and for-others. This is made more difficult by the historical moment, in which the communication dictated by the market – symptomatically the replacement of linguistic theory by communication theory – places such a burden on language that, in order to resist the conformity of what positivism calls ‘everyday language’, it inevitably terminates communication.”<d-footnote>Theodor W. Adorno: “Skoteinos or how to read”, in: Three Studies on Hegel, Frankfurt am Main 1963, p. 122 f.</d-footnote></p> <p>This is no less true in view of the regulated and purified languages – principally the systematized expressions or ‘grammars’ of social-natural currents and linguistic conventions in the form of their own purified, ‘transcendental’ norm, which brings them to their adequate concept -, such languages that rationalize the expression of ‘everyday life’, i.e. the complex of ‘system’ and ‘lifeworld’, in accordance with the overall social functionalization of the forms of existence and under their objective constraints. No expression can escape this compulsion; it itself also produces the termination of communication. It is the counter-reaction of expression that resists disappearing in the rationalized – a dialectical figure of speaking language against language, of holding on to its intention rather than its silence. Both authors have stuck to it, trusting in a language in which thought and expression are not cut off by language. The medium of such a language, threatened internally and externally – and never historically unthreatened -, was the medium from which both minds wrested expression – the one that things and people long for and which they always persistently refuse in the state of bewitchment between language and things.</p> <h3 id="iii">§III.</h3> <p>Finally, let me point out some questions of linguistic presentation induced by this visualization of the language problem and how their overcoming is attempted in the oeuvre of both authors. – One of the initial conditions, as mercilessly imposed on thinking and formulating by the era, is the silent contradiction of the present, roughly – and increasingly – in the form that “the entire sophisticated machinery of modern industrial society is just nature” that is “tearing itself apart.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 304.</d-footnote> Muteness would have to be given expression. But that expression would not be a saying, not a formula – not the name that can be found “in isolated words and sentences,”<d-footnote>Horkheimer, Critique of Instrumental Reason, p. 167.</d-footnote>which the diverse new irrationalism nevertheless believes itself to be in possession of with all its powerless and suggestive gestures of incantation (linguistic ones above all). The expression sought is rather the “knowledge” that has been bored into individual realities through “conscious effort” and connected “into a linguistic structure.”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> The effort of thinking, working through the matter itself, and differentiating predication receptive to language are all intertwined, so that every moment of the articulation process is present with the others and through them, the context can be called knowledge, the knowledge an expression of what has been known: the “right name” of things.<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote> It would be a piece of developed truth, and not simply a given one – it would be the truth that can be put together from right names, that is, only negatively, with undistracted intention. We are not allowed to say the absolute positively – the individual in its historical determination, in the “predicament of nature,”<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote>the deteriorization reflected thereby, the limited and oppressed, misery and need themselves, which point beyond themselves, remain to be addressed by the right name, which is nothing other than the expression of the limited in the light of its pointing beyond itself.</p> <p>If it is to be heard, ‘adequate description’ is indispensable – the micrological, physiognomizing process that does not grasp something linguistically until it has been grasped by it and it by language. Formulation, the expression of thinking, depends in what it says on the person who is thinking about it. This only succeeds if formulation, language <em>in actu</em>, gives in to the trait of language through which it is a “presentation,”<d-footnote>Adorno, Negative Dialectics, quoted from: Tiedemann, p. 69.</d-footnote>a representation of what is said in it. It is no coincidence that both authors used the idiom of dialectical philosophy and theory – the most reflective, most advanced – especially in Hegel’s thought, the problem of language becomes apparent: <em>thinking, contemplation, presenting, the expressive power of language, differentiating, negating predication</em>, all of which constitute the theory in its medium, form the elements of its own theoretical articulation. With that idiom they learned what logical negation is in its linguistic manifestation: specifically, the objection, contradiction, that the subject contributes, and that in the objective, factually determined sense in which dialectics is called ‘organized spirit of contradiction’.</p> <p>But what is organized can also be explained by the linguistic means through which the objection occurs – specifically by the canon of forms that a developed language provides and which is differentiated beyond any theoretical idiom in the narrower sense; being found also in literary ones, which can only appear untheoretical due to the cultural division of labor, but not in terms of the matter itself, the authentic expression – just as, conversely, theory and philosophy appear to be completely separated from the sphere of expression. Precisely for the sake of the matter itself, for the sake of expression, both authors did not respect the industrial-intellectual division of labor and made use of that differentiated canon of forms; such specific forms of expression of the European Enlightenment, whose name says what has not expired – but then also forms such as the essay, aphorism and fragment, polemic and dialogue, the sober presentation with the power of revealing objections, the ur-philosophical gesture, of standing firm in the name of the truth and of forcing those who continue to talk and argue to pause. An appeal is made by force of the matter itself: an accusation in which the complaint of the oppressed is intended to be made clear.</p> <p>In this sense, one could say that the authors’ texts simulate speech in writing – a model of communication that is intended to ensure binding, authenticity by force of the matter itself, through writing, communication and understanding. If the style – the linguistic physiognomy of thinking devoted to the matter itself – is criticized for what is incomprehensible about Adorno’s expression, then this is precisely due to the fact that today speech and counter-speech, hearing and being heard, the illuminating and penetrating form of conversation itself, are disappearing socially – and with it also the metamorphosis of such speech and counter-speech, the form of reading with its susceptibility to the readability of the unwritten – and that therefore the character of such speech simulated in writing can no longer be identified. The situation is similar with the brittle texture of Horkheimer’s texts – apart from those that followed the common speech of empirical people divided according to subjects, departments and interests, which spoke to the hidden community within them and in which he was master. Those other texts of Horkheimer’s with such brittle texture, a kind of severe dispensation, the shortest connection between the thought and the thing, which leaves no room for linguistic excess – primarily terminological and methodological – on the one hand and for factual pedantry on the other; the sober, unvarnished, even merciless nature of these texts, which Schmidt emphasized in the structure of later writings,<d-footnote>Schmidt: “Max Horkheimer’s Spiritual Physiognomy”, p. 111</d-footnote>repels casual reception no less than the conceptual-linguistic expressive movement of the differential transitions in Adorno.</p> <p>In either case, it requires perseverance and listening to a theorist who thought with his ears: for both of them a concentrated receptivity, which in turn helped them to get to the bottom of things. Both theorists – in view of the patterns that appear before their listening, reading, speaking and thinking, which increasingly sink into each theorist until they take their place – harbored no illusions about the addressee, and, indeed, spoke first of all to imaginary recipients of the text, those imaginary readers who alone have remained the potential readers because the text before them is readable to them; those who can still absorb the text and the speech made objective by it, and as long as other people like themselves have not disappeared. The dialectic in objectification itself provides hope. The all-objectifying violence of the process also delivers the instruments of objectification to everyone: “Language, weapons, machines,” “which should seize everyone,” “must allow themselves to be seized by everyone.”</p> <p>In this way, the element of rationality asserts itself in domination as something different from it. The objectivity of the means, which makes it universally available, its ‘objectivity’ for everyone, implies the criticism of domination, as the means of which thought arose” – still in the late, concessionless thought of each theorist.<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, p. 51.</d-footnote> If the writing preserves it, in the distance between the text and the speech that speaks in it, seemingly inhumanely, in a concentrated manner, then it keeps people bound through opening this distance. Readers retaliate badly – giving in to “equalizing ideology that everyone understands because they don’t think anything of it,”<d-footnote>Max Horkheimer: Critical Theory. A Documentation, edited by A Schmidt, Band II, Frankfurt am Main 1968, p. 199.</d-footnote>and in which the idea of the “dependence of all conditions controllable by man on real agreement” disappeared<d-footnote>Ibid. p. 198.</d-footnote>– to the thought of independents, to which these poorly- or mis-understood texts testify. If these texts are written in the unwavering thought of ‘real democracy and association’, in the awareness of the “degree of development of socialization” that is only laboriously obscured by the pseudo-democratic forms,<d-footnote>Ibid.</d-footnote>hen this is precisely why their appeal should not go unnoticed by those who have gained a piece of freedom, however precarious. Using those texts on the path of least resistance – that of a freedom to one’s own lack of freedom -, means to give in to the resistance that lives in those rigorous texts. For their part, such texts express an objectively possible change for the better. According to the old word, writing is the grave of speech, from which it remains to be resurrected – in communication. And so it would be, if it were brought to life through the historical sense that writing preserves in terms such as <em>communio, the Commune, and communism as the kingdom of freedom</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name>James Callahan</name></author><category term="translation"/><category term="language"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An essay by Hermann Schweppenhäuser on the concept of language and linguistic presentation in Horkheimer and Adorno.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Help for the Helpless Teddie’s Music Theory of Communism, A Prelude</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/help_for_the_helpless/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Help for the Helpless Teddie’s Music Theory of Communism, A Prelude"/><published>2024-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/help_for_the_helpless</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2024/help_for_the_helpless/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post3-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <blockquote> <p>Horses are survivors / of the age of heroes.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Adorno, In Search of Wagner (Verso, 2005), epigraph.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>But Wagner’s music knows more about this than do his words… The feverish passages in Act III of <em>Tristan</em> contain that black, abrupt, jagged music which instead of undermining the vision unmasks it. Music, the most magical of all the arts, learns how to break the spell it casts over the characters. When <em>Tristan</em> curses love, this is more than the impotent sacrifice offered up by rapture to asceticism. It is the rebellion—futile though it may be—of the music against the iron laws that rule it, and only in its total determination by those laws can it regain the power of self-determination. It is not for nothing that those phrases in the <em>Tristan</em> score which follow the words ‘that potion so dread’ stand on the threshold of modern music in whose first canonic work, Schoenberg’s F# minor quartet, we find the words, ‘Take love from me, give me your happiness!” They mean love and happiness are false in the world in which we live, and that the whole power of love has passed over into its antithesis. Anyone able to snatch such gold from the deafening surge of the Wagnerian Orchestra, would be rewarded by its altered sound, for it would grant him that solace which for all its rapture and phantasmagoria, it consistently refuses. By voicing the fears voicing of helpless people, it could signal help for helpless, however feebly and distortedly. In doing so it would renew the promise contained in the age-old protest of music: the promise of a life without fear.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Ibid., 144–45.</p> </blockquote> <p>Adorno’s scathing Versuch über Wagner begins with an enigmatic epigraph, printed beneath a comparably incongruous dedication to his wife, Gretel; the epigraph reads: “Horses are survivors/of the age of heroes.” The essay concludes with a similarly mysterious and tender claim that if a listener can steal gold from the phantasmagoric rapture of the Wagnerian orchestra, then they might discover the orchestra’s transformed sound gives voice to “the fears of helpless people” and in turn reasserts music’s primordial protest: <em>Ohne Angst Leben</em> (“life without fear”). My principal aim is this introduction is simply to clarify these final three words of the Wagner essay—<em>Ohne Angst Leben</em>—and in doing so shed some light on the equine beginning.<d-footnote>Although the epigraph was not included in the original 1939 Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung essay, “Fragmente über Wagner,” it first appeared in a 1937 essay of aphorisms about music called “Motifs,” which can be found in Quasi una fantasia. In Eros and Civilization, Marcuse cites the last words of the Wagner essay, translated as “to live without anxiety,” as encapsulating what he calls the Great Refusal: “the protest against unnecessary repression, the struggle for the ultimate form of freedom.” (149–150).</d-footnote></p> <p>Very briefly, and so somewhat abstractly, here’s the connection between the ending and the epigraph. The idea is perhaps easiest to approach by way of the virtuosic finale of the “Color” chapter, where Adorno concludes that the crowning paradox of the many paradoxes that comprise “the existence of art in high capitalism” is that art critiques reification via its reification. We are not yet in a position to analyze the particulars of the “Color” finale, but to put its concluding claim in general terms: only by virtue of the social process of music’s rationalization and objectification as autonomous art alienated from social function does music have the capacity to give voice to the victims of the mastery and mutilation of nature under capitalism. And insofar as capitalist society, as Adorno often remarks elsewhere, is a form of life dominated by the “reality principle” of anxious “self-preservation,” where everything in nature is reduced to “something desired, something socially useful, something by which human beings may profit,” the giving of voice to suppressed nature gives form to a “pictureless picture” of utopia, a glimpse of happiness beyond capitalist self-preservation <em>in negative form</em>—in short, a conceptless concept of a life without fear.<d-footnote>Aesthetics, e.g., 14–15 and 27. “Some Ideas on the Sociology of Music,” 11.</d-footnote>What does this have to do with horses? Brünnhilde’s horse, Grane, who Brünnhilde rides into the fire at end of the heroic age, insisting it should repress its fear and “neigh with joy as it leaps into the flames,”<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 135.</d-footnote>is a memory of nature in its mutilated form, the same sort of trace a thinking listener might wrest from the third act of <em>Tristan</em> upon entering the hidden abode of Wagnerian musical production.<d-footnote>For a different approach to the epigraph in the Wagner essay, see Peter E. Gordon, “Wounded Modernism: Adorno on Wagner.” The different isms in our respective titles index the differences in approach, which I hope to further clarify in expansions of this preliminary work.</d-footnote>The horse helps us overcome our “muteness,” as it once did, since it knows what we don’t: that we too belong to the world of victims from which we flee. <d-footnote>In “Motifs,” Adorno writes, “For the horse knows more about heroes than they do themselves. Horses are the survivors from the age of heroes: they appear as if the very first words had been addressed to them, so that those who have been made victims might struggle free from the condition of muteness. It is the only animal for which we feel no disgust, and hence the only one we should not eat, if we do not wish to regress to a pre-linguistic age.” It is said that the last Berlin Philharmonic performance in April 1945 concluded with this scene with this scene from Götterdämmerung, after which boys from the Hitler Youth handed out cyanide.</d-footnote></p> <p>A more concrete rendering of the trajectory from the beginning to the end of the Wagner essay lies in an extended, musically specific account of the paradox sketched above. When it comes to music, the term “autonomy” points to a number of different social processes with different histories, histories which Adorno often only gestures toward with a word or two. First off, “autonomy” refers to the liberation of music not only from the archaic social functions of dance and ritual but also from the medieval social functions of court and church. Autonomy, then, means the bourgeoisification of music, which entailed, among many other developments, the emergence of a public, mediated by various industries, which consumed musical works at concert halls. By the later nineteenth century, a German who could afford the price of a ticket might find himself seated in a darkened hall listening to a wordless composition that was meant to be an event in its own right, demanding listeners suspend all other activities for an extended period of practical quiescence and focus not just on the sensual stimuli but on grasping those stimuli as a spiritual whole at a distance from empirical immediacy. The spiritual object of music in this case is functionless or useless, in the sense that it is not for worshipping, for dancing, or even for setting a convivial mood, but meant to be appreciated for its own sake. This is precisely how Kant describes liking for beauty, as opposed to liking for agreeableness or liking for goodness. When we judge an object as beautiful, according to Kant, we are saying that we perceive in the object formal purposiveness without external purpose, and Kant calls this formal purposiveness without external purpose “disinterested pleasure,” that is, a pleasure that is not directed at the practical aspects of self-preservation and the mastery of nature.</p> <p>And here we return to an aspect of the paradox of art under “high capitalism,” as Adorno sees it. By virtue of its isolation from social function and its nonidentity with sensuous, empirical reality, the artwork adopts a polemical stance not only against capitalism, insofar as accumulation requires that products of labor are salable and therefore objects of utility, but also against the whole of enlightenment, rationalization, and the mastery of nature. As Adorno states:</p> <blockquote> <p>For in empirical reality—that is to say, the world in which we live as active, “practical” people, pursue goals, use other people to achieve goals, and commit God knows what other atrocities—this world is indeed ruled by the reality principle, the principle that one behaves in such a way as to master this reality as comprehensively as possible. And the behavior of art is fundamentally a negation of this reality principle—fundamentally in the sense that it constitutes a sphere whose ambition is essentially to be the semblance and the representation of a total area that is certainly independent from the reality principle, and hence an area one cannot “get something out of” in the same practical sense as with most things in this world. And when people invoke the liberating quality that inheres in art… it is far more probably because art promises through its mere existence to exempt us from the omnipotence of that same reality principle, the omnipotence of a mechanism of self-preservation at the expense of everything else that exists in the world. This is, of course, closely connected to the fact that great art… could be said to stand with victims… and that what calls from works of art is in fact always the voice of the victim, and that there is no art which cannot truly do this</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Adorno, Aesthetics, 48.</p> </blockquote> <p>So on the one hand, the bourgeois artwork, by virtue its functionlessness, protests against capitalism and the reality principle’s drive toward the mastery of nature, which in Adorno’s thinking are both historically and socially coterminous and not.<d-footnote>“The Odyssey is already Robinsonade.” Dialectic of Enlightenment, 48.</d-footnote>And on the other hand, the cost of this protest is that music cannot take on a positive role in changing the world, that it cannot satisfy immediate desire. All of which is to say that the artwork gives form to what Adorno calls the antimony between the moral and the aesthetic, to the conflict between the aim to do good in the world and the intolerability of the world as it is.<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 120–121.</d-footnote></p> <p>Let me reformulate this paradox of art in slightly less deflating terms, since Adorno emphasizes that it is productive in the sense of transforming ideology into truth and is therefore not bereft of desire exactly. The artwork’s isolation from society is, as Adorno writes, a function of the “social structure” of “the bourgeois consciousness of freedom” and the capitalist division of labor—even in extreme cases of “totally unproductive,” radically autonomous music-making, like that of Adorno’s beloved Internationale <em>Gesellschaft für Neue Musik</em>, where concert tickets were “furnished to the audience gratis.”<d-footnote>Aesthetic Theory, 225–26; “On the Social Situation of Music,” 420.</d-footnote>Which is to say that an artwork’s autonomy character is a sort of fetish, the semblance of freedom from a society that is its origin and that constitutes a “nexus of guilt” to which “nothing stands external.”<d-footnote>Aesthetic Theory, 227.</d-footnote>As Adorno writes in his unfinished swan-song, <em>Aesthetic Theory</em>, “The absolute artwork converges with the absolute commodity.<d-footnote>Aesthetic Theory, 21. Stewart Martin is principally responsible for drawing attention to this particular sentence of Aesthetic Theory. See Martin, “The Absolute Artwork Meets the Absolute Commodity.”</d-footnote>”And it is precisely in this convergence that the reversal of ideology into truth occurs. Insofar as the absolute artwork is functionless, it shape-shifts into the absolute commodity qua pure “exchange-value” divorced from use; and this shapeshifting, Adorno writes, reveals a truth about the commodity form in its twofold reality, that it “pretends to exist for-another [but is ironically] something merely for-itself: It exists for those who hold power.”<d-footnote>Aesthetic Theory, 236.</d-footnote>So it is precisely by virtue of its uselessness that the artwork makes manifest the truth of how “stunted” use-value is in capitalism, not only insofar as it is a vanishing moment of blind accumulation but also because the whole of nature (including us) is pressed into “the service of usefulness to the exploiters.”<d-footnote>“Theses on Need.”</d-footnote></p> <p>This late account in <em>Aesthetic Theory</em> is clearly prefigured in the finale of <em>Wagner‘s</em> “Color” chapter and its elaboration in the “Phantasmagoria,” “Music Drama,” and “Myth” chapters. The former introduces the idea that (1) the commodity form has reshaped the artwork, insofar as artistic satisfaction requires the concealment of the signs of the work that produces it, and that (2) only through the distortions of the commodity form does the artwork have the ability to speak the truth of the commodity form’s subterfuge—its effacing of the signs of work that produce it for the sake of obscuring the exploitative class structure of commodity-producing labor. According to Adorno, Wagner attempts “to escape the market requirements of the commodity known as opera” and is thereby driven “more deeply into the commodity.”<d-footnote>In Search Wagner, 71.</d-footnote>Oddly enough, only the word “escape” possibly suggests a crime, since, as we just learned, no artwork is innocent of commodity fetishism, meaning no artwork is any more guilty of fetishism than any other product in the “universally socially mediated world.”<d-footnote>Aesthetic Theory, 227.</d-footnote></p> <p>Indeed, Adorno strongly praises Wagner’s orchestration technique, which “represents the victory of reification in instrumental practice,” as Wagner’s principal musical innovation, inasmuch as it equally signals “victory over conventional schemes of every kind.”<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 71, 60.</d-footnote> All of which is to say that Wagner’s reified instrumentation practice, in which sound is made “absolute” and the “traces of its production have been removed,” is of course no crime, since the paradox of music under high capitalism is that it critiques reification precisely by means of this reification. Adorno is certainly not suggesting that Wagner should have spurned his own innovations and anachronistically embraced a Mozartian style, for as Adorno indicates, the principle that Wagner actualizes in his orchestration was already present in Mozart’s doublings at the unison and octave.<d-footnote>Ibid., 70–1.</d-footnote></p> <p>As becomes clearer in the succeeding chapters, Wagner’s musical crime is neither resistance to market pressures nor the convergence of his art with the commodity, but that he tries to escape the commodity form in ways that redouble its deceptions—he has lost his “good conscience” in the bourgeois fetishization of art but responds by fetishizing art anew. Wagner’s rebellion, Adorno emphasizes, is a “bad infinity” that lacks any “authentic dialectical interaction”<d-footnote>Ibid., e.g., 47 and 40.</d-footnote>—it is a betrayal of the dream of happiness contained in the rebellion. By attempting to heroically dereify his art, Wagner only intensifies the spell of reification. His music thus anticipates the illusory character of the commodities produced by the culture industry in the twentieth century. Indeed, Adorno sees Wagner’s phantasmagoric <em>Zukunftsmusik</em> as the matrix in which the commodity art of the future grows: “the magic work of art dreams its complete antithesis, the mechanical work of art.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 98.</d-footnote></p> <p>Of course, it’s not just the neutralization of music’s protest against the commodity form that is the issue, but rather how this neutralization, which seems to undergird all Wagner’s musical procedures as much as his words, instantiates the core dynamic of a meretricious romantic anti-capitalism which bespeaks the bourgeois revolution and Nazism as well as a pessimism more “dubious” than Schopenhauer’s.<d-footnote>Ibid., 132.</d-footnote>At the core of this dynamic is something akin to the dialectic of enlightenment described by Adorno and Horkheimer in their Odysseus excursus: “self-preservation destroys that very thing which is to be preserved” at the moment humans “cut themselves off from the consciousness of themselves as nature” and thereby “[enthrone] the means as the end, which in late capitalism is taking on the character of overt madness.”<d-footnote>Dialectic of Enlightenment, 42–3. That excursus ends with a reflection on the phrase “not for long” from this sentence from Book XXII of the Odyssey, describing the hanging of maidservants for harlotry: “For a little while their feet kicked out, but not for long.” That analysis, both in form and content, bears certain similarities to the ending of the Wagner essay, which I bring up to further highlight how much of the Wagner essay material anticipates Adorno’s later work.</d-footnote>It’s clear enough in the first chapter of the Wagner essay that in the whole of Wagner’s life and art, from the moment of <em>Rienzi</em> to that of the <em>Ring</em>, rebellion takes the form of purifying “integration” rather than of class conflict, and defines itself in natural or biological terms rather than historical or social ones, such that it ultimately serves terroristic domination rather than the freedom it purports to. But the transformation of this initial formulation at the conclusion of the essay is more obscure, even as the themes of false identity, false reconciliation, and bad infinity return throughout. In the analysis of the <em>Ring</em> in the concluding chapters, Adorno reframes the betrayal immanent to Wagnerian resistance, writing, “The dominion over nature and subjugation to nature are one and the same.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 126.</d-footnote>He seems to in part mean that the rebel’s wish to exit “the nexus of social guilt” for the “asocial innocence” of nature is a further act of domination over nature, insofar as it presents nature as “unmutilated” and therefore further represses the oppression, fear, and pain whose source it is trying to escape, replacing “compassion” with an exculpating but freedomless “total determinism.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 120 and 135.</d-footnote></p> <p>We have come quite a way, as far as most go, but still not far enough, because we have not yet arrived at an account of the dialectic of rationality and nature that is most applicable to the conclusion of the Wagner essay and most central to Adorno’s aesthetic theory. And in order to do so, we need to move beyond an “external” and “reproductive” relation to music and move into the hidden abode of musical production, specifically, the internal development of the music’s objective technical aspects. Indeed, Adorno strongly rejects Kant’s “castrated hedonism” and “aesthetic subjectivism,” where pleasure is disinterested and beauty is defined as a mere effect on the subject. Instead he embraces a more Hegelian “objectivism,” which takes as its starting point Hegel’s definition of beauty (“the sensuous appearance of the idea”) and locates musical meaning in the immanent dynamics of the musical material itself.<d-footnote>On the rejection of Kant’s aesthetics, see both Aesthetic Theory, 11 and his lectures on aesthetics.</d-footnote>As Adorno points out, this materialism is historically appropriate, since “the absurd situation” in which art increasingly finds itself, “[searching] for meaning in its materials where it says something without knowing what to say,” expresses “the current state of the world with absolute purity.”<d-footnote>Aesthetics, 72.</d-footnote></p> <p>As music in Europe isolates itself from society, it develops an internal history of its own that replicates the social totality and its core dynamics. In other words, we find in music, as Jameson puts it with his usual charm, “a tiny history of inventions and machines” redolent of “the larger world of business and industry”—that is, a history of the development of instruments and techniques for the sake of the control of the musical material, the control of nature.<d-footnote>Jameson, Marxism and Form, 14. Jameson does not elaborate the dialectic of enlightenment aspect of my account. That can be found, for instance, in Adorno, Aesthetics, 51–52 and Adorno, “Some Ideas on the Sociology of Music.”</d-footnote>According to Adorno, Wagner’s relation to the mastery of the musical material is both progressive and regressive. A conductor concerned with the effect of his music on an increasingly inattentive public, Wagner, we are told, constructed his music around the static repetition of allegorical leitmotivs—discrete theme-like units akin to “advertising slogans.” As a result, he “softened up” the “musical logic” embedded in the material of his epoch and regressed to a gesticulating, pre-linguistic mimesis without entirely sloughing off quasi-linguistic elements, “rather the way agitators substitute linguistic gestures for the discursive exposition of their thoughts.”<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 24.</d-footnote>In contrast to the motivic development Beethoven’s sonatas and symphonies, Adorno writes, the stasis of Wagner’s leitmotiv technique “revokes [time],” creating “a state of immutability that refutes all history by confronting it with the silence of nature” and thereby consecrating “everything that is insufferable in the actual social reality from which [Wagner’s] work seeks to flee.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 30. </d-footnote>But insofar as the regressive element of the musical material raised the problem of generating the required allegorical meaning of the leitmotivs through the “developing sequence” technique, it also placed demands on Wagner to develop a progressive harmonic practice. In brief, Wagner’s harmonies sometimes, particularly in <em>Tristan</em>, break free of the conventional diatonic system based on the bourgeois symmetry of dissonance and consonance or tension and resolution, anticipating Schoenberg’s free atonality and 12- tone technique.</p> <p>The function of this antinomy of progress and regression within the Wagner essay is not as obvious as it may seem. Adorno judges the quality and truth of artworks produced after Beethoven, when the idea of human autonomy hardened into a defense of heteronomous class society, by virtue of how precisely they give form to capitalism’s irreconcilable antagonisms—the actual and the possible, the particular and the universal, subject and object. And in much of the “Motiv” and “Sonority” chapters, one even gets the impression that the antinomic character of Wagner’s art speaks the truth of its historical moment. At the same time, Adorno emphasizes that Wagner’s music fails music when it endeavors to identify regressive elements with progress. This is perhaps most evident in the case of the <em>Gesamtkunstwerk</em>, where the rationalization of the musical material is curtailed by the regressive nature of the progressive formal aspirations. Like Horkheimer, Adorno often speaks of the irrational and mythic character of capitalist rationality—the blind, aimless way capitalist society reproduces itself, the way it makes the satisfaction of needs impossible by virtue of it how satisfies needs, and so on. But in the rejection of rationalization for nature, Adorno primarily sees reaction. As he writes in his 1932 essay “On the Social Situation of Music,” for example, “Class interests bring rationalization to a halt as soon as it threatens to turn against class conditions themselves.”<d-footnote>“On the Social Situation of Music,” 392.</d-footnote>At the end of the “Music Drama” chapter, Adorno makes what seems like a fairly straightforward political analogy along these lines, saying that in the production of the <em>Gesamtkunstwerk</em> Wagner fails “to enlist the rational control of the labor process in the cause of freedom.”<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 99.</d-footnote> In other words, by trying to singlehandedly unite poetry, theatre, and music into a seamless total artwork through an act of genius that repudiates specialization, Wagner produces a false whole that comes closest to the rationalization of technique only in his specialty of music. But even in the case of music, the exigencies of the <em>Gesamtkunstwerk</em> fracture it into the orchestra and <em>Sprechgesang</em> and precipitate a new division of labor “unprecedented in the history of music” (98). “A valid <em>Gesamtkunstwerk</em>, purged of its false identity,” Adorno writes to hammer-home the political analogy, “would have required a collective of specialist planners” (99). In short, Wagner’s progressive attempt to individually will into being an “irrational” and “undivided primordial world” (97), which paradoxically produces an even more rationalized division of labor than the one from which it sought to flee, stands opposed to a communist program of bringing reason into the world through planning.</p> <p>As I suggested above, however, the political implications of Adorno’s critique go beyond this fairly straightforward analogy. The rationalization of the musical material, as Adorno writes in his more comprehensive theorizing about art, gives voice to suppressed, mutilated nature, thereby impeding the sacrifice of particularity to universality in the dialectic of enlightenment. According to Adorno, art regresses into a sort of mythology, into “something blind and unilluminated,” when it fails to liberate itself from the heteronomy of nature, when it remains dependent on “some material that stands outside the artistic process as something… unpenetrated, and which exercises a power over humans that they perceive… as foreign, as other.”<d-footnote>Aesthetics, 51.</d-footnote>But when art liberates itself from nature through the technical domination of its materials, it gives voice to everything that falls victim to the process of rationalization, not only the “natural world mangled by humans” but also “the infinite abilities of humans themselves, such as all the abilities that were once mimetic abilities and which we perceive in ourselves only in scattered, fragmented state.” As Adorno writes, “one could say that art is an attempt to do justice to all that falls victim to this ongoing concept of control over nature, to give nature its due, albeit now for only a symbolic portion—namely the portion of memory, the memory of the suppressed, of that which becomes victim, and also the memory of all those internal human powers which are destroyed by this process of progressive human rationalization.”<d-footnote>Ibid., 47–8.</d-footnote> Wagner’s music fails music, then, to the extent that it tries to sever progress from the rationalization of its materials and thus victimizes the victims further. As the well-known critique of “blood and soil” anti-capitalism goes, trying to escape from the mutilating rationalization of capital by locating the progressive in the regressive only releases more mutilating rationalization. Giving voice to what rationalization represses requires progressive rationalization. Just as music critiques reification via reification, it critiques rationalization via rationalization.</p> <p>Let’s now return to the end of the Wagner essay, which is not exactly the dramatic change of course it is usually said to be. Indeed, once one is exposed to Adorno’s theory of music’s inner dialectic of enlightenment, it becomes clear just how many set-ups Adorno has planted.<d-footnote>To note only a few examples, principally from the “Color” chapter of Adorno’s Wagner: “And this remains true even when it gives expression to suffering” (71); ““But by the same token, the social isolation of the work of art from its own production is also the measure of tis immanent progress, that of its mastery of its own artistic material” (73); “The music leaves us in no doubt about this” (126).</d-footnote> Despite Wagner’s deceptions and failures, his music, by virtue of the fact that the introduction of the leitmotiv technique put further demands on him to rationally control the musical material, gives voice to mutilated nature, to the free play of dissonance outlawed by the tonal system. And in doing so, this music seems to provide both a negative image of and some justification for the political program that Adorno offers as an alternative to bourgeois nihilism—a form of sociality where nature need not be enlisted into usefulness for the sake of profit and a form of rationality that does justice to the otherness within it. In his Lectures on <em>Negative Dialectics</em>, Adorno says “the mental reflex” of “the mastery of nature” is “the principle of identity, by which I mean the intrinsic aspiration of all mind to turn every alterity that is introduced to it… into something like itself and in this way to draw it into its own sphere of influence.”<d-footnote>Lectures on Negative Dialectics, 9.</d-footnote> And as is well known, Adorno, in the final part of <em>Negative Dialectics</em>, says, “Auschwitz confirmed the philosopheme of pure identity as death.”<d-footnote>Negative Dialectics, 362.</d-footnote> In the last pages of the Wagner essay, Adorno seems to be saying that if one can listen with a certain kind of effort, then one might hear in the terror-filled life of self-preservation that leads to the gas chambers over and over again, the real possibility of a conflicting life without fear—in short, the sensual appearance of the idea and “what cannot be pinned down” within it.<d-footnote>“If you recall the arguments against basing theoretical aesthetics on natural beauty… you will not be able to shake off the feeling that a motif is at work here which is familiar to those who are acquainted with Hegel’s philosophy: the motif that the elusive, that which has not taken on fixed form, which has not been objectified in a certain sense in order to be reconciled with the living subject again after passing through its objectification—that, I mean to say, anything elusive or ephemeral means very little to this philosophy…. On the one hand, of course, this holds great power against the sentimentalism of a mere romantic mood, but… on the other hand, this fundamental stance against…the powerless in Hegel’s philosophy also sees the growth of that tendency which ultimately drew this philosophy as a whole too much onto the side of prevailing conditions. But with regard to art, or the question of beauty in general, it is undoubtedly the case that this very aspect of the elusive, the not-quite-graspable, that which cannot be pinned down, is its vital principle…. The progress made by Hegel… comes at thee price of an aspect one could almost call inartistic, a surplus of materiality which sometimes give rise to the suspicion that, for all its greatness, this philosophy of art has not, in fact, fully accessed the work of art itself, which consists precisely in this ephemeral element” (Adorno, Aesthetics, 23–4). Speaking of Hegel, this might be the time to clarify a possible link between the epigraph and the ending. Hegel’s lectures on aesthetics, which Adorno praises highly in his own aesthetics lectures, includes the following passage on the “Heroic Age” of Odysseus (who of course is also central to Dialectic of Enlightenment): “The means of satisfaction have not been degraded to a purely external matter; we see their living origin itself and the living consciousness of the value which man puts on them because in them he has things not dead or killed by custom, but his own closest productions” (Vol. 1, 260–61). This strikes me as another plausible source for the horse epigraph, insofar as it brings use-value into the equation—the horse is not just a survivor and therefore a memory of the mutilation of nature but also of the mutilation of the human relation to production and usefulness.</d-footnote></p> <p>To say art gives voice to mutilated nature is not to say that it is a “nature reserve” for our horses to roam. Adorno calls such a vision a “satanic parody of the establishment of art as a special area strictly separated from empirical reality.” In his explanation of what he means, Adorno speaks of a gifted “young Englishman” he “befriended” who wept regardless of what Adorno played for him at the piano. Adorno cites this kind of weeping, severed from the specificity of the musical material, as an example of the way music has become a receptacle for the affects capitalism represses—the crying, he says, has nothing to do with the particular material that triggers it, and so in this case, one is not so much giving voice to mutilated nature as further dominating it, sequestering it away from real life. Adorno describes this sort of engagement with music, where listening is severed from its material aspect, as indicative of the separation of work from leisure and the assignment of art to the latter. Music’s transformation into “something that absolves us from effort,” is also its transformation into a leisure activity for the sake of the reproduction of labor power.<d-footnote>Aesthetics, 183-7.</d-footnote></p> <p>Now it is perhaps a bit clearer why Adorno distinguishes aesthetic experience from both commodity consumption and immediately political music and also how he can claim a dialectical asceticism for art even as he rejects Wagner’s ascetic politics.<d-footnote>In Search of Wagner, 69.</d-footnote> According to Adorno, consumption of music, by its very structure, offers “culinary” pleasure, the attempt to extract enjoyment worthy of the money one pays for it, but not what Adorno calls “immanent recognition of the matter itself.”<d-footnote>Aesthetics, 189.</d-footnote> Such recognition is more giving than taking, Adorno says. Meanwhile, Adorno writes, “The agitatory value and therewith the political correctness of proletarian communal music is beyond question and only utopian idealistic thinking could demand in its place music internally suited to the function of the proletariat, but incomprehensible to [them].” Yet when such “music retreats form the front of direct action, where it grows reflective and establishes itself as an artistic form,” it fails to express the antinomies that would best serve proletarian practice, since its material has not been adequately rationalized.<d-footnote>“On the Social Situation of Music.” At this point one might be able to tell a history of jazz that Adorno was not able to tell in the 1930s, one based on the development of the material that unfolds in a way that is tantalizingly similar to European art music, beginning with the polyphony of New Orleans jazz and culminating with abstract and dissonant free jazz. The similarity in trajectories of material development poses interesting questions for the historical materialists about the artification and its retroactive force.</d-footnote> In this materialist criterion above all does Adorno see the possibility of a music that can think both the end of art and its beginning: “If classless society promises the end of art by sublating the tension between the actual and the possible, then at the same time it also promises the beginning of art, the useless [<em>das Unnütze</em>], whose intuition tends towards reconciliation with nature because it is no longer in the service of usefulness [<em>Nutzen</em>] to the exploiters.”</p> <hr/> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post4-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <hr/>]]></content><author><name>Zachary Loeffler</name></author><category term="write-up"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A brief introduction to the music theory of communism]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ZfS in English</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/ZfS/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ZfS in English"/><published>2023-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/ZfS</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/ZfS/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post2.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>The <em>Institut für Sozialforschung</em> under Horkheimer’s direction, insisted the <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em> (ZfS) remain a German-language periodical, both to preserve the humanist tradition in German culture in defiance of Nazism (against both the Nazi’s claims on and destruction of this culture) and to resist the pressure to publish in English – which IfS members felt with increasing intensity after the leading majority of their number had been forced into exile from Europe to America in a process beginning in 1933. Because the IfS maintained a Paris office throughout the 30’s to serve as a liaison with its publisher, <em>Librairie Felix Alcan</em>, the ZfS reflected growing ties between the IfS and French intellectual culture. Notable, consistent exception was made in the ZfS for French-language contributors for articles on sociology and the history of science (including figures such as Alexandre Koyre, Raymond Aron, and Raymond de Saussure). Further study of this all-too-often neglected relationship (and English translations from French contributors) should be a desideratum of future research on the history of the ZfS. The Paris office was closed at the outbreak of WWII and the IfS found an American publisher for its last few issues, renaming the journal “Studies in Philosophy and Social Science”. Under these new conditions, the ZfS published its first (primarily) English issue in 1939 (V.8; I.3), followed by the three English-language issues of its ninth, and final, volume before the journal was discontinued.<d-footnote>Jay, Martin. The Dialectical Imagination: A History of the Frankfurt School and the Institute of Social Research 1923-1950. Hieinemann. London. 1973. See the following passages: “In general, the Institut was not especially eager to jettison its past and become fully American. This reluctance can be gauged by the decision to continue using Felix Alcan as publisher even after leaving Europe. By resisting the entreaties of its new American colleagues to publish in America, the Institut felt that it could more easily retain German as the language of the Zeitschrift. Although articles occasionally appeared in English and French and summaries in those languages followed each German essay, the journal remained essentially German until the war. It was in fact the only periodical of its kind published in the language that Hitler was doing so much to debase. As such, the Zeitschrift was seen by Horkheimer and the others as a vital contribution to the preservation of the humanist tradition in German culture, which was threatened with extirpation. Indeed, one of the key elements in the Institut’s self-image was this sense of being the last outpost of a waning culture. Keenly aware of the relation language bears to thought. its members were thus convinced that only by continuing to write in their native tongue could they resist the identification of Nazism with everything German. Although most of the German-speaking world had no way of obtaining copies, the Institut was willing to sacrifice an immediate audience for a future one, which indeed did materialize after the defeat of Hitler. The one regrettable by-product of this decision was the partial isolation from the American academic community that it unavoidably entailed.” (pp. 39-40); And: “Before turning to the Institut’s analysis of American society, its history during the war must be brought up to date. With the expansion of fascism’s power in Europe and America’s entry into the war there came a general reorganization of the Institut’s institutional structure and a reevaluation of its goals. The French branch, the sole remaining Institut outpost in Europe at the outbreak of the war, was closed with the occupation of Paris in 1940. During the thirties, the Paris office had not only been a liaison with the Institut’s publishers and a source· of data for the Studien über Autorität und Familie, but also a link with the French academic and cultural community. Walter Benjamin was not the only contributor of articles to the Zeitschrift living in Paris. Other pieces were written by Celestin BougIe, Raymond Aron, Alexandre Koyre, Jeanne Duprat, Paul Honigsheim, Maxime Leroy, Bernard Groethuysen, and A. Demangeon. In 1938 BougIe was one of two distinguished European scholars to deliver a series of public lectures at the Institut’s New York branch (Morris Ginsberg was the other). Now the link was broken. In addition, the Librairie Felix Alcan could no longer continue to print the Zeitschrift. Instead, the Institut decided to publish in America the third section of the 1939 volume, which appeared in the summer of 1940. This necessitated a reversal of the Institut’s long-standing unwillingness to write in English. As Horkheimer explained in his foreword to the rechristened Studies in Philosophy and Social Science: Philosophy, art, and science have lost their home in most of Europe. England is now fighting desperately against the domination of the totalitarian states. America, especially the United States, is the only continent in which the continuation of scientific life is possible. Within the framework of this country’s democratic institutions, culture still enjoys the freedom without which, we believe, it is unable to exist. In publishing our journal in its new form we wish to give this belief its concrete expression.” (p. 167)</d-footnote></p> <p>The difficulty English-language readers face in attempting to read the ZfS in full is a direct consequence of the immanence of the ZfS to its historical context. This immanence has a double expression. On the one hand, these texts express the compulsion to which each individual theoretician was unavoidably and existentially subject in the total, global, unfolding social crisis from which their theorizing emerged. On the other, they express the freedom of critical reflection found in a collective project to win clarity without consolation out of and of this chaos. Each applies themselves, with all the rigors of their own discipline and in coordination with leading scholars in others, to the problem of determining the anti-social forms of 20th century capitalist society in the midst of cascading national-economic conflicts. Critical theory, conceived as “social research” (<em>Sozialforschung</em>), is comprehensive:</p> <blockquote> <p>The term ‘social research’ [<em>Sozialforschung</em>] does not claim to draw new boundary lines on the map of science, which, today, seems very questionable in any case. What is meant by [‘social research’] here is that investigations on the most diverse subject areas and levels of abstraction are held together by the intention that they should advance the theory of contemporary society as a whole. This unifying principle – according to which the individual investigations must be carried out with unconditional empirical rigor, but in view of a central theoretical problem – distinguishes the social research this journal offers from mere factual description as well as [theoretical] construction foreign to the empirical. [Social research] strives to understand the course of society as a whole and, therefore, presupposes that beneath the chaotic surface of events, there is a structure of powers at work – one which, available to the concept, can be known. In social research, history is not seen as the phenomenon of mere arbitrariness, but as a law-governed dynamic, and the knowledge of which is therefore science. Obviously, this depends in a particularly unique way on the development of other disciplines. To reach its goal, which is to comprehend the processes of social life according to the [highest] level of [theoretical] insight possible in its time, social research must endeavor to concentrate a range of specialist sciences on its [unifying] problem and evaluate them for its purposes.</p> </blockquote> <blockquote> <p>Max Horkheimer – Vorwort // ZfS vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages i – iv, 1932.</p> </blockquote> <p>For these theorists, the strictest scientific practice is, at most, right in a wrong world and, at best, makes itself obsolete by facilitating the emergence of a free, but fragile, world taking shape in the fight over real possibility: between the universal self-emancipation of each and all and the indefinite reign of empires under the rule of capital. Or, as the anti-capitalist, anti-fascist avant-garde of the ZfS would say: between socialism and barbarism. It is this that makes the ZfS an organon of <em>critical</em> theory.</p> <p>For this reason, the <a href="/people">editors</a> of the CTWG believe running the gauntlet of the ZfS as an evolving whole is a worthwhile aspiration for English-language social critics and theorists. To that end, this page is the beginning of a larger project to make the full catalogue of texts from the <em>Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung</em> (1932-1941), volumes 1-9, available in English. Almost all extant translations of articles from the first 8 volumes were translated and published decades after their initial appearance in the pages of the ZfS – and often only partially or individually, scattered across various periodicals, collections, book series, and websites over the course of the last half century. This page will be updated with further high-quality PDFs and scans of English-language translation of ZfS articles as soon as editors are able to acquire them. Any help in this process would be greatly appreciated.</p> <p>In the future, this project will include calls for translators to work with CTWG members on making more of the ZfS available in English than ever before.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="theoretical-foundations-of-the-zfs">Theoretical Foundations of the ZfS</h2> <ul> <li> <p>Leo Löwenthal. <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/lowenthal/1921/demonic.htm">The Daemonic: Concept of a Negative Philosophy of Religion</a> (1921). (<a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/leo-lowenthal-daemonic-1921.pdf">PDF back-up</a>)</p> </li> <li>Herbert Marcuse, <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">“Contributions to a Phenomenology of Historical Materialism”</a> (1928).<d-footnote>Herbert Marcuse. ,<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">Heideggerian Marxism</a>. Ed. R Wolin &amp; J. Abromeit. University of Nebraska Press. 2005. “Contributions to a Phenomenology of Historical Materialism” was first published in Germany as “Beiträge zu einer Phänomenologie des historischen Materialismus” in Philosophische Hefte 1 (1928): 45–68 and was subsequently republished in Marcuse’s Schriften 1 (Frankfurt: Suhrkamp, 1978), 347–84. It first appeared in English in Telos 4 (1969): 3–34. It has been newly translated here by Eric Oberle. “On Concrete Philosophy” originally appeared as “Über konkrete Philosophie” in Archiv für Sozialwissenschaft und Sozialpolitik 62 (1929): 111–20. It was subsequently republished in the Schriften, 385–406. It appears here in English for the first time in a translation by Matthew Erlin “On the Problem of the Dialectic” originally appeared as “Zum Problem der Dialektik.” Part 1 was published in Die Gesellschaft 7 (1930): 15–30 and part 2 was published in Die Gesellschaft 8 (1931): 541–57. Die Gesellschaft was the main theoretical organ of the German Social Democratic Party (spd) at the time and was edited by Rudolf Hilferding. The essay was subsequently republished in the Schriften, 423–44. It was first published in English translation (part 1 was translated by Morton Schoolman and part 2 by Duncan Smith) in Telos 27 (1976): 12–39. It has been retranslated here by John Abromeit.</d-footnote> <ul> <li><a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse_conrete.pdf">“On Concrete Philosophy”</a> (1929)</li> <li><a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">“On the Problem of the Dialectic”</a> (1930)</li> </ul> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer, <a href="https://crittheoryworkgroup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/a-new-concept-of-ideology-1930-1.pdf">“A New Concept of Ideology?”</a> (1930).<d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993. // Original Publication: “Ein neuer Ideologiebegriff?,” Grünbergs Archiv 15, no. 1 (1930).</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer, <a href="https://crittheoryworkgroup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/hork-bourg-phil-hist.pdf">“Beginnings of the Bourgeois Philosophy of History”</a> (1930).<d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993. // Original publication: Anfänge der bürgerlichen Geschichtsphilosophie (Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 1930)</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Erich Fromm, <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/fromm-1930-dogma-christ.pdf">“The Dogma of Christ”</a> (1930/1).<d-footnote>Transl. JL Adams. The dogma of Christ and other essays on religion, psychology and culture. New York, Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1963. // Original publication: Die Entwicklung des Christusdogmas.: Ein psychoanalytische Studie zur sozialpsychologischen Funktion der Religion. Vienna: Internationaler Psychoanalytischer Verlag, 1931</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer, <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/1931-pres-situ.pdf">“The Present Situation of Social Philosophy and the Task of an Institute for Social Research”</a> (1931).<d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993. (<a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/horkheimer/1931/present-situation.htm">Alternate link</a>). // Original publication: “Die gegenwärtige Lage der Sozialphilosophie und die Aufgaben eines Instituts für Sozialforschung,” Frankfurter Universitätsreden 27 (1931)</d-footnote></p> </li> <li>Theodor Adorno, <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno_actualityphilosophy-1.pdf">“The Actuality of Philosophy”</a> (1931).<d-footnote>Telos March 20, 1977 vol. 1977 no. 31 120-133.</d-footnote> <ul> <li><a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno_historynature.pdf">“Idea of Natural History”</a> (1932).<d-footnote>Adorno, Theodor W. (1984). The idea of natural history. Telos: Critical Theory of the Contemporary 1984 (60):111-24.</d-footnote></li> </ul> </li> <li>Herbert Marcuse, <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/9e/Marcuse_Herbert_Hegels_Ontology_and_Theory_of_Historicity.pdf">Hegel’s Ontology and the Theory of Historicity</a> (1932).<d-footnote>Transl. Seyla Benhabib. M I T Press. 1987. // Original Publication: Hegels Ontologie Und Die Grundlegung Einer Theorie der Geschichtlichkeit. V. Klostermann. (1932)</d-footnote> <ul> <li><a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">“New Sources on the Foundation of Historical Materialism”</a> (1932). <d-footnote>Herbert Marcuse. <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">Heideggerian Marxism</a>. Ed. R Wolin &amp; J. Abromeit. University of Nebraska Press. 2005. “New Sources on the Foundation of Historical Materialism” was first published as “Neue Quellen zur Grundlegen des Historischen Materialismus” in Die Gesellschaft 9 (1932): 136–74 and was subsequently republished in the Schriften, 509–55. It was first published in English in a translation by Joris de Bres in Studies in Critical Philosophy (London: New Left Review Books, 1972), 1–48. De Bres’s translation has been lightly revised by John Abromeit here to render it terminologically consistent with the other essays in the volume. “On the Philosophical Foundations of the Concept of Labor in Economics” was first published as “Über die philosophischen Grundlagen des wirtschaftswissenschaftlichen Begriff der Arbeit” in Archiv für Sozialwissenschaften und Sozialpolitik 69 (1933): 257–92 and was republished in the Schriften, 556–94. It was first published in English, translated by Douglas Kellner, in Telos 16 (1973): 9–37. It has been retranslated here by John Abromeit. Marcuse wrote one version of “German Philosophy, 1871–1933” (“Deutsche Philosophie im zwanzigsten Jahrhundert”) in French in 1934 when he was living in Geneva, Switzerland, just prior to his joining the Institute for Social Research and departing for the United States in June 1934. It has never been published before in any language; the manuscript is located in the Marcuse Archives in Frankfurt, catalogue number 0030.01. Ron Haas has translated the text from French into English here.</d-footnote></li> <li><a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">“On the Philosophical Foundations of the Concept of Labor in Economics”</a> (1933)</li> <li><a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/95/MARCUSE_Herbert_-_Heideggerian_marxism.pdf">“German Philosophy, 1871–1933”</a> (1934)</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-1-1932">Volume 1 (1932)</h3> <h4 id="issue-12-1932">Issue 1/2 (1932)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Bemerkungen über Wissenschaft und Krise // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 1 – 7, 1932. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">“Notes on Science and the Crisis”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1972). Critical theory: selected essays. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Erich Fromm – Über Methode und Aufgabe einer analytischen Sozialpsychologie // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 28 – 54, 1932. – English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/fromm-method-and-function.pdf">“The Method and Function of an Analytic Social Psychology: Notes on Psychoanalysis and Historical Materialism”</a> <d-footnote>Arato, Andrew &amp; Gebhardt, Eike (eds.) (1977). The Essential Frankfurt School Reader. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Leo Löwenthal – Zur gesellschaftlichen Lage der Literatur // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 85 – 102, 1932. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lowenthal-socio-of-lit-1932.pdf">“On Sociology of Literature”</a><d-footnote>L. Lowenthal. Literature and Mass Culture. Routledge. 1984.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Henryk Grossmann – Die Wert-Preis-Transformation bei Marx und das Krisenproblem // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 55 – 84, 1932. English – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/h-grossmann-value-price-crisis.pdf">“The Value-Price Transformation in Marx and the Problem of Crisis”</a>.<d-footnote>Grossman, H. (2016). The Value-Price Transformation in Marx and the Problem of Crisis. Historical Materialism, 24(1), 105-134.</d-footnote> (+ <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/r-kuhn-h-grossmann-vpt-intro.pdf">New introduction</a> by R Kuhn)<d-footnote>Kuhn, R. (2016). Introduction to Henryk Grossman, ‘The Value-Price Transformation in Marx and the Problem of Crisis’. Historical Materialism, 24(1), 91-103.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Theodor Wiesengrund-Adorno – Zur gesellschaftlichen Lage der Musik // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 103 – 124, 1932. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-social-situ-music-32-1.pdf">“On the Social Situation of Music”</a><d-footnote>Adorno, Theodor W. (1978). On the Social Situation of Music. Telos: Critical Theory of the Contemporary 35:129.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Geschichte und Psychologie // vol. 1, no. 1/2, pages 125 – 144, 1932. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/history-and-psychology-1932-2.pdf">“History and Psychology”</a><d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1932">Issue 3 (1932)</h4> <ul> <li>Erich Fromm // Die psychoanalytische Charakterologie und ihre Bedeutung für die Sozialpsychologie – vol. 1, no. 3, pages 253 – 277, 1932. – English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/characterology-essay.pdf">“Psychoanalytic Characterology and Its Relevance for Social Psychology”</a><d-footnote>Fromm, Erich. The Crisis of Psychoanalysis: Essays on Freud, Marx and Social Psychology. 1st ed. Newburyport: Open Road Distribution, 2014. Print.</d-footnote></li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-2-1933">Volume 2 (1933)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1933">Issue 1 (1933)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Materialismus und Metaphysik // vol. 2, no. 1, pages 1 – 33, 1933. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">“Materialism and Metaphysics”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1972). Critical theory: selected essays. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Leo Löwenthal – Conrad Ferdinand Meyers heroische Geschichtsauffassung // vol. 2, no. 1, pages 34 – 62, 1933. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/cfm-essay.pdf">“Conrad Ferdinand Meyer: An Apologia of the Upper Middle Class”</a><d-footnote>Lowenthal, L. (1980). Conrad Ferdinand Meyer: An Apologia of the Upper Middle Class. Telos: Critical Theory of the Contemporary 1980 (45):97-113.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1933">Issue 2 (1933)</h4> <ul> <li>Max Horkheimer – Materialismus und Moral // vol. 2, no. 2, pages 162 – 197, 1933. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-materialism-and-morality-2.pdf">“Materialism and Morality”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1986). Materialism and morality. Telos: Critical Theory of the Contemporary 1986 (69):85-118.</d-footnote> (<a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/mat-moral-2.pdf">Alternate English translation</a>)<d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-3-1934">Volume 3 (1934)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1934">Issue 1 (1934)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Zum Rationalismusstreit in der gegenwärtigen Philosophie // vol. 3, no. 1, pages 1 – 53, 1934. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/rationalism-debate-1.pdf">“The Rationalism Debate in Contemporary Philosophy”</a><d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Walter Benjamin – Zum gegenwärtigen gesellschaftlichen Standort des französischen Schriftstellers // vol. 3, no. 1, pages 54 – 78, 1934. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/benjamin-present-social-situation-of-the-french-writer-1934-1.pdf">“The Present Social Situation of the French Writer”</a><d-footnote>Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, Volume 2, Part 2: 1931-1934, eds. Michael W. Jennings, Howard Eiland and Gary Smith, 1999; 2005</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Pauline V. Young – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/pauline-young-delinquent.pdf">Differentiation of Delinquent and Non-Delinquent Boys</a> // vol. 3, no. 1, pages 79 – 81, 1934.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1934">Issue 2 (1934)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – Der Kampf gegen den Liberalismus in der totalitären Staatsauffassung // vol. 3, no. 2, pages 161 – 195, 1934. – English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/5/57/Marcuse_Herbert_Negations_Essays_in_Critical_Theory_2009.pdf">“The struggle against liberalism in the totalitarian view of the state”</a> <d-footnote>Marcuse, Herbert (1968). Negations: essays in critical theory. London: Free Association Books.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Erich Fromm – Die sozialpsychologische Bedeutung der Mutterrechtstheorie // vol. 3, no. 2, pages 196 – 227, 1934. – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/mother-right-theory-soc-psych.pdf">“The Theory of Mother Right and its Relevance for Social Psychology“</a><d-footnote>Fromm, Erich. The Crisis of Psychoanalysis: Essays on Freud, Marx and Social Psychology. 1st ed. Newburyport: Open Road Distribution, 2014. Print.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1934">Issue 3 (1934)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Zu Bergsons Metaphysik der Zeit // vol. 3, no. 3, pages 321 – 342, 1934. English <a href="https://www.radicalphilosophy.com/article/on-bergsons-metaphysics-of-time">“On Bergson’s Metaphysics of Time”</a></p> </li> <li> <p>Leo Löwenthal – Die Auffassung Dostojewskis im Vorkriegsdeutschland // vol. 3, no. 3, pages 343 – 382, 1934. – English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lowenthal-dostoyevsky.pdf">“The Reception of Dostoevsky in Pre-World War I Germany”</a><d-footnote>L. Lowenthal. Literature and Mass Culture. Routledge. 1984.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-4-1935">Volume 4 (1935)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1935">Issue 1 (1935)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Bemerkungen zur philosophischen Anthropologie // vol. 4, no. 1, pages 1 – 25, 1935. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/remarks-on-phil-anthro-1.pdf">“Remarks on Philosophical Anthropology”</a><d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>K. A. Wittfogel – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/kaw-stages-of-chines-econ-history.pdf">The Foundations and Stages of Chinese Economic History</a> // vol. 4, no. 1, pages 26 – 60, 1935.</p> </li> <li> <p>Charles A. Beard – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/ca-beard-socsci-us.pdf">The Social Sciences in the United States</a> // vol. 4, no. 1, pages 61 – 65, 1935.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1935">Issue 2 (1935)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Henryk Grossmann – Die gesellschaftlichen Grundlagen der mechanistischen Philosophie und die Manufaktur // vol. 4, no. 2, pages 161 – 231, 1935. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/h-grossmann-social-found.pdf">“The Social Foundations of the Mechanistic Philosophy and Manufacture”</a><d-footnote>Grossmann, Henryk (2009). The social foundations of the mechanistic philosophy and manufacture. In Boris Hessen, Henryk Grossmann, Gideon Freudenthal &amp; Peter McLaughlin (eds.), The Social and Economic Roots of the Scientific Revolution: Texts by Boris Hessen and Henryk Grossmann. Springer.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Walter Benjamin – Probleme der Sprachsoziologie // vol. 4, no. 2, pages 248 – 268, 1935. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/benjamin-problems-in-the-sociology-of-language-1935-1.pdf">“Problems in the Sociology of Language“</a><d-footnote>Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, Volume 3, 1935-1938, eds. Howard Eiland and Michael W. Jennings, 2002; 2006.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1935">Issue 3 (1935)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Zum Problem der Wahrheit // vol. 4, no. 3, pages 321 – 364, 1935. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/on-the-problem-of-truth-1.pdf">“On the Problem of Truth“</a><d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Erich Fromm – Die gesellschaftliche Bedingtheit der psychoanalytischen Therapie // vol. 4, no. 3, pages 365 – 397, 1935. English <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/fromm-soc-det-psych-therapy.pdf">“Social Determinants of Psychoanalytic Therapy“</a><d-footnote>Int Forum Psychoanal 9:(149-165), 2000</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-5-1936">Volume 5 (1936)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1936">Issue 1 (1936)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – Zum Begriff des Wesens // vol. 5, no. 1, pages 1 – 39, 1936. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/5/57/Marcuse_Herbert_Negations_Essays_in_Critical_Theory_2009.pdf">“The Concept of Essence”</a><d-footnote>Marcuse, Herbert (1968). Negations: essays in critical theory. London: Free Association Books.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Walter Benjamin – L’œuvre d’art à l’époque de sa reproduction mécanisée // vol. 5, no. 1, pages 40 – 68, 1936. English: “The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction.” <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/benjamin-wamr-2nd.pdf">Second Version</a> (basis for the first version published, abridged and in French, in the ZfS)<d-footnote>Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, Volume 3, 1935-1938, eds. Howard Eiland and Michael W. Jennings, 2002; 2006.</d-footnote>; <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/benjamin-wamr-3rd.pdf">Third Version</a> (revised through 1939, the basis of the 1955 publication in Benjamin’s Schriften)<d-footnote>Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, Volume 4, 1938-1940, eds. Howard Eiland and Michael W. Jennings, 2003; 2006.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Margaret Mead – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/m-mead-zfs.pdf">On the Institutionalized Rôle of Women and Character Formation</a> // vol. 5, no. 1, pages 69 – 75, 1936.</p> </li> <li> <p>Hilde Weiss – <a href="https://notesfrombelow.org/article/hilde-weiss-die-enquete-ouvriere-von-karl-marx-193">Die “Enquête Ouvrière” von Karl Marx</a> // vol. 5, no. 1, pages Pages 76-98, 1936.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1936">Issue 2 (1936)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Egoismus und Freiheitsbewegung: Zur Anthropologie des bürgerlichen Zeitalters // vol. 5, no. 2, pages 161 – 234, 1936. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-egoism-freedom-movements-1.pdf">“Egoism and Freedom Movements: On the Anthropology of the Bourgeois Era”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1982). Egoism and the Freedom Movement. Telos: Critical Theory of the Contemporary 54:10.</d-footnote>(<a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/egoism-freedom-2.pdf">Alternative English translation</a>)<d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Hektor Rottweiler (Adorno) – Über Jazz // vol. 5, no. 2, pages 235 – 259, 1936. English – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-on-jazz.pdf">“On Jazz“</a><d-footnote>Theodor W. Adorno and Jamie Owen Daniel Discourse Vol. 12, No. 1, A Special issue on Music (Fall-Winter 1989-90), pp. 45-69</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-6-1937">Volume 6 (1937)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1937">Issue 1 (1937)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Der neueste Angriff auf die Metaphysik // vol. 6, no. 1, pages 4 – 53, 1937. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">“The Latest Attack on Metaphysics”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1972). Critical theory: selected essays. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – Über den affirmativen Charakter der Kultur // vol. 6, no. 1, pages 54 – 94, 1937. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/5/57/Marcuse_Herbert_Negations_Essays_in_Critical_Theory_2009.pdf">“On the Affirmative Character of Culture”</a><d-footnote>Marcuse, Herbert (1968). Negations: essays in critical theory. London: Free Association Books.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Paul F. Lazarsfeld – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lazarsfeld-typology.pdf">Some Remarks on the Typological Procedures in Social Research</a> // vol. 6, no. 1, pages 119 – 139, 1937.</p> </li> <li> <p>Otto Neurath – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/o-neurath-standard-of-living.pdf">Inventory of the Standard of Living</a> // vol. 6, no. 1, pages 140 – 151, 1937.</p> </li> <li> <p>David Efron , John P. Foley, Jr. – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/gbss.pdf">Gestural Behavior and Social Setting</a> // vol. 6, no. 1, pages 152 – 161, 1937.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1937">Issue 2 (1937)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Traditionelle und kritische Theorie // vol. 6, no. 2, pages 245 – 294, 1937. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">“Traditional and Critical Theory”</a><d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1972). Critical theory: selected essays. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Leo Löwenthal – Knut Hamsun: Zur Vorgeschichte der autoritären Ideologie // vol. 6, no. 2, pages 295 – 345, 1937. – English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lowenthal-knut-hamsun.pdf">“Knut Hamsun”</a><d-footnote>Arato, Andrew &amp; Gebhardt, Eike (eds.) (1977). The Essential Frankfurt School Reader. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Walter Benjamin – Eduard Fuchs, der Sammler und der Historiker // vol. 6, no. 2, pages 346 – 381, 1937. English: <a href="https://files.libcom.org/files/Eduard%20Fuchs,%20Collector%20and%20Historian%20-%20W.%20Benjamin%201937_0.pdf">“Eduard Fuchs: Collector and Historian”</a><d-footnote>Benjamin, Walter, and Knut Tarnowski. “Eduard Fuchs: Collector and Historian.” New German Critique, no. 5, 1975, pp. 27–58.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>C. M. Bowra – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/bowra-socio-grk-poetry.pdf">Sociological Remarks on Greek Poetry</a> // vol. 6, no. 2, pages 382 – 399, 1937.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1937">Issue 3 (1937)</h4> <ul> <li>Max Horkheimer , Herbert Marcuse – Philosophie und kritische Theorie // vol. 6, no. 3, pages 625 – 647, 1937. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">Horkheimer</a> (“Postscript”)<d-footnote>Horkheimer, Max (1972). Critical theory: selected essays. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote>; <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/5/57/Marcuse_Herbert_Negations_Essays_in_Critical_Theory_2009.pdf">Marcuse</a>(“Philosophy and Critical Theory”)<d-footnote>Marcuse, Herbert (1968). Negations: essays in critical theory. London: Free Association Books.</d-footnote></li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-7-1938">Volume 7 (1938)</h3> <h4 id="issue-12-1938">Issue 1/2 (1938)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Montaigne und die Funktion der Skepsis // vol. 7, no. 1/2, pages 1 – 54, 1938. English: <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/montaigne-skepticism.pdf">“Montaigne and the Function of Skepticism”</a><d-footnote>Between Philosophy and Social Science. Selected Early Writings – Max Horkheimer. Translated by G. Frederick Hunter, Matthew S. Kramer, and John Torpey. M I T Press 1993.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – Zur Kritik des Hedonismus // vol. 7, no. 1/2, pages 55 – 89, 1938. English: <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/5/57/Marcuse_Herbert_Negations_Essays_in_Critical_Theory_2009.pdf">“On Hedonism”</a><d-footnote>Marcuse, Herbert (1968). Negations: essays in critical theory. London: Free Association Books.</d-footnote></p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1938">Issue 3 (1938)</h4> <ul> <li>T. W. Adorno – Über den Fetischcharakter in der Musik und die Regression des Hörens // vol. 7, no. 3, pages 321 – 356, 1938. English: <a href="https://fswg.files.wordpress.com/2015/02/on-the-fetish-character-in-music-and-the-regression-of-listening.pdf">“On the Fetish Character in Music and the Regression of Listening”</a><d-footnote>Arato, Andrew &amp; Gebhardt, Eike (eds.) (1977). The Essential Frankfurt School Reader. New York: Continuum.</d-footnote></li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-8-1939">Volume 8 (1939)</h3> <h4 id="issue-12-1939">Issue 1/2 (1939)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Walter Benjamin – Uber einige Motive bei Baudelaire // vol. 8, no. 1/2, pages 50 – 91, 1939. English: <a href="https://langurbansociology.files.wordpress.com/2013/01/benjamin-on-some-motifs-in-baudelaire.pdf">“On Some Motifs in Baudelaire”</a><d-footnote>Walter Benjamin: Selected Writings, Volume 4, 1938-1940, eds. Howard Eiland and Michael W. Jennings, 2003; 2006.</d-footnote></p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – Die Juden und Europa // vol. 8, no. 1/2, pages 115 – 137, 1939. English: <a href="https://thecharnelhouse.org/2015/03/20/the-jews-and-europe/">“The Jews and Europe”</a></p> </li> <li> <p>K. A. Wittfogel – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/wittfogel-prehistoric-china.pdf">The Society of Prehistoric China</a> // vol. 8, no. 1/2, pages 138 – 186, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="https://philpapers.org/archive/MARHMR.pdf">Review of John Dewey Logic, The Theory of Inquiry</a> // vol. 8, no. 1/2, pages 221 – 228, 1939.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1939">Issue 3 (1939)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-fw-v8-i3.pdf">Forward</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 321 – 321, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer –<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">The Social Function of Philosophy</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 322 – 337, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Franz L. Neumann – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/f-neumann-natlaw.pdf">Types of Natural Law</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 338 – 361, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-intro-to-hegel.pdf">An Introduction to Hegel’s Philosophy</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 394 – 412, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>T. W. Adorno – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-kierk-love.pdf">On Kierkegaard’s Doctrine of Love</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 413 – 429, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-psych-soc-dilthey-engl.pdf">The Relation between Psychology and Sociology in the Work of Wilhelm Dilthey</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 430 – 443, 1939.</p> </li> <li> <p>Otto Kirchheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/kirchheimer-criminal-law.pdf">Criminal Law in National-Socialist Germany</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 444 – 463, 1939.</p> </li> </ul> <h4 id="reviews">Reviews</h4> <ul> <li>Leo Lowenthal – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lowenthal-jung-review-integration.pdf">Reivew of Jung’s The Integration of the Personality</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 479 – 481, 1939.</li> <li>Frederick Pollock – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/pollock-review-v8-i3.pdf">Technological Trends and National Policy</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 483 – 490, 1939.</li> <li>Henryk Grossman – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/grossmann-review-v8-i3.pdf">Turning Points in Business Cycles</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 490 – 492, 1939.</li> <li>F. Weil – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/f-weil-v8-i3.pdf">The Coming Struggle for Latin America</a> // vol. 8, no. 3, pages 492 – 494, 1939.</li> </ul> <h3 id="volume-9-1941">Volume 9 (1941)</h3> <h4 id="issue-1-1941">Issue 1 (1941)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-v9-i1-preface.pdf">Preface</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 1 – 1, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Paul F. Lazarsfeld – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/lazarsfeld-remarks-v9-i1.pdf">Remarks on Administrative and Critical Communications Research</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 2 – 16, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>T. W. Adorno , George Simpson – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-simpson-pop-music.pdf">On Popular Music</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 17 – 48, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Harold D. Lasswell – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/hd-lass-radio.pdf">Radio as an Instrument of Reducing Personal Insecurity</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 49 – 64, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Herta Herzog – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/herta-herzog-radio.pdf">On Borrowed Experience: An Analysis of Listening to Daytime Sketches</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 65 – 95, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>William Dieterle – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/dieterle-hollywood.pdf">Hollywood and the European Crisis</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 96 – 103, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Charles A. Siepmann – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/siepmann-radio.pdf">Radio and Education</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 104 – 120, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-notes-on-institute-activities.pdf">Notes on Institute Activities</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 121 – 123, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p><a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/research-project-on-anti-semitism.pdf">Research Project on Antisemitism</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 124 – 143, 1941.</p> </li> </ul> <h5 id="reviews-1">Reviews</h5> <ul> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-rev-dewey-valuation.pdf">Review of Dewey’s Theory of Valuation</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 144 – 148, 1941.</li> <li>T. W. Adorno , Eunice Cooper – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-cooper-rev-of-jazz.pdf">American Jazz Music</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 167 – 178, 1941.</li> <li>Henryk Grossman – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/grossmann-business-cycles-rev.pdf">Business Cycles</a> // vol. 9, no. 1, pages 181 – 189, 1941.</li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-2-1941">Issue 2 (1941)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-pref-state-cap.pdf">Preface</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 195 – 199, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Frederick Pollock – <a href="https://platypus1917.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/12/pollock_statecapitalism.pdf">State Capitalism: Its Possibilities and Limitations</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 200 – 225, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>A. R. L. Guiland – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/gurland-tech-trends-v9-i2.pdf">Technological Trends and Economic Structure under National Socialism</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 226 – 263, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Otto Kirchheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/kirchheimer-political-compromise.pdf">Changes in the Structure of Political Compromise</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 264 – 289, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">Art and Mass Culture</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 290 – 304, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>T. W. Adorno – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-spengler.pdf">Spengler Today</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 305 – 325, 1941.</p> </li> </ul> <h5 id="reviews-2">Reviews</h5> <ul> <li>Felix Weil – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/f-weil-bottlenecks-business-rev.pdf">The Bottlenecks of Business</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 326 – 336, 1941.</li> <li>Henryk Grossman – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/gbss.pdf">The Output of Manufacturing Industries 1899-1937</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 352 – 354, 1941.</li> <li>Karl Korsch – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/korsch-armed-horde-rev.pdf">The Armed Horde 1793-1939: A Study of the Rise, Survival, and Decline of the Mass Army</a> // vol. 9, no. 2, pages 358 – 361, 1941.</li> </ul> <h4 id="issue-3-1941">Issue 3 (1941)</h4> <ul> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-preface-v9-i3.pdf">Preface</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 365 – 365, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Max Horkheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/horkheimer-end-of-reason.pdf">The End of Reason</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 366 – 388, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>T. W. Adorno – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-veblen-culture.pdf">Veblen’s Attack on Culture: Remarks Occasioned by the Theory of the Leisure Class</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 389 – 413, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="https://nissenbaum.tech.cornell.edu/papers/Socialimplicationsoftechnology.pdf">Some Social Implications of Modern Technology</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 414 – 439, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Frederick Pollock – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/pollock-nat-soc.pdf">Is National Socialism a New Order?</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 440 – 455, 1941.</p> </li> <li> <p>Otto Kirchheimer – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/kirchheimer-nat-soc.pdf">The Legal Order of National Socialism</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 456 – 475, 1941.</p> </li> </ul> <h5 id="reviews-3">Reviews</h5> <ul> <li>Paul Tillich <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/tillich-v9-i1.pdf">Reason and Revolution: Hegel and the Rise of Social Theory</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 476 – 478, 1941.</li> <li>T. W. Adorno – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-unmitt-v9.pdf">Unmittelbarkeit und Sinndeutung: Aufsätze zur Ausgestaltung des Systems der Philosophie</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 479 – 482, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-review-of-kleines-lehrbuch-and-russell.pdf">Kleines Lehrbuch des Positivismus</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 483 – 486, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-logic-lit-rev.pdf">The Problems of Logic</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 487 – 490, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-soc-psych-rev.pdf">Social Psychology of Modern Life</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 500 – 501, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-dante-phil-rev.pdf">Dante et la philosophie</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 512 – 513, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-italian-humanists.pdf">Adversity’s Noblemen: The Italian Humanists on Happiness</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 513 – 514, 1941.</li> <li>Henryk Grossman – <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/grossmann-hist-magic-sci.pdf">A History of Magic and Experimental Science</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 514 – 519, 1941.</li> <li>T. W. Adorno <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/adorno-life-of-wagner.pdf">The Life of Richard Wagner</a>, 1859-1866 // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 523 – 525, 1941.</li> <li>Herbert Marcuse <a href="/assets/pdf/zfs/marcuse-shall-not-perish.pdf">. . . Shall not Perish from the Earth</a> // vol. 9, no. 3, pages 531 – 531, 1941.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="archive"/><category term="study"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Collection of English translations of articles from the Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung (1932-1941), volumes 1-9.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Previous Sessions and Work</title><link href="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/previous_work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Previous Sessions and Work"/><published>2023-09-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/previous_work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ctwgwebsite.github.io/blog/2023/previous_work/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/post1-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/post1-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/post1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/post1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Outtake from the Erste Marxistische Arbeitswoche (1923) group photograph, in which almost everyone is trying to figure out what to do with their hands </div> <p>For the most recent updates on working group activities, check out the posts on our home page and our spring 2024 report <a href="/news/announcement_4">here</a>.</p> <h3 id="past-ctwg-reading-group-sessions-2023-2024">Past CTWG Reading Group Sessions (2023-2024)</h3> <p><strong>The Fight for the Dialectic of Enlightenment (Summer 2024):</strong> Link to the full schedule and reading list <a href="/news/announcement_3">here</a>.</p> <p>Recordings (uploaded as they are edited):</p> <ul> <li>June 1st, “Prefaces” to DoE. (James/Crane) <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/prefaces-to-doe-106806484">Recorded session here</a></li> <li>June 8th, “Concept of Enlightenment.” (James/Crane) <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/concept-of-6-8-110396854">Recorded session here</a></li> <li>June 15th, “Excursus I: Odysseus or Myth and Enlightenment.” (Mac Parker) <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/odysseus-6-15-107819849">Recorded session here</a></li> <li>June 22nd, “Excursus II: Juliette or Enlightenment and Morality” (Esther Planas Balduz) <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/6-22-excursus-ii-111666274">Recorded session here</a></li> <li>June 29th, “The Culture Industry: Enlightenment as Mass Deception” (Zachary Loeffler) <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/6-29-culture-as-113616865">Recorded session here</a></li> <li>July 6th, “Elements of Anti-Semitism: Limits of Enlightenment” (J.E. Morain)</li> <li>July 13th, “Notes and Sketches” (Group Presentation)</li> </ul> <p><strong>The Zeitschrift für Sozialforschung: Organon of Early Critical Theory (Fall/Winter 2023)</strong> Link to the full schedule and reading list <a href="/news/announcement_2">here</a></p> <p>Recordings:</p> <ul> <li>Discussion 1 – 11/25/23: <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/11-25-23-concept-93636285">On Marcuse’s “Concept of Essence” (1936) with Mac Parker</a></li> <li>Discussion 2 – 12/2/24: <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/12-2-24-new-of-100926227">On Horkheimer’s “A New Concept of Ideology?” (1930) with Sam Thomas</a></li> <li>Discussion 3 – 12/9/2024: <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/12-9-2024-essays-100927103">Horkheimer’s Materialism Essays (1933) with Esther Planas Balduz</a></li> <li>Discussion 4 – 12/16/2024: <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/12-16-2024-in-of-100927684">Adorno’s “In Search of Wagner” with Zachary Loeffler</a></li> </ul> <h3 id="preliminary-sessions-hosted-by-jamescrane-spring-fall-2023">Preliminary Sessions (Hosted by James/Crane) (Spring-Fall 2023)</h3> <p><strong>Self-Criticism and Historical Materialism (Early Fall 2023):</strong> Returning to Lukacs (<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/3/3b/Lukacs_Georg_History_and_Class_Consciousness_Studies_in_Marxist_Dialectics.pdf">“The Changing Function of Historical Materialism”</a> (1919); <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/3/3b/Lukacs_Georg_History_and_Class_Consciousness_Studies_in_Marxist_Dialectics.pdf">“What is Orthodox Marxism?”</a> (1919); <a href="https://files.libcom.org/files/georg-lukacc81cs-tactics-and-ethics-political-essays-1919-1929a.compressed.pdf">“Moses Hess and the Problems of Idealist Dialectics”</a> (1926)) and Korsch (<a href="https://ia801906.us.archive.org/2/items/karl-korsch-marxism-and-philosophy-marxismus-und-philosophie-marxismo-e-filosofi/Karl%20Korsch%2C%20Marxism%20and%20Philosophy%2C%20Marxismus%20und%20Philosophie%2C%20Marxismo%20e%20filosofia%2C%20Massimo%20Morigi%2C%20Repubblicanesimo%20Geopolitico%2C%20marxismo%20occidentale.pdf">“Marxism and Philosophy”</a> (1923); “Introduction to the Critique of the Gotha Program” (1922); “The Marxism of the First International” (1924)) for three weeks, focusing on how each argues – by reference to the concepts of totality and the unity of theory and practice – that Marxism is self-critical or it is nothing. We conclude with two weeks discussing the heterodox historical materialisms of Ernst Bloch (<a href="https://archive.org/details/TheSpiritOfUtopiaErnstBloch">The Spirit of Utopia</a> (1923): “Karl Marx, Death, and the Apocalypse”) and Walter Benjamin (<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/9/93/Benjamin_Walter_1934_1999_The_Author_as_Producer.pdf">“Author as Producer”</a> (1934); <a href="https://files.libcom.org/files/Eduard%20Fuchs,%20Collector%20and%20Historian%20-%20W.%20Benjamin%201937_0.pdf">“Eduard Fuchs: Collector and Historian”</a> (1937)). Link to the collection of recordings for this session on our Patreon <a href="https://www.patreon.com/collection/190928">here</a>.</p> <p><strong>Horkheimer’s Early (pre-40s) Historical Criticism (Late Summer 2023)</strong> Focusing on Horkheimer’s work in the 1930’s: “The Present Situation” (1931), “Traditional and Critical Theory” (1937) and its “Postscript” (1937) (<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">collected here</a>, in Critical Theory), Marcuse’s reply “Philosophy and Critical Theory” (1937) (<a href="https://monoskop.org/images/7/74/Horkheimer_Max_Critical_Theory_Selected_Essays_2002.pdf">collected here</a>, in Negations), and Horkheimer’s later reflection <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/horkheimer/1939/social-function.htm">“The Social Function of Philosophy”</a> (1939) (also collected in Critical Theory, link above). Our focus was on defining the concept of critical theory that Horkheimer develops in his writings in the 30’s – namely, Horkheimer’s argument that critical theory must be an extension of Marx’s critique of political economy into a comprehensive social theory. Rather than providing just another scientific paradigm for the explanation of social history, critical theory begins as a theory of the failure of modern social theories (whether speculative-metaphysical or empirical-scientific) to provide such a comprehensive social theory. (This is only Horkheimer’s point of departure. The core of his 30’s concept of critical theory is a careful combination of historical criticism and materialist logic.) Link to the collection of recordings for this session on our Patreon <a href="https://www.patreon.com/collection/190904">here.</a></p> <p><strong>Method and Science (1919-1931) in Marxian Social Criticism (Early Spring 2023).</strong> Focusing on Lukacs’ <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/lukacs/works/1919/orthomarx.html#:~:text=In%20Marxism%2C%20orthodoxy%20refers%20solely,the%20tradition%20of%20its%20founders.">“What is Orthodox Marxism?”</a> (1919), Korsch’s <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/korsch/1923/marxism-philosophy.htm">Marxism and Philosophy</a> (1923), and Horkheimer’s <a href="https://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/horkheimer/1931/present-situation.htm">“The Present Situation of Social Philosophy and the Tasks of an Institute for Social Research”</a> (1931). Our focus was on the theoretical practice of early, Marxian critical theory – the problem of Marxist ‘method’ after the critique of methodological formalism (Lukacs), the problem of ‘vulgar’ Marxism that pretends to the status of non-partisan social science (Korsch), and the interpenetration of social philosophy and empirical social science required by any critical theory of capitalist society (Horkheimer). Link to the collection of recordings for this session on our Patreon <a href="https://www.patreon.com/collection/190864">here.</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="first-post"/><category term="report"/><category term="session"/><category term="write-up"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Write-up of past reading group sessions]]></summary></entry></feed>